which is what we wanted to
prove.
Done.
OK, I'm getting more and more
excited as we get into the meat
of this proof.
Any questions so far?
Good.
Now comes the hard part.
These are both very easy
lemmas, right?
I'll use these two boards.
We don't need these proofs
anymore.
We just need these statements:
correctness one,
correctness lemma;
great names.
So, now finally we get to
correctness two.
So, we had one and one and a
half.
So, I guess correctness is,
itself, a mini-trilogy,
the mini-series.
OK, so correctness two says
when the algorithm is done,
we have the right answer.
This is really correctness.
But, it's going to build on
correctness one and correctness
lemma.
So, we want d of v to equal
delta of s, v for all vertices,
v at the end of the algorithm.
That is clearly our goal.
Now, this theorem is assuming
that all of the weights are
nonnegative, just to repeat.
It doesn't assume anything
else.
So, it's going to get the
infinities right.
But, if there are minus
infinities, all bets are off.
OK, even if there's any
negative weight edge anywhere,
it's not going to do the right
thing necessarily.
But, assuming all the weights
are nonnegative,
which is reasonable if they're
measuring time.
Usually it costs money to
travel along edges.
They don't pay you to do it.
But who knows?
So, I need just to say a few
things.
One of the things we've
mentioned somewhere along the
way is when you add a vertex to
S, you never change its weight.
OK, that actually requires
proof.
I'm just going to state it
here.
It's not hard to see.
d of v doesn't change.
OK, this is essentially an
induction once v is added to S.
OK, this will actually followed
by something we'll say in a
moment.
OK, so all I really care about
is when a vertex is added to S,
we better have the right
estimate because after that,
we're not going to change it,
let's say.
OK, we could define the
algorithm that way.
We are not, but we could.
I'll say more about this in a
second.
So, all we care about is
whether d of v equals delta of
s, v.
That's what we want to prove.
So, it's clearly that.
It should be true at the end.
But, it suffices to prove that
it holds when v is added to S,
to capital S.
OK, this actually implies the
first statement.
It has sort of a funny
implication.
But, if we can prove this,
that d of v equals delta of s,
v, when you add to S,
we know relaxation only
decreases value.
So, it can't get any smaller.
It would be from correctness
one.
Correctness one says we can't
get any smaller than delta.
So, if we get a quality at that
point, we'll have a quality from
then on.
So, that actually implies d of
v never changes after that
point.
OK, so we're going to prove
this.
Good.
Well, suppose it isn't true.
So this would be a proof by a
contradiction.
Suppose for contradiction that
this fails to hold.
And, let's look at the first
failure.
Suppose u is the first vertex
--
-- that's about to be added to
S.
I want to consider the time
right before it's added to S,
for which we don't have what we
want.
These are not equal.
d of u does not equal delta of
s, u.
Well, if they're not equal,
we know from correctness one
that d of E is strictly greater
than delta of s,
u, so, d of u.
So, we have d of u is strictly
greater than delta of s,
u.
OK, that's the beginning of the
proof, nothing too exciting yet,
just some warm-up.
OK, but this,
used already correctness one.
I think that's the only time
that we use it in this proof.
OK, so I sort of just want to
draw picture of what's going on.
But I need a little bit of
description.
So, let's look at the shortest
path.
Somehow, d of u is greater than
the shortest path.
So, consider the shortest path
or a shortest path.
Let p be a shortest path,
not just any shortest path,
but the shortest path from s to
u.
OK, so that means that the
weight of this path is the
shortest path weight.
So, we have some equations for
what's going on here.
So, we care about delta of s,
u.
Here's a path with that weight.
It's got to be one because
shortest paths exist here;
slight exceptional cases if
it's a plus infinity,
but I'm not going to worry
about that.
So, let me draw a picture
somewhere.
So, we have s.
We have u.
Here is the shortest path from
s to u.
That's p.
No idea what it looks like so
far.
Now, what we also have is the
notion of capital S.
So, I'm going to draw capital
S.
So, this is big S.
We know that little s is in big
S.
We know that u is not yet in
big S.
So, I haven't screwed up
anything yet,
right?
This path starts in S and
leaves it at some point because
until we are about to add u to
S, so it hasn't happened yet,
so u is not in S.
Fine.
What I want to do is look at
the first place here where the
path, p, exits S.
So, there is some vertex here.
Let's call it x.
There's some vertex here.
We'll call it y.
OK, possibly x equals S.
Possibly y equals u.
But it's got to exit somewhere,
because it starts inside and
ends up outside.
And it's a finite path.
OK, so consider the first time
it happens; not the second time,
the first.
OK, so consider the first edge,
(x,y), where p exits capital S.
The shortest path from s to u
exits capital S.
It's got to happen somewhere.
Cool, now, what do we know?
Little x is in S.
So, it has the right answer
because u, we were about to add
u to S, and that was the first
violation of something in S that
has the wrong d of x estimate.
So, d of x equals delta of s,
x.
Because we are looking at the
first violation,
x is something that got added
before.
So, by induction on time,
or because we had the first
violation, d of x equals the
shortest path weight from S to
x.
So, that's good news.
Now we are trying to apply this
lemma.
It's the only thing left to do.
We haven't used this lemma for
anything.
So, we have the setup.
If we already know that one of
the d values is the right
answer, and we relaxed the edge
that goes out from it,
then we get another right
answer.
So that's what I want to argue
over here.
We know that the d of x equals
this weight because,
again, subpaths of shortest
paths are shortest paths.
We have optimal substructure,
so this is a shortest path,
from S to x.
It might not be the only one,
but it is one.
So we know that matches.
Now, I want to think about
relaxing this edge,
(x,y).
Well, x is in capital S.
And, the algorithm says,
whenever you add a vertex,
u, to the big set,
S, you relax all the edges that
go out from there.
OK, so when we added x to S,
and we now look far in the
future, we're about to add some
other vertex.
Right after we added x to S,
we relax this edge,
(x,y), because we relaxed every
edge that goes out from x,
OK, whatever they were.
Some of them went into S.
Some of them went out.
Here's one of them.
So, when we added x to S,
we got XS.
When we added x to S,
we relaxed the edge,
(x,y).
OK, so now we're going to use
the lemma.
So, by the correctness lemma --
What do you get?
Well, we add this correct
shortest path weight to x now.
We relax the edge,
(x,y).
So, now we should have the
correct shortest path weight for
y.
d of y equals delta of s,
OK, this is sometime in the
past.
In particular,
now, it should still be true
because once you get down to the
right answer you never change
it.
OK, we should be done.
OK, why are we done?
Well, what else do we know
here?
We assumed something for
contradiction,
so we better contradict that.
We assume somehow,
d of u is strictly greater than
delta of s, u.
So, d of u here is strictly
greater than the length of this
whole path.
Well, we don't really know
whether u equals y.
It could, could not.
And, but what do we know about
this shortest path from S to y?
Well, it could only be shorter
than from S to u because it's a
subpath.
And it's the shortest path
because it's the subpath of the
shortest path.
The shortest path from S to y
has to be less than or equal to
the shortest path from S to u.
OK, S to y: less than or equal
to s, u, OK, just because the
subpath.
I'm closer.
I've got delta of s,
u now.
Somehow, I want to involve d of
u.
So, I want to relate d of y to
d of u.
What do I know about d of u?
Yeah?
d of u is smaller because we
have a Min heap,
yeah.
We always chose,
let's erase,
it's way down here.
We chose u.
This is the middle of the
algorithm.
It's the reason I kept this to
be the minimum key.
This is keyed on d.
So, we know that at this
moment, when we're trying to add
u to S, right,
y is not in S,
and u is not in S.
They might actually be the same
vertex.
But both of these vertices,
same or not,
are outside S.
We chose u because d of u has
the smallest d estimate.
So, d of y has to be greater
than or equal to d of u.
It might be equal if they're
the same vertex,
but it's got to be greater than
or equal to.
So, d of y here is greater than
or equal to d of u.
So, here we're using the fact
that we actually made a greedy
choice.
It's the one place we're using
the greedy choice.
Better use it somewhere because
you can't just take an arbitrary
vertex and declare it to be
done.
You've got to take the greedy
one.
OK, now we have d of u is less
than or equal to delta of s,
u, which contradicts this.
OK, sort of magical that that
all just worked out.
But sort of like the previous
proofs, you just see what
happens and it works.
OK, that's the approximation.
The only real idea here is to
look at this edge.
In fact, you could look at this
edge too.
But let's look at some edge
that comes from S and goes out
of S, and argue that while x has
to be correct,
and what we made x correct,
y had to be correct,
and now, why the hell are we
looking at u?
y is the thing you should have
looked at.
And, there you get a
contradiction because y had the
right answer.
If u equals y,
that's fine,
or if u and y were sort of
equally good,
that's also fine if all these
weights were zero.
So, the picture might actually
look like this.
But, in that case,
d of u is the correct answer.
It was delta SU.
We assumed that it wasn't.
That's where we're getting a
contradiction.
Pretty clear?
Go over this proof.
It's a bit complicated,
naturally.
OK, we have a little bit more
to cover, some easier stuff.
OK, the first thing is what's
the running time of this
algorithm?
I'll do this very quick because
we're actually seen this many
times before last class.
There was some initialization.
The initialization,
which is no longer here,
is linear time.
No big deal.
OK, extract Min.
Well, that's some data
structure.
So, we have something like size
of V.
Every vertex we extract the Min
once, and that's it.
So, size of V,
extract mins.
OK, so that's pretty simple.
OK, then we had this main loop.
This is a completely conceptual
operation.
S is not actually used in the
algorithm.
It's just for thinking.
OK, so this takes zero time.
Got to love it.
OK, and now the heart is here.
So, how many times does this
loop iterate?
That's the degree of u.
So, what is the total number of
times that we execute a
relaxation step?
It doesn't necessarily mean we
do this, but we at least execute
this body.
Over the whole algorithm,
how many times do we do this?
Every vertex,
we look at all the outgoing
edges from there.
So, the total would be?
Number of edges,
yeah.
So, this number of edges
iterations.
OK, this is essentially the
handshaking lemma we saw last
time, but for directed graphs.
And we are only looking at the
outgoing edges.
So, it's not a factor of two
here because you're only
outgoing from one side.
So, we have number of
reiterations.
In the worst case,
we do a decreased key for
everyone.
So, at most:
E decreased keys.
OK, so the time is,
well, we have v extract Mins,
so the time to do an extract
Min, whatever that is.
And we have E decreased keys,
whatever that is,
and this is exactly the running
time we had for Prim's algorithm
for a minimum spanning tree last
time.
And, it depends what data
structure you use,
what running time you get.
So, I'm going to skip the whole
table here.
But, if you use an array,
the final running time will be
V^2 because you have order of v
extract Min, and you have
constant time decreased key.
If you use a binary heap,
which we know and love,
then we have order log v for
each operation.
And so, this is V plus E log V.
And, so that's what we know how
to do.
And, if you use this fancy data
structure called a Fibonacci
heap, you get constant time
decreased key amortized.
And, you get an E plus v log v
worst case bound on the running
time.
So, this is the best we know
how to solve shortest paths
without any extra assumptions,
single source shortest paths
with non-negative edge weights
in general.
OK, this is almost as good and
this is sometimes better than
that.
But these are essentially
irrelevant except that you know
how to do these.
You don't know how to do a
Fibonacci heap unless you read
that in the chapter of the book.
That's why we mention the top
two running times.
OK, I want to talk briefly
about a simpler case,
which you may have seen before.
And so it's sort of fun to
connect this up to breadth first
search in a graph.
So, I mean that ends Dijkstra,
so to speak.
But now I want to think about a
special case where the graph is
unweighted, meaning w of (u,v)
equals one for all vertices,
u and v.
OK, suppose we had that
property.
Can we do any better than
Dijkstra?
Can we do better than this
running time?
Well, we probably have to look
at all the edges and all the
vertices.
So, the only thing I'm
questioning is this log v.
Can I avoid that?
I gave away the answer a little
bit.
The answer is called breadth
first search,
or BFS, which you have probably
seen before.
Next to depth first search,
it's one of the standard ways
to look at the graph.
But we can say a little bit
more than you may have seen
before.
Breadth for search is actually
Dijkstra's algorithm:
kind of nifty.
There are two changes.
First change is that breadth
for search does not use a
priority queue.
I'll just tell you what it uses
instead.
You can use a queue first in
first out honest-to-goodness
queue instead of a priority
queue.
OK, it turns out that works.
Instead of doing extract Min,
you just take the first thing
off the queue.
Instead of doing decreased key,
OK, here's a subtlety.
But, this if statement changes
a little bit.
So, here is the relaxation
step.
So, in order to relax,
you say this much simpler
thing.
If we haven't visited v yet,
then we declare it to have the
shortest path weight,
say, d of v is d of u plus one,
which is the weight of the
edge, (u,v).
And we add v to the end of the
queue.
So, now, we start with the
queue empty.
Actually, it will just contain
the vertex, S,
because that's the only thing
we know the shortest path for.
So, the queue is just for,
I know the shortest path of
this thing.
Just deal with it when you
can't look at all the outgoing
edges when you can.
So, initially that's just S.
You say, well,
for all the outgoing edges,
S has zero.
All the outgoing edges from
there have weight one.
The shortest path weight from
the source is one.
You certainly can't do any
better than that if all the
weights are one.
OK, so we add all those
vertices to the end of the
queue.
Then, we process things in
order, and we just keep
incrementing,
if their value is d of u,
add one to it.
That's d of v.
And then we are going to add v
to S what we get to it in the
queue.
OK, that is breadth for search,
very simple.
And, you can look at the text
for the algorithm and for an
example because I don't have
time to cover that.
But the key thing is that the
time is faster.
The time is order V plus E
because as before,
we only look at each edge once
we look at all the outgoing
edges from all the vertices.
As soon as we set d of v to
something, it will remain that.
We never touch it.
We are going to add it to S.
That only happens once.
So, this if statement,
and so on, in the in-queuing,
is done order E times,
or actually E times,
exactly.
An in-queuing to a queue,
and de-queuing from a queue,
that's what we use instead of
extract Min, take constant time,
so the total running time,
number of vertices plus the
number of edges.
OK, not so obvious that this
works, but you can prove that it
works using the Dijkstra
analysis.
All you have to do is prove
that the FIFO priority queue.
Once you know that,
by the correctness of Dijkstra
you get the correctness of
breadth for search.
So, not only is breadth for
search finding all the vertices,
which is maybe what you
normally use it for,
but it finds the shortest path
weights from S to every other
vertex when the weights are all
one.
So, there we go:
introduction to shortest paths.
Next time we'll deal with
negative weights.