we have plus h of v_1,
and minus h of v_k.
OK, those guys don't quite
cancel.
We're not looking at a cycle,
just a path.
And, this thing is just w of
the path, as this is the normal
weight of the path.
And so the change,
the difference between w_h of P
and w of P is this thing,
which is just h of u minus h of
v.
And, the point is that's the
same as long as you fix the
endpoints, u and v,
of the shortest path,
you're changing this path
weight by the same thing for all
paths.
This is for any path from u to
v, and that proves the theorem.
So, the one word here was
telescopes.
These change in weights
telescope over any path.
Therefore, if we want to find
shortest paths,
you just find the shortest
paths in this re-weighted
version, and then you just
change it by this one amount.
You subtract off this amount
instead of adding it.
That will give you the shortest
path weight in the original
weights.
OK, so this is a tool.
We now know how to change
weights in the graph.
But what we really want is to
change weights in the graph so
that the weights all come out
nonnegative.
OK, how do we do that?
Why in the world would there be
a function, h,
that makes all the edge weights
nonnegative?
It doesn't make sense.
It turns out we already know.
So, I should write down this
consequence.
Let me get this in the right
order.
So in particular,
the shortest path changes by
this amount.
And if you want to know this
value, you just move the stuff
to the other side.
So, we compute deltas of h,
then we can compute delta.
That's the consequence here.
How many people here pronounce
this word corollary?
OK, and how many people
pronounce it corollary?
Yeah, we are alone.
Usually get at least one other
student, and they're usually
Canadian or British or
something.
I think that the accent.
So, I always avoid pronouncing
his word unless I really think,
it's corollary,
and get it right.
I at least say Z not Zed.
OK, here we go.
So, what we want to do is find
one of these functions.
I mean, let's just write down
what we could hope to have.
We want to find a re-weighted
function, h, the signs of weight
to each vertex such that w_h of
(u,v) is nonnegative.
That would be great for all
edges, all (u,v) in E.
OK, then we could run Dijkstra.
We could run Dijkstra,
get the delta h's,
and then just undo the
re-weighting,
and get what we want.
And, that is Johnson's
algorithm.
The claim is that this is
always possible.
OK, why should it always be
possible?
Well, let's look at this
constraint.
w_h of (u,v) is that.
So, it's w of (u,v) plus h of u
minus h of V should be
nonnegative.
Let me rewrite this a little
bit.
I'm going to put these guys
over here.
That would be the right thing,
h of v minus h of u is less
than or equal to w of (u,v).
Does that look familiar?
Did I get it right?
It should be right.
Anyone seen that inequality
before?
Yeah, yes, correct answer.
OK, where?
In a previous lecture?
In the previous lecture.
What is this called if I
replace h with x?
Charles knows.
Good, anyone else remember all
the way back to episode two?
I know there was a weekend.
What's this operator called?
Not subtraction but,
I think I heard it,
oh man.
All right, I'll tell you.
It's a difference constraint,
all right?
This is the difference
operator.
OK, it's our good friend
difference constraints.
So, this is what we want to
satisfy.
We have a system of difference
constraints.
h of V minus h of u should be,
we want to find these.
These are our unknowns.
Subject to these constraints,
we are given the w's.
Now, we know in these
difference constraints are
satisfiable.
Can someone tell me when these
constraints are satisfiable?
We know exactly when for any
set of difference constraints.
You've got to remember the
math.
Terminology,
I can understand.
It's hard to remember words
unless you're a linguist,
perhaps.
So, when is the system of
different constraints
satisfiable?
All right, you should
definitely, very good.
[LAUGHTER] Yes,
very good.
Someone brought their lecture
notes: when the constraint graph
has no negative weight cycles.
Good, thank you.
Now, what is the constraint
graph?
OK, this has a one letter
answer more or less.
I'll accept the one letter
answer.
What?
A?
A: close.
G.
Yeah, I mean,
same thing.
Yeah, so the constraint graph
is essentially G.
Actually, it is G.
The constraint graph is G,
good.
And, we prove this by adding a
new source for text,
and connecting that to
everyone.
But that's sort of beside the
point.
That was in order to actually
satisfy them.
But this is our
characterization.
So, if we assume that there are
no negative weight cycles in our
graph, which we've been doing
all the time,
then we know that this thing is
satisfiable.
Therefore, there is an
assignment of this h's.
There is a re-weighting that
makes all the weights
nonnegative.
Then we can run Dijkstra.
OK, we're done.
Isn't that cool?
And how do we satisfy these
constraints?
We know how to do that with one
run of Bellman-Ford,
which costs order VE,
which is less than V times
Dijkstra.
So, that's it,
write down the details
somewhere.
So, this is Johnson's
algorithm.
This is the fanciest of them
all.
It will be our fastest,
all pairs shortest path
algorithm.
So, the claim is,
we can find a function,
h, from V to R such that the
modified weight of every edge is
nonnegative for every edge,
(u,v), in our graph.
And, we do that using
Bellman-Ford to solve the
difference constraints.
These are exactly the different
constraints that we were born to
solve that we learned to solve
last time.
The graphs here are
corresponding exactly if you
look back at the definition.
Or, Bellman-Ford will tell us
that there is a negative weight
cycle.
OK, great, so it's not that we
really have to assume that there
is no negative weight cycle.
We'll get to know.
And if your fancy,
you can actually figure out the
minus infinities from this.
But, at this point,
I just want to think about the
case where there is no negative
weight cycle.
But if there is,
we can find out that it exists,
and that just tell the user.
OK, then we'd stop.
Otherwise, there is no negative
weight cycle.
Therefore, there is an
assignment that gives is
nonnegative edge weights.
So, we just use it.
We use it to run Dijkstra.
So, step two is,
oh, I should say the running
time of all this is V times E.
So, we're just running
Bellman-Ford on exactly the
input graph.
Plus, we add a source,
if you recall,
to solve a set of difference
constraints.
You add a source vertex,
S, connected to everyone at
weight zero, run Bellman-Ford
from there because we don't have
a source here.
We just have a graph.
We want to know all pairs.
So, this, you can use to find
whether there is a negative
weight cycle anywhere.
Or, we get this magic
assignment.
So now, w_h is nonnegative,
so we can run Dijkstra on w_h.
We'll say, using w_h,
so you compute w_h.
That takes linear time.
And, we run Dijkstra for each
possible source.
I'll write this out explicitly.
We've had this in our minds
several times.
But, when we said n times
Dijkstra over n times BFS,
here it is.
We want to compute delta sub h
now, of (u,v) for all V,
and we do this separately for
all u.
And so, the running time here
is VE plus V^2 log V.
This is just V times the
running time of Dijkstra,
which is E plus V log V.
OK, it happens that this term
is the same as this one,
which is nice,
because that means step one
costs us nothing asymptotically.
OK, and then,
last step is,
well, now we know delta h.
We just need to compute delta.
So, for each pair of vertices,
we'll call it (u,v),
we just compute what the
original weights would be,
so what delta (u,v) is.
And we can do that using this
corollary.
It's just delta sub h of (u,v)
minus h of u plus h of v.
I got the signs right.
Yeah, so this takes V^2 time,
also dwarfed by the running
time of Dijkstra.
So, the overall running time of
Johnson's algorithm is just the
running time of step two,
running Dijkstra n times --
-- which is pretty cool.
When it comes to single source
shortest paths,
Bellman-Ford is the best thing
for general weights.
Dijkstra is the best thing for
nonnegative weights.
But for all pair shortest
paths, we can skirt the whole
negative weight issue by using
this magic we saw from
Bellman-Ford.
But now, running Dijkstra n
times, which is still the best
thing we know how to do,
pretty much,
for the all pairs nonnegative
weights, now we can do it for
general weights too,
which is a pretty nice
combination of all the
techniques we've seen.
In the trilogy,
and along the way,
we saw lots of dynamic
programming, which is always
good practice.
Any questions?
This is the last new content
lecture before the quiz.
On Wednesday it will be quiz
review, if I recall correctly.
And then it's Thanksgiving,
so there's no recitation.
And then the quiz starts on
Monday.
So, study up.
See you then.