linear time algorithm for order
statistics for cache oblivious.
Great.
This may turn you off a little
bit, but even though this is
like the simplest algorithm,
it's also probably the most
complicated analysis that we
will do.
In the future,
our algorithms will be more
complicated, and the analyses
will be relatively simple.
And usually,
it's that way with cache
oblivious algorithms.
So, I'm giving you this sort of
as the intuition of why this
should be enough.
Then you have to prove it.
OK, let's go to another problem
where divide and conquer is
useful, our good friend,
matrix multiplication.
I don't know how many times
we've seen this in this class,
but in particular we saw it
last week with a recursive
matrix multiply,
multithreaded algorithm.
So, I won't give you the
algorithm yet again,
but we're going to analyze it
in a very different way.
So, we have C and we have A,
and actually up to you.
So, I could cover standard
matrix multiplication,
which is when you do it row by
row, and column by column.
And, we could see why that's
bad.
And then, we could do the
recursive one and see why that's
good.
Or, we could skip the standard
algorithm.
So, how many people would like
to see why the standard
algorithm is bad?
Because it's not totally
obvious.
One, two, three,
four, five, half?
Wow, that's a lot of votes.
Now, how many people want to
skip to the chase?
No one.
One, OK.
And, everyone else is asleep.
So, that's pretty good,
50% awake, not bad.
OK, then, so standard matrix
multiplication.
I'll do this fast because it
is, I mean, you all know the
algorithm, right?
To compute this value of C;
in A, you take this row,
and in B you take this column.
Sorry I did a little bit
sloppily.
But this is supposed to be
aligned.
Right?
So I take all of this stuff,
I multiply it with all of the
stuff, add them up,
the dot product.
That gives me this element.
And, let's say I do them in
this order row by row.
So for every item in C,
I loop over this row and this
column, B, multiply them
together.
That is an access pattern in
memory.
So, exactly how much that costs
depends how these matrices are
laid out in memory.
OK, this is a subtlety we
haven't had to worry about
before because everything was
uniform.
I'm going to assume to give the
standard algorithm the best
chances of being good,
I'm going to store C in row
major order, A in row major
order, and B in column major
order.
So, everything is nice and
you're scanning.
So then this inner product is a
scan.
Cool.
Sounds great,
doesn't it?
It's bad, though.
Assume A is row major,
and B is column major.
And C, you could assume is
really either way,
but if I'm doing it row by row,
I'll assume it's row major.
So, this is what I call the
layout, the memory layout,
of these matrices.
OK, it's good for this
algorithm, but the algorithm is
not good.
So, it won't be that great.
So, how long does this take?
How many memory transfers?
We know it takes M^3 time.
Not going to try and beat M^3
here.
Just going to try and get
standard matrix multiplication
going faster.
So, well, for each item over
here I pay N over B to do the
scans and get the inner product.
So, N over B per item.
So, it's N over B,
or we could go with the plus
one here, to compute each c_ij.
So that would suggest,
as an upper bound at least,
it's N^3 over B.
OK, and indeed that is the
right bound, so theta.
This is memory transfers,
not time, obviously.
That is indeed the case because
if you look at consecutive,
I do this c_ij,
then this one,
this one, this one,
this one, keep incrementing j
and keeping I fixed,
right?
So, the row that I use stays
fixed for a long time.
I get to reuse that if it
happens, say that that fits a
block maybe, I get to reuse that
row several times if that
happens to fit in cache.
But the column is changing
every single time.
OK, so every time I moved here
and compute the next c_ij,
even if a column could fit in
cache, I can't fit all the
columns in cache.
And the columns that I'm
visiting move,
you know, they just scan
across.
So, I'm scanning this whole
matrix every time.
And unless you're entire matrix
fits in cache,
in which case you could do
anything, I don't care,
it will take constant time,
or you'll take M over B time,
enough to read it into the
cache, do your stuff,
and write it back out.
Except in that boring case,
you're going to have to pay N^2
over B for every row here
because you have to scan the
whole collection of columns.
You have to read this entire
matrix for every row over here.
So, you really do need N^3 over
B for the whole thing.
So, it's usually a theta.
So, you might say,
well, that's great.
It's the size of my problem,
the usual running time,
divided by B.
And that was the case when we
are thinking about linear time,
N versus N over B.
It's hard to beat N over B when
your problem is of size N.
But now we have a cubed.
And, this gets back to,
we have good spatial locality.
When we read a block,
we use the whole thing.
Great.
It seems optimal.
But we don't have good temporal
locality.
It could be that maybe if we
stored the right things,
we kept them around,
we could them several times
because we're using each element
like a cubed number of times.
That's not the right way of
saying it, but we're reusing the
matrices a lot,
reusing those items.
If we are doing N^3 work on N^2
things, we're reusing a lot.
So, we want to do better than
this, and that's the recursive
algorithm, which we've seen.
So, we know the algorithm
pretty much.
I just have to tell you what
the layout is.
So, we're going to take C,
partition of C_1-1,
C_1-2, and so on.
So, I have an N by N matrix,
and I'm partitioning into N
over 2 by N over 2 submatrices,
all three of them times
whatever.
And, I could write this out yet
again but I won't.
OK, we can recursively compute
this thing with eight matrix
multiplies, and a bunch of
matrix additions.
I don't care how many,
but a constant number.
We see that at least twice now,
so I won't show it again.
Now, how do I lay out the
matrices?
Any suggestions how I lay out
the matrices?
I could lay them out in row
major order.
I'll call it major order.
But that might be less natural
now.
We're not doing anything by
rows or by columns.
So, what layout should I use?
Yeah?
Quartet major order,
maybe quadrant major order
unless you're musically
inclined, yeah.
Good idea.
You've never seen this order
before, so it's maybe not so
natural.
Somehow I want to cluster it by
blocks.
OK, I think that's about all.
So, I mean, it's a recursive
layout.
This was not an easy question.
It's OK.
Store matrices or lay out the
matrices recursively by block.
OK, I'm cheating a little bit.
I'm redefining the problem to
say, assume that your matrices
are laid out in this way.
But, it doesn't really matter.
We can cheat,
can't we?
In fact, it doesn't matter.
You can turn a matrix into this
layout without too much linear
work, almost linear work.
Log factors,
maybe.
OK, so if I want to store my
matrix A as a linear thing,
I'm going to recursively
defined that layout to be
recursively store the upper left
corner, then store,
let's say, the upper right
corner.
It doesn't matter which order I
do these.
I should have drawn this wider,
then store the lower left
corner, and then store the lower
right corner recursively.
So, how do you store this?
Well, you divide it in four,
and lay out the top left,
and so on.
OK, this is a recursive
definition of how the element
should be stored in a linear
array.
It's a weird one,
but this is a very powerful
idea in cache oblivious
algorithms.
We'll use this multiple times.
OK, so now all we have to do is
analyze the number of memory
transfers.
How hard could it be?
So, we're going to store all
the matrices in this order,
and we want to compute the
number of memory transfers on an
N by N matrix.
See, I lapsed and I switched to
lowercase n.
I should, throughout this week,
be using uppercase N because
for historical reasons,
any external memory kinds of
algorithms, to level algorithms,
always talk about capital N.
And, don't ask why.
You should see what they define
little n to be.
OK, so, any suggestions on what
the recurrence should be now?
All his fancy setup with the
recurrence is actually pretty
easy.
So, definitely it involves
multiplying matrices that are N
over 2 by N over 2.
So, what goes here?
Eight, thank you.
That you should know.
And that the tricky part is
what goes here.
OK, what goes here is,
now, the fact that I can even
write this, this is the matrix
additions.
Ignore those for now.
Suppose there weren't any.
I just have to recursively
multiply.
The fact that this actually is
eight times memory transfers of
N over 2 relies on this layout.
Right, I'm assuming that the
arrays that I'm given are given
as contiguous intervals and
memory.
If they aren't,
I mean, if they're scattered
all over memory,
I'm screwed.
There's nothing I can do.
So, but by assuming that I have
this recursive layout,
I know that the recursive
multiplies will always deal with
three consecutive chunks of
memory, one for A,
one for B, one for C,
OK, no matter what I do.
Because these are stored
consecutively,
recursively I have that
invariant.
And I can keep recursing.
And I'm always dealing with
three consecutive chunks of
memory.
That's why I need this layout
is to be able to say this.
OK, Now what does addition
cost?
I'll just give you two
matrices.
They're stored in some linear
order, the same linear order
among the three of them.
Do I care what the linear order
is?
How should I add two matrices,
get the output?
Yeah?
Right, if each of the three
arrays I'm dealing with are
stored in the same order,
I can just scan in parallel
through all three of them and
just add corresponding elements,
and output it to the third.
So, I don't care what the order
is, as long as it's consistent
and I get N^2 over B.
I'll ignore plus one here.
That's just looking at the
entire matrix.
So, there we go:
another recurrence.
We've seen this with N^2,
and we just got N^3.
But, it turns out now we get
something cooler if we use the
right base case.
So now we get to the base case,
ah, the tricky part.
So, any suggestions what base
case I should use?
The block size,
good suggestion.
So, if we have something of
size order B,
we know that takes a constant
number of memory transfers.
It turns out that's not enough.
That won't solve it here.
But good guess.
In this case,
it's not the right answer.
I'll give you some intuition
why.
We are trying to improve on N^3
over B.
If you were just trying to get
it divided by B,
this is a great base case.
But here, we know that just the
improvement afforded by the
block size is not enough.
We have to somehow use the fact
that the cache is big.
It's M, so however big M is,
it's that big.
OK, so if we want to get some
improvement on this,
we've got to have M in the
formula somewhere,
and there's no M's yet.
So, it's got to involve M.
What's that?
MT of M over B?
That would work,
but MT of M is also OK,
I mean, some constant times M,
let's say.
I want to make this constant
small enough so that the entire
problem fits in cache.
So, it's like one third.
I think it's actually,
oh wait, is it the square root
of M actually?
Right, this is an N by N
matrix.
So, it should be C times the
square root of M.
Sorry.
So, the square root of M by
square root of M matrix has M
entries.
If I make C like one third or
something, then I can fit all
three matrices in memory.
Actually, one over square root
of three would do,
but who cares?
So, for some constant,
C, now everything fits in
memory.
How many memory transfers does
it take?
One?
It's a bit too small,
because I do have to read the
problem in.
And now, I mean,
here was one because there's
only one block to read.
Now how many blocks are there
to read?
Constants?
No.
B?
M over B, good.
Get it right eventually.
That's the great thing about
thinking with an oracle.
You can just keep guessing.
M over B because we have cache
size M.
There are M over B blocks in
that cache to read each one,
OK?
This is maybe,
you forgot what M was because
we haven't used it for a long
time.
But M is the number of elements
in cache.
This is the number of blocks in
cache.
OK, some of was saying B,
and it's reasonable to assume
that M over B is about B.
That's like a square cache,
but in general,
we don't make that assumption.
OK, where are we?
We're hopefully done,
just about, good,
because we have three minutes.
So, that's our base case.
I have a square root here;
I just forgot it.
Now we just have to solve it.
Now, this is an easier
recurrence, right?
I don't want to use the master
method, because master method is
not going to handle these B's
and M's, and these crazy base
cases.
OK, master method would prove
N^3.
Great.
Master method doesn't really
think about these kinds of
cases.
But with regression trees,
if you remember way back to the
proof of the master method,
just look at the recursion tree
as geometric up or down where
everything is equal,
and then you just add them up,
every level.
The point is that this is a
nice recurrence.
All of the sub problems are the
same size, and that analysis
always works,
I say, when everything has the
same size, all the children.
So, here's the recursion tree.
We have N^2 over B at the top.
We split into eight subproblems
where each one,
the cost is one half N^2 over
B.
I'm not going to write them
all.
There they are.
You add them up.
How much do you get?
Well, there's eight of them.
Eight times a half is two.
Four.
[LAUGHTER] Thanks.
Four, right?
OK, I'm bad at arithmetic.
I probably already said it,
but there are three kinds of
mathematicians,
those who can add,
and those who can't.
OK, why am I looking at this?
It's obvious.
OK, so we keep going.
This looks geometrically
increasing.
Right?
You just know in your heart
that if you work out the first
two levels, you can tell whether
it's geometrically increasing,
decreasing, or they're all
equal, or something else.
And then you better think.
But I see this as geometrically
increasing.
It will indeed be like 16 at
the next level,
I guess.
OK, it should be.
So, it's increasing.
That means the leaves matter.
So, let's work out the leaves.
And, this is where we use our
base case.
So, we have a problem of size
square root of M.
And so, yeah,
you have a question?
Oh, indeed.
I knew there was something.
I knew it was supposed to be
two out here.
Thanks.
This is why you're here.
It's actually N over two
squared over B.
Thanks.
I'm substituting N over 2 into
this.
OK, so this is actually N^2
over 4 B.
So, I get two,
because there are eight times
one over four.
OK, I wasn't that far off then.
It's still geometrically
increasing, still the case,
OK?
But now, it actually doesn't
matter.
Whatever the cost is,
as long as it's bigger than
one, great.
Now we look at the leaves.
The leaves are root M by root
M.
I substitute root M into this:
I get M over B with some
constants.
Who cares?
So, each leaf is M over B,
OK, lots of them.
How many are there?
This is the only,
deal with recursion trees,
counting the number of leaves
is always the annoying part.
Oh boy, well,
we start with an N by N matrix.
We stop when we get down to
root N by root N matrix.
So, that sounds like something.
Oh boy, I'm cheating here.
Really?
That many?
It sounds plausible.
OK, the claim is,
and I'll cheat.
So I'm going to use the oracle
here, and we'll figure out why
this is the case.
N over root N^3 leaves,
hey what?
I think here,
it's hard to see the tree.
But it's easy to see in the
matrix.
Let's enter the matrix.
We have our big matrix.
We divided in half.
We recursively divide in half.
You get the idea,
OK?
Now, at some point these
sectors, let's say one of these
sectors, and each of these
sectors, fits in cache.
And three of them fit in cache.
So, that's when we stop the
recursion in the analysis.
The algorithm goes all the way.
But in the analysis,
let's say we stop at M.
OK, now, how many leaves or
problems are there?
Oh man, this is still not
obvious.
OK, the number of leaf chunks
here is, like,
I mean, the number of these
things is something like N over
root M, right,
the number of chunks.
But, it's a little less clear
because I have so many of these.
But, all right,
so let's just suppose,
now, I think of normal,
boring, matrix multiplication
on chunks of this size.
That's essentially what the
leaves should tell me.
I start with this big problem,
I recurse out to all these
little, tiny,
multiply this by that,
OK, this root M by root M
chunk.
OK, how many operations,
how many multiplies do I do on
those things?
N^3.
But now, N, the size of my
matrix in terms of these little
sub matrices,
is N over root M.
So, it should be N over root
M^3 subproblems of this size.
If you work it out,
normally we go down to things
of constant size and we get
exactly N^3 of them.
Now we are stopping at this
short point in saying,
well, it's however many there
are, cubed.
OK, this is a bit of hand
waving.
You could work it out with the
recurrence on the number of
leaves.
But there it is.
So, the total here is N over,
let's work it out.
N^3 over M to the three halves,
that's this number of leaves,
times the cost at each leaf,
which is M over B.
So, some of the N's cancel,
and we get N^3 over B root M,
which is a root M factor better
than N^3 over B.
It's actually quite a lot,
the square root of the cache
size.
That is optimal.
The best two level matrix
multiplication algorithm is N^3
over B root M memory transfers.
Pretty amazing,
and I'm over time.
You can generalize this into
all sorts of great things,
but the bottom line is this is
a great way to do matrix
multiplication as a recursion.
We'll see more recursion for
cache oblivious algorithms on
Wednesday.