and W(n) = 2W(n/2) + O(1).
The usual base cases.
I mean, these are recurrences
we should know and love.
This is log n,
I sort of have already given
away the answers,
and this better be linear.
This is again Case 1.
And to the log base 2 of 2 is
n, which is the answer,
much bigger than 1.
And here n to the log base 2 of
1 is n to the zero,
which is 1, which is the same
so we get log n.
The area is n log n,
but if you are making chips you
want the area as small as
possible so you can fit more
good stuff in there.
So, we would like to aim for,
well, we certainly cannot do a
better area than n.
You've got to put the leaves
down somewhere,
but this is already pretty
good.
It is only a log factor off,
but we want to aim for n.
How could we get n?
Any guesses on what needs to
change in this layout?
Not how to do it because that
is not obvious,
but in terms of height and
width what should we do?
It is pretty hard to get the
height smaller than log n,
I will tell you,
because this is a tree.
It cannot really get its width
down to less than log n.
What could we do to make the
product linear?
Just random ideas.
What are two functions whose
product is n?
Square root of n and square
root of n.
That is a good choice.
Were there other suggestions?
n times constant.
Yeah, n times constant would be
nice.
But I claim you cannot get
either of these down to less
than a constant.
You could aim for n over log n
by log n, that is more likely,
but I think that is almost
impossible.
Root n by root n is the right
answer, so let's go with that.
So, root n by root n.
We haven't seen any recurrences
whose solution is root n,
but surely they are out there.
Let's say the goal is to get
W(n) = Theta(root n) and to get
H(n) = Theta(root n).
If we did that we would be
happy, because then the area is
the product is linear.
How?
What is a recurrence that is in
the usual master method form
whose solution is root n?
I mean, you could think of it
that way.
Recurrence is a bit tricky,
but let's just think of
n^log_b(a).
When is log base b of a ½?
Because then n^log_b(a) is root
n.
And there is some hope that I
could get a root n solution to
recurrence.
This is designed by knowing
that it is divide-and-conquer,
and therefore it must be
something like this.
It is easy once you know the
approach you are supposed to
take and you can try this
approach.
When is log base b of a ½?
Lots of solutions,
shout them out.
4 and 2, that is a good one.
I better get this right.
Log base 4 of 2 is ½ because
the square root of 4 is 2.
So, let's aim for this.
Why not?
When would we get log base 4 of
2?
This is b, this is a,
so it should be 2T(n/4) plus
something.
And if I want the n^log_b(a) to
dominate, it has got to be
polynomially smaller than root
n.
So, this should be
n^1/2-epsilon.
But it could be smaller.
It could be 1.
Zero would be nice,
but that is probably too much
to hope for.
So, something smaller,
strictly polynomially smaller
than root n.
That is our goal.
And now comes the magic.
If you played with this for a
while you would find it,
I think, at this point.
When you know that you are
somehow solve this problem of
size n with two subproblems of
size n/4 what could you do?
Well, if you start thinking of
things as squares,
this is the natural thing that
happens.
This is called the H layout.
You can imagine why.
It would be much easier to draw
if I had a grid board,
a graph board,
whatever, if that exists.
This is a recursive layout.
I am only going to draw a
couple iterations,
but hopefully you can imagine
the generalization.
I take four Hs,
a good plan because I want
problems of size n/4.
This has n/4 leaves.
This is the root,
by the way, in the middle.
This has n/4 leaves.
So, I have four problems of
size n/4.
Somehow I have got to get that
down to two.
Thankfully, if I look at width
or if I look at height,
there are only two that matter.
And these two matter and these
two get along for free.
They are going in parallel,
just like we had with height
over here.
But I get that both in height
and in width.
If I measure,
well, now they are equal,
so I will just call them the
length.
We have L(n)-by-L(n).
And if I compute well,
what is L(n)?
I have here L(n/4) because
there are only a quarter of the
leaves in this one or in that
one, then I have a constant,
Theta(1), no big deal,
and then I have L(n/4) again.
So, I get the recurrence that I
wanted.
L(n) = 2L(n/4) + Theta(1).
And that has solution square
root of n, as we claimed before.
Again, we are in Case 1 of the
master method.
Cool, ha?
This is a much more compact
layout.
Charles, did you invent this
layout?
No.
But I know it appears on your
PhD thesis and you extended it
in various directions.
So, this is sort of a classic
cool layout of trees into grids
and another application of
divide-and-conquer.
I mean this is not particularly
useful for algorithms directly.
It is useful for VLSI layout
directly.
But it gives you more flavor of
how you should think.
If you know what running time
you are aiming for,
like in problem sets in quizzes
often we say here is the running
time you have got to get,
think about the recurrence that
will get you there.
And that could inspire you.
And that is it.
Recitation Friday.
Homework lab Sunday.
No class Monday.
See you Wednesday.