we're looking at here roughly,
so let's call that floor of n
over 2, and then within each
group we have three elements.
So we have at least 3 times
floor of floor of n over 5 over
2 n floor elements that are less
than or equal to x.
And we have the same that are
greater than or equal to x.
Let me simplify this a little
bit more.
I can also give you some more
justification,
and we drew the picture,
but just for why this is true.
We have at least n over 5 over
2 group medians that are less
than or equal to x.
This is the argument we use.
We have half of the group
medians are less than or equal
to x because x is the median of
the group median,
so that is no big surprise.
This is almost an equality but
we're making floors so it's
greater than or equal to.
And then, for each group
median, we know that there are
three elements there that are
less than or equal to that group
median.
So, by transitivity,
they're also less than or equal
to x.
We get this number times three.
This is actually just floor of
n over 10.
I was being unnecessarily
complicated there,
but that is where it came from.
What we know is that this thing
is now at least 3 times n over
10, which is roughly 3/10 of
elements are in one side.
In fact, at least 3/10 of the
elements are in each side.
Therefore, each side has at
most 7/10 elements roughly.
So the number here will be
7/10.
And, if I'm lucky,
7/10 plus 1/5 is strictly less
than one.
I believe it is,
but I have trouble working with
tenths.
I can only handle powers of
two.
What we're going to use is a
minor simplification,
which just barely still works,
is a little bit easier to think
about.
It's mainly to get rid of this
floor because the floor is
annoying.
And we don't really have a
sloppiness lemma that applies
here.
It turns out if n is
sufficiently large,
3 times floor of n over 10 is
greater than or equal to 1/4.
Quarters I can handle.
The claim is that each group
has size at least 1/4,
therefore each group has size
at most 3/4 because there's a
quarter on the side.
This will be 3/4.
And I can definitely tell that
1/5 is less than 1/4.
This is going to add up to
something strictly less than one
and then it will work.
How is my time?
Good.
At this point,
the rest of the analysis is
easy.
How the heck you would come up
with this algorithm,
you realize that this is
clearly a really good choice for
finding a partition element,
just barely good enough that
both recursions add up to linear
time.
Well, that's why it took so
many famous people.
Especially in quizzes,
but I think in general this
class, you won't have to come up
with an algorithm this clever
because you can just use this
algorithm to find the median.
And the median is a really good
partition element.
Now that you know this
algorithm, now that we're beyond
1973, you don't need to know how
to do this.
I mean you should know how this
algorithm works,
but you don't need to do this
in another algorithm because you
can just say run this algorithm,
you will get the median in
linear time, and then you can
partition to the left and the
right.
And then the left and the right
will have exactly equal size.
Great.
This is a really powerful
subroutine.
You could use this all over the
place, and you will on Friday.
Have I analyzed the running
time pretty much?
The first step is linear.
The second step is T of n over
The third step,
I didn't write it,
is linear.
And then the last step is just
a recursive call.
And now we know that this is
3/4.
I get this recurrence.
T of n is, I'll say at most,
T of n over 5 plus T of 3/4n.
You could have also used 7/10.
It would give the same answer,
but you would also need a floor
so we won't do that.
I claim that this is linear.
How should I prove it?
Substitution.
Claim that T of n is at most
again c times n,
that will be enough.
Proof is by substitution.
Again, we assume this is true
for smaller n.
And want to prove it for n.
We have T of n is at most this
thing.
T of n over 5.
And by induction,
because n of 5 is smaller than
n, we know that this is at most
c.
Let me write it as c over 5
times n.
Sure, why not.
Then we have here 3/4cn.
And then we have a linear term.
Now, unfortunately,
I have to deal with things that
are not powers of two.
I will cheat and look at my
notes.
This is also known as 19/20
times c times n plus theta n.
And the point is just that this
is strictly less than one.
Because it's strictly less than
one, I can write this as one
times c of n minus some
constant, here it happens to be
1/20, as long as I have
something left over here,
1/20 times c times n.
Then I have this annoying theta
n term which I want to get rid
of because I want this to be
nonnegative.
But it is nonnegative,
as long as I set c to be
really, really large,
at least 20 times whatever
constant is here.
So this is at most c times n
for c sufficiently large.
And, oh, by the way,
if n is less than or equal to
50, which we used up here,
then T of n is a constant,
it doesn't really matter what
you do, and T of n is at most c
times n for c sufficiently
large.
That proves this claim.
Of course, the constant here is
pretty damn big.
It depends exactly what the
constants and the running times
are, which depends on your
machine, but practically this
algorithm is not so hot because
the constants are pretty big.
Even though this element is
guaranteed to be somewhere
vaguely in the middle,
and even though these
recursions add up to strictly
less than n and it's geometric,
it's geometric because the
problem is reducing by at least
a factor of 19/20 each time.
So it actually takes a while
for the problem to get really
small.
Practically you probably don't
want to use this algorithm
unless you cannot somehow flip
coins.
The randomized algorithm works
really, really fast.
Theoretically this is your
dream, the best you could hope
for because it's linear time and
you need linear time as
guaranteed linear time.
I will mention,
before we end,
an exercise.
Why did we use groups of five?
Why not groups of three?
As you might guess,
the answer is because it
doesn't work with groups of
three.
But it's quite constructive to
find out why.
If you work through this math
with groups of three instead of
groups of five,
you will find that you don't
quite get the problem reduction
that you need.
Five is the smallest number for
which this works.
It would work with seven,
but theoretically not any
better than a constant factor.
Any questions?
All right.
Then recitation Friday.
Homework lab Sunday.
Problem set due Monday.
Quiz one in two weeks.