The indicator random variable
is zero, except if you get the
particular split.
Therefore, this summation is
going to be zero,
except for that k which
actually appeared in which case
it is the value that we say it
is.
See the trick using
multiplication by 0,
1 variable to handle all the
cases?
I think that is damn clever.
And this is like the classic
thing that you do with indicator
random variables.
It's one of the reasons they
are a very powerful method.
Because now we actually have a
mathematical expression,
hairy although it may be,
for our recurrence.
Now, what we are going to
analyze is the expected value of
T(n).
That is what we want to do.
What is the expected value of
T(n)?
To do that, I just write the
expected value of T(n) is equal
to the expected value of this
big summation.
And now we can go ahead and
start to evaluate the expected
value of that summation.
Everybody with me?
Yes?
Any questions at this point?
I see a thumbs up.
That's nice to see.
But I generally believe that
what I want to see is no thumbs
down.
It is good to see the thumbs
up, but that means one person
understands, or thinks he
understands.
[LAUGHTER] So,
this is, I claim,
equal to the following.
Actually, I am going to need a
little space here so I am going
to move the equal sign over a
little bit.
I claim that summation is equal
to that.
This expectation is equal to
that summation of expectations.
Why is that?
What are the magic words that
justify this step?
Linearity of expectation.
The expectation of a sum is the
sum of the expectations.
So, that is linearity of
expectation.
I don't need independence for
that.
That is just always true for
expectation of any random
variables.
The sum of the expectations is
the expectation of the sum and
vice versa.
Here we did the vice versa.
That is equal to now the sum of
k=0 to n-1 of expectation of X_k
[T(k) + T(n-k-1) + Theta(n)].
Why is that true?
What I have done is I've said
the expectation of the product
is the product of the
expectations.
That is because of
independence.
What is independent of what?
The X_k here,
random variable,
are independent of any of the
other partitionings in,
if you will,
the X_k that would exist for
any of the other recursive
calls.
So, whatever happens in here is
independent of what happened
there.
We are actually hiding.
Since we have a recurrence,
we are not partitioning the
same wage time.
We have a different one.
We actually have something
going on underneath the
mathematics you have to pay
attention to that the
mathematics alone isn't really
showing, which is that in T(k)
there is actually a set of
random choices that are being
made, if you will.
And so you have to understand
that those are independent of
those, in which case we can
multiple the probabilities of
their expectations.
Is everybody with me?
That is a big one,
independence of X_k from other
random choices.
That is equal to now,
well, first of all,
this is nice.
What is the expectation of X_k?
1/n.
That actually doesn't even
belong in the summation.
We will just pop it outside.
I get 1/n times the sum of k=0
to n-1 of expectation of T(k) +
1/n summation k=0 to n-1 of
expectation of T(n-k-1) + 1/n
summation k=0 to n-1 up to
Theta(n).
That is, again,
using linearity of expectation
there this time to split up
these pieces and just factoring
out the expectation of k as
being 1/n.
Everybody with me still?
All of this is elementary.
It is just one of these things
that is hard just because there
are so many steps.
And it takes that you have seen
some of this before.
Now the next observation is
that these two summations are,
in fact, identical.
They are the same summation,
just in a different order.
This is going T(0),
T(1), T(2), T(3) up to T(n-1).
This one is going T(n-1),
T(n-2), T(n-3) down to T(0).
These are, in fact,
equal.
So, therefore,
I have two of them.
And then what is this term
equal to?
What is that one equal to?
Theta(n).
Let's just see why.
The summation of 0 :
n of Theta(n) is Theta(n^2)
divided by n.
Or, if I want to bring the
Theta(n) out,
I have 1 times the summation of
k equals1 to n of Theta(1) or of
So, once again,
you get n, either way of doing
it.
This is, in some sense,
because the summations have
identical terms,
and this is just algebra.
Now what we are going to do is
do something for technical
convenience.
Because we are going to absorb
the k=0, 1 terms into the
Theta(n) for technical
convenience.
We have a recurrence here where
I have an order n.
And, if I look at the cases
where k=0 or k=1,
I know what the expectation is.
For 0, 1, the expected cost is
the worst case cost,
which is constant.
Because I am only solving the
problem for a constant size.
And we know that for any of the
boundary cases that our solution
of recurrence,
our assumption is that it is
constant time.
So, I basically can just take
those two terms out.
And all that does it accumulate
some more constant here in the
Theta(n).
It is going to make the
solution of the recurrence a
little bit easier.
And, if I do that,
I get expectation of T(n) = 2/n
summation k=2 to n-1 of
expectation of T(k) + Theta(n).
So, all of that work was to
derive the recurrence.
And now we have to solve it.
Just to review what we did,
we started out with a
recurrence which was for the
random variable which involved a
case statement.
We converted that into some
mathematics without the case
statement, just with a product,
and then we derived a
recurrence for the expectation.
And now we are in the process
of trying to solve that
recurrence.
We have done some
simplification of the recurrence
so that we understand what it is
that we are going to solve here.
By the way, I don't give things
like this on quizzes.
I do expect you to understand
it.
The elements of this you will
find on a quiz.
This is a lot of work to figure
out.
This took smart people to do.
Even though it is all
elementary, but working out
something like this at the
elementary level is still a bit
of work even for somebody who is
knowledgeable in this area.
Now we are going to solve that
last recurrence over there and
we are going to prove that the
expectation of T(n) is less than
or equal to (an lg n) for some
constant a greater than 0.
That is going to be what we are
going to do.
And so what technique do you
think we should use to prove
this?
Does this look like a master
method?
It is nothing like the master
method.
So, when in doubt do
substitution.
It is the grand-daddy of all
methods.
What we will do is solve the
base case by simply choosing a
big enough so that (an lg n) is
bigger than the expectation of
T(n) for sufficiently large
small n.
So, I just pick a to be big
enough.
And this is,
by the way, why I wanted to
exclude 0 and 1 from the
recurrence.
Because, for example,
when n=0, log of 0 is,
it's like dividing by 0,
right, you cannot do it.
Log of 1 is 0.
So here, even if I restricted
it to 1, here I would have a 0,
and I can't ever pick a big
enough to dominate those cases.
What I do is I just say look,
I just absorb whatever the cost
is into the T(n) for technical
convenience.
And that lets me address it as
(an lg n) to be big enough to
handle the base case.
So, that is why we made that
technical assumption.
We are going to use a fact
which is that the summation of
k=2 to n-1 of k lg k is less
than or equal to 1/2n^2 lg n -
1/8n^2.
I am going to leave that as an
exercise for you to workout.
I think it is an exercise in
the book, too.
I want you to go and evaluate
this.
There are two ways to evaluate
it.
One is by using purely
summations and facts about
summations by splitting the
summation into two pieces and
reconstituting it to prove this
bound.
The other way is to use the
integral method for solving
summations.
Either way you can prove.
The integral method actually
gets you a tighter bound than
this.
This is a basic fact,
and you should go off and know
how to do that.
Now let's do substitution.
The expectation of T(n) is less
than or equal to 2/n times the
summation k=2 to n-1,
now we do the substitution of
ak lg k, the smaller values plus
Theta(n).
I might mentioned,
by the way, that the hard part
of doing this,
it is easy to get the bound
without this term,
it is easy to get this bound,
1/2n^2 lg n,
it is harder to get the second
order term.
It turns out you need the
second order term in order to do
what we are going to do.
You have to be able to subtract
a quadratic amount of the n^2 lg
n in order to make this proof
work.
And that is the trickier part
in evaluating that summation.
So, we get this.
That is less than or equal to?
Well, I happen to know how much
this is by using that formula.
I use my fact and get 2a/n
(1/2n^2 lg n - 1/8n^2) +
Theta(n).
Did I do something wrong?
There we go.
Very good.
That is equal to -
If I multiply this first part
through that is an lg n.
And now, so I don't make a
mistake, I want to express this
as my desired,
this is what I want it to be,
minus a residual.
I am going to write the
residual as this part.
And so, the way to write that
is, that is going to be minus.
And then it is going to be this
term here, which is going to be
an/4 - Theta(n).
And that is going to be less
than or equal to an lg n if this
part is positive.
And I can make that part
positive by picking a big enough
such that an/4 dominates the
constant in the Theta(n) here.
Whatever the constant is here,
I can find an a that is big
enough so that this term makes
this part positive.
If a is big enough so that an/4
dominates Theta(n).
And so the running time of
randomized quicksort is order n
lg n.
That is what we just proved,
the expected running time is
order n lg n.
Now, in practice,
quicksort is a great algorithm.
It is typically three or more
times faster than mergesort.
It doesn't give you the strong
guarantee necessarily of
mergesort and being worst-case n
lg n.
But in practice,
if you use randomized
quicksort, it is generally as
much as three times faster.
It does require code tuning in
order to get it up to be that
fast.
You do have to go and coarsen
the base cases and do some other
tricks there,
but most good sorting
algorithms that you will find
are based on quicksort.
Also one of the other reasons
it works well is because it
tends to work well with caches
in virtual memory.
We are not really talking much
about caching models and so
forth, big topic these days in
algorithms, but it does work
very well with caches in virtual
memory.
It is another reason that this
is a good algorithm to use.
Good recitation,
by the way, on Friday.
We are going to see another n
log n time algorithm,
a very important one in
recitation on Friday.