in some sense I'm being
wasteful because I can't
possibly get enough speed up to
justify those extra processors.
So, understanding parallelism
of a job says that's sort of a
limit on the number of
processors I want to have.
And, in fact,
I can achieve that.
Question?
Yeah, really,
in some sense,
this is saying it should be
omega P.
Yeah, so that's fine.
It's a question of,
so ask again.
No, no, it's only if it's
bounded above by a constant.
T_1 and T infinity aren't
constants.
They're variables in this.
So, we are doing multivariable
asymptotic analysis.
So, any of these things can be
a function of anything else,
and can be growing as much as
we want.
So, the fact that we say we are
given it for a particular thing,
we're really not given that
number.
We're given a whole class of
DAG's or whatever of various
sizes is really what we're
talking about.
So, I can look at the growth.
Here, where it's talking about
the growth of the parallelism,
sorry, the growth of the
runtime T_P as a function of T_1
and T infinity.
So, I am talking about things
that are growing here,
OK?
OK, so let's put this to work,
And, in fact,
so now I'm going to go back to
here.
Now I'm going to tell you about
a little bit of my own research,
and how we use this in some of
the work that we did.
OK, so we've developed a
dynamic multithreaded language
called Cilk, spelled with a C
because it's based on the
language, C.
And, it's not an acronym
because silk is like nice
threads, OK, although at one
point my students had a
competition for what the acronym
silk could mean.
The winner, turns out,
was Charles' Idiotic Linguistic
Kluge.
So anyway, if you want to take
a look at it,
you can find some stuff on it
here.
OK,
OK, and what it uses is
actually one of these more
complicated schedulers.
It's a randomized online
scheduler, OK,
and if you look at its expected
runtime on P processors,
it gets effectively T_1 over P
plus O of T infinity provably.
OK, and empirically,
if you actually look at what
kind of runtimes you get to find
out what's hidden in the big O
there, it turns out,
in fact, it's T_1 over P plus T
infinity with the constants here
being very close to one
empirically.
So, no guarantees,
but this turns out to be a
pretty good bound.
Sometimes, you see a
coefficient on T infinity that's
up maybe close to four or
something.
But generally,
you don't see something that's
much bigger than that.
And mostly, it tends to be
around, if you do a linear
regression curve fit,
you get that the constant here
is close to one.
And so, with this,
you get near perfect if you use
this formula as a model for your
runtime.
You get near perfect linear
speed up if the number of
processors you're running on is
much less than your average
parallelism, which,
of course, is the same thing as
if T infinity is much less than
T_1 over P.
So, what happens here is that
when P is much less than P
infinity, that is,
T infinity is much less than
T_1 over P, this term ceases to
matter very much,
and you get very good speedup,
OK, in fact,
almost perfect speedup.
So, each processor gives you
another processor's work as long
as you are the range where the
number of processors is much
less than the number of
parallelism.
Now, with this language many
years ago, which seems now like
many years ago,
OK, it turned out we competed.
We built a bunch of chess
programs.
And, among our programs were
Starsocrates,
and Cilkchess,
and we also had several others.
And these were,
I would call them,
world-class.
In particular,
we tied for first in the 1995
World Computer Chess
Championship in Hong Kong,
and then we had a playoff and
we lost.
It was really a shame.
We almost won,
running on a big parallel
machine.
That was, incidentally,
some of you may know about the
Deep Blue chess playing program.
That was the last time before
they faced then world champion
Kasparov that they competed
against programs.
They tied for third in that
tournament.
OK, so we actually out-placed
them.
However, in the head-to-head
competition, we lost to them.
So we had one loss in the
tournament up to the point of
the finals.
They had a loss and a draw.
Most people aren't aware that
Deep Blue, in fact,
was not the reigning World
Computer Chess Championship when
they faced Kasparov.
The reason that they faced
Kasparov was because IBM was
willing to put up the money.
OK, so we developed these chess
programs, and the way we
developed them,
let me in particular talk about
Starsocrates.
We had this interesting anomaly
come up.
We were running on a 32
processor computer at MIT for
development.
And, we had access to a 512
processor computer for the
tournament at NCSA at the
University of Illinois.
So, we had this big machine.
Of course, they didn't want to
give it to us very much,
but we have the same machine,
just a small one,
at MIT.
So, we would develop on this,
and occasionally we'd be able
to run on this,
and this was what we were
developing for on our processor.
So, let me show you sort of the
anomaly that came up,
OK?
So, we had a version of a
program that I'll call the
original program,
OK, and we had an optimized
program that included some new
features that were supposed to
make the program go faster.
And so, we timed it on our 32
processor machine.
And, it took us 65 seconds to
run it.
OK, and then we timed this new
program.
So, I'll call that T prime of
sub 32 on our 32 processor
machine, and it ran and 40
seconds to do this particular
benchmark.
Now, let me just say,
I've lied about the actual
numbers here to make the
calculations easy.
But, the same idea happened.
Just the numbers were messier.
OK, so this looks like a
significant improvement in
runtime, but we rejected the
optimization.
OK, and the reason we rejected
it is because we understood
about the issues of work and
critical path.
So, let me show you the
analysis that we did,
OK?
So the analysis,
it turns out,
if we looked at our
instrumentation,
the work in this case was
2,048.
And, the critical path was one
second, which,
over here with the optimized
program, the work was,
in fact, 1,024.
But the critical path was
eight.
So, if we plug into our simple
model here, the one I have up
there with the approximation
there, I have T_32 is equal to
T_1 over 32 plus T infinity,
and that's equal to,
well, the work is 2,048 divided
by 32.
What's that?
64, good, plus the critical
path, one, that's 65.
So, that checks out with what
we saw.
OK, in fact,
we did that,
and it checked out.
OK, it was very close.
OK, over here,
T prime of 32 is T prime,
one over 32 plus T infinity
prime, and that's equal to 1,024
divided by 32 is 32 plus eight,
the critical path here.
That's 40.
So, that checked out too.
So, now what we did is we said
is we said, OK,
let's extrapolate to our big
machine.
How fast are these things going
to run on our big machine?
Well, for that,
we want T of 512.
And, that's equal to T_1 over
512 plus T infinity.
And so, what's 2,048 divided by
512?
It's four, plus T infinity is
one.
That's equal to five.
So, go quite a bit faster on
this.
But here, T prime of 512 is
equal to T one prime over 512
plus T infinity prime is equal
to, well, 1,024 plus divided by
512 is two plus critical path of
eight, that's ten.
OK, and so, you see that on the
big machine, we would have been
running twice as slow had we
adopted that,
quote, "optimization",
OK, because we had run out of
parallelism, and this was making
the path longer.
We needed to have a way of
doing it where we could reduce
the work.
Yeah, it's good to reduce the
work but not as the critical
path ends up getting rid of the
parallels that we hope to be
able to use during the runtime.
So, it's twice as slow,
OK, twice as slow.
So the moral is that the work
and critical path length predict
the performance better than the
execution time alone,
OK, when you look at
scalability.
And a big issue on a lot of
these machines is scalability;
not always, sometimes you're
not worried about scalability.
Sometimes you just care.
Had we been running in the
competition on a 32 processor
machine, we would have accepted
this optimization.
It would have been a good
trade-off.
OK, but because we knew that we
were running on a machine with a
lot more processors,
and that we were close to
running out of the parallelism,
it didn't make sense to be
increasing the critical path at
that point, because that was
just reducing the parallelism of
our calculation.
OK, next time,
any questions about that first?
No?
OK.
Next time, now that we
understand the model for
execution, we're going to start
looking at the performance of
particular algorithms what we
code them up in a dynamic,
multithreaded style,
OK?