k, so if this is a statement
about condition on this event,
which is a random event,
then what we have is X_n equals
one plus the max of X_(k minus
one), X_(n minus k) because the
height of this tree is the max
of the heights of the two
subtrees plus one because we
have one more level up top.
OK, so that's the natural thing
to do.
What we are trying to analyze,
though, is Y_n.
So, for Y_n,
we have to take two to this
power.
So, it's two times the max of
two to the X_(k minus one),
which is Y_(k minus one),
and two to this,
which is Y_(n minus k).
And, now you start to see,
maybe, why we are interested in
Y's instead of X's in the sense
that it's what we know how to
do.
When we solve a recursion,
when we solve,
like, the expected running
time, we haven't taken
expectations,
yet, here.
But, when we compute the
expected running time of
quicksort, we have something
like two times,
I mean, we have a couple of
recursive subproblems,
which are being added together.
OK, here, we have a factor of
two.
Here, we have a max.
But, intuitively,
we know how to multiply random
variables by a constant because
that's, like,
there's two recursive
subproblems of the size is equal
to the max of these two,
which we don't happen to know
here.
But, there it is,
whereas one plus,
we don't know how to handle so
well.
And, indeed,
our techniques are really good
at solving recurrences,
except up to the constant
factors.
And, this one plus really
doesn't affect the constant
factor too much,
it would seem.
OK, but it's a big deal.
In exponentiation,
it's a factor of two.
So here, it's really hard to
see what this one plus is doing.
And, our analysis,
if we tried it,
and it's a good idea to try it
at home and see what happens,
if you tried to do what I'm
about to do with X_n,
the one plus will sort of get
lost, and you won't get a bound.
You just can't prove anything.
With a factor of two,
we're in good shape.
We sort of know how to deal
with that.
We'll say more when we've
actually done the proof about
why we use Y_n instead of X_n.
But for now,
we're using Y_n.
So, this is sort of a
recursion, except it's
conditioned on this event.
So, how do I turn this into a
statement that holds all the
time?
Sorry?
Divide by the probability of
the event?
More or less.
Indeed, these events are
independent.
Or, they're all equally likely,
I should say.
They're not independent.
In fact, one determines all the
others.
So, how do I generally
represent an event in algebra?
Indicator random variables:
good.
Remember your friends,
indicator random variables.
All of these analyses use
So, they will just represent
this event, and we'll call it
Z_nk.
It's going to be one if the
root has rank,
k, and zero otherwise.
So, in particular,
the probability of,
these things are all equally
likely for, a particular value
of n if you try all the values
of k.
The probability that this
equals one, which is also the
expectation of that indicator
random variable,
which you should know,
is it only takes values one or
zero.
The zero doesn't matter in the
expectation.
So, this is going to be,
hopefully, one over n if I got
right.
So, there are n possibility of
what the rank of the root could
be.
Each of them are equally likely
because we have a uniform
permutation.
So, now, I can rewrite this
condition statement as a
summation where the Z_nk's will
let me choose what case I'm in.
So, we have Y_n is the sum,
k equals one to n of Z_nk times
two times the max of X,
sorry, Y, k minus one,
Y_n minus k.
So, now we have our good
friend, the recurrence.
We need to solve it.
OK, we can't really solve it
because this is a random
variable, and it's talking about
recursive random variables.
So, we first take the
expectation of both sides.
That's the only thing we can
really bound.
Y_n could be n^2 in an unlucky
case, sorry, not n^2.
It could be n^2.
It could be two to the,
boy, two to the n if you are
unlucky because X_n could be as
big as n, the height of the
tree.
And, Y_n is two to that.
So, it could be two to the n.
What we want to prove is that
it's polynomial in n.
If it's n to some constant,
and we take logs,
it'll be order log n.
OK, so we'll take the
expectation, and hopefully that
will guarantee that this holds.
OK, so we have expectation of
this summation of random
variables times recursive random
variables.
So, what is the first,
woops, I forgot a bracket.
What is the first thing that we
do in this analysis?
This should,
yeah, linearity of expectation.
That one's easy to remember.
OK, we have a sum.
So, let's put the E inside.
OK, now we have the expectation
of our product.
What should we use?
Independence.
Hopefully, things are
independent.
And then, we could write this.
Then, it would be the
expectation of the product.
And, heck, let's put the two
outside, because it's not,
no sense in keeping it in here.
Y is there starting to look
like X's?
I can't even read them.
Sorry about that.
This should all be Y's.
OK, very wise,
random variables.
So.
Why are these independent?
So, here we are looking at the
choice of what the root is,
what rank the root has in a
problem of size n.
In here, we're looking at what
the root, I mean,
there are various choices of
what the search tree looks like
in the stuff left of the root,
and in the stuff right of the
root.
Those are independent choices
because everything is uniform
here.
So, the choice of this guy was
uniform.
And then, that determines who
partitions in the left and the
right.
Those are completely
independent recursive choices of
who's the root in the left
subtree?
Who's the root in the left of
the left subtree,
and so on?
So, this is a little trickier
than usual.
Before, it was random choices
in the algorithm.
Now, it's in some construction
where we choose the random
numbers ahead of time.
It's a bit funny,
but this is still independent.
So, we get this just like we
did in quicksort,
and so on.
OK.
Now, we continue.
And, now it's time to be a bit
sloppy.
Well, one of these things we
know.
OK, E of ZNK,
that, we wrote over here.
It's one over n.
So, that's cool.
So, we get a two over n
outside, and we get this sum of
the expectation of a max of
these two things.
Normally, we would write,
well, I think sometimes you
write T of max,
or Y of the max of the two
things here.
You've got to write it as the
max of these two variables.
And, the trick,
I mean, it's not too much of a
trick, is that the max is,
at most, the sum.
So, we have nonnegative things.
So, we have two over n,
sum k equals one to n of the
expectation of the sum instead
of the max.
OK, this is,
in some sense,
the key step where we are
losing something in our bound.
So far, we've been exact.
Now, we're being pretty sloppy.
It's true the max is,
at most, the sum.
But, it's a pretty loose upper
bound as things go.
We'll keep that in mind for
later.
What else can we do with the
summation?
This should,
again, look familiar.
Now that we have a sum of a sum
of two things,
I'm trying to like it to be a
sum of one thing.
Sorry?
You can use linearity of
expectation, good.
So, that's the first thing I
should do.
So, linearity of expectation
lets me separate that.
Now I have a sum of 2n things.
Right, I could break that into
the sum of these guys,
and the sum of these guys.
Do you know anything about
those two sums?
Do we know anything about those
two sums?
They're the same.
In fact, every term here is
appearing exactly twice.
One says a k minus one.
One says an n minus k,
and that even works if it's
odd, I think.
So, in fact,
we can just take one of the
sums and multiply it by two.
So, this is four over n times
the sum, and I'll rewrite it a
little bit from zero to n minus
one of E of Y_k.
Just check the number of times
each Y_k appears from zero up to
n minus one is exactly two.
So, now I have a recurrence.
I have E of Y_n is,
at most, this thing.
Let's just write that for our
memory.
So, how's that?
Cool.
Now, I just have to solve the
recurrence.
How should I solve an ugly,
hairy, recurrence like this?
Substitution:
yea!
Not the master method.
OK, it's a pretty nasty
recurrence.
So, I'm going to make a guess,
and I've already told you the
guess, that it's n^3.
I think n^3 is pretty much
exactly where this proof will be
obtainable.
So, substitution method,
substitution method is just a
proof by induction.
And, there are two things every
proof by induction should have,
well, almost every proof by
induction, unless you're being
fancy.
It should have a base case,
and the base case here is n
equals order one.
I didn't write it,
but, of course,
if you have a constant size
tree, it has constant height.
So, this thing will be true as
long as we set true if c is
sufficiently large.
OK, so, don't forget that.
A lot of people forgot it on
the quiz.
We even mentioned the base
case.
Usually, we don't even mention
the base case.
And, you should assume that
there's one there.
And, you have to say this in
any proof by substitution.
OK, now, we have the induction
step.
So, I claim that E of Y_n is,
at most, Ccof n^3,
assuming that it's true for
smaller n.
You should write the induction
hypothesis here,
but I'm going to skip it
because I'm running out of time.
Now, we have this recurrence
that E of Y_n is,
at most, this thing.
So, E of Y_n is,
at most, four over n,
sum k equals zero to n minus
one of E of Y_k.
Now, notice that k is always
smaller than n.
So, we can apply induction.
So, this is,
at most, four over n,
sum k equals zero to n minus
one of c times k^3.
That's the induction
hypothesis.
Cool.
Now, I need an upper bound on
this sum, if you have a good
memory, then you know a closed
form for this sum.
But, I don't have such a good
memory as I used to.
I never memorized this sum when
I was a kid, so I don't remember
everything when I memorize when
I was less than 12 years old.
I still remember all the digits
of pi, whatever.
But, anything I try to memorize
now just doesn't quite stick the
same way.
So, I don't happen to know this
sum.
What's a good way to
approximate this sum?
Integral: good.
So, in fact,
I'm going to take the c
outside.
So, this is 4c over n.
The sum is, at most,
the integral.
If you get the range right,
so, you have to go one larger.
Instead of n minus one,
you go up to n.
This is in the textbook.
It's intuitive,
too, as long as you have a
monotone function.
That's key.
So, you have something that's
like this.
And, you know,
the sum is taking each of these
and weighting them with a value
of one.
The integral is computing the
area under this curve.
So, in particular,
if you look at this
approximation of the integral,
then, I mean,
this thing is certainly,
this would be the sum if you go
one larger at the end,
and that's, at most,
the integral.
So, that's proof by picture.
But, you can see this in the
book.
You should know it from 042 I
guess.
Now, integrals,
hopefully, you can solve.
Integral of x^3 is x^4 over
four.
I got it right.
And then, we're valuing that at
n.
And, it's zero.
Subtracting the zero doesn't
matter because zero to the
fourth power is zero.
So, it's just n^4 over four.
So, this is 4c over n times n^4
over four.
And, conveniently,
this four cancels with this
four.
The four turns into a three
because of this,
and we get n^3.
We get cn^3.
Damn convenient,
because that's what we wanted
to prove.
OK, so this proof is just
barely snaking by:
no residual term.
We've been sloppy all over the
place, and yet we were really
lucky.
And, we were just sloppy in the
right places.
So, this is a very tricky
proof.
If you just tried to do it by
hand, it's pretty easy to be too
sloppy, and not get quite the
right answer.
But, this just barely works.
So, let me say a couple of
things about it in my remaining
one minute.
So, we can do the conclusion,
again.
I won't write it because I
don't have time,
but here it is.
We just proved a bound on Y_n,
which was two to the power X_n.
What we cared about was X_n.
So, we used Jensen's
inequality.
We get the two to the E of X_n
is, at most, E of two to the
X_n.
This is what we know about
because that's Y_n.
So, we know E of Y_n is now
order n^3.
OK, we had to set this constant
sufficiently large for the base
case.
We didn't really figure out
what the constant was here.
It didn't matter because now
we're taking the logs of both
sides.
We get E of X_n is,
at most, log of order n^3.
This constant is a
multiplicative constant.
So, you take the logs.
It becomes additive.
This constant is an exponent.
So, it would take logs.
It becomes a multiple.
Three log n plus order one.
This is a pretty damn tight
bound on the height of a
randomly built binary search
tree, the expected height,
I should say.
In fact, the expected height of
X_n is equal to,
well, roughly,
I'll just say it's roughly,
I don't want to be too precise
here, 2.9882 times log n.
This is the result by a friend
of mine, Luke Devroy,
if I spell it right,
in 1986.
He's a professor at McGill
University in Montreal.
So, we're pretty close,
three to 2.98.
And, I won't prove this here.
The hard part here is actually
the lower bound,
but it's only that much.
I should say a little bit more
about why we use Y_n instead of
X_n.
And, it's all about the
sloppiness.
And, in particular,
this step, where we said that
the max of these two random
variables is,
at most, the sum.
And, while that's true for X
just as well as it is true for
Y, it's more true for Y.
OK, this is a bit weird
because, remember,
what we're analyzing here is
all possible values of k.
This has to work no matter what
k is, in some sense.
I mean, we're bounding all of
those cases simultaneously,
the sum of them all.
So, here we're looking at k
minus one versus n minus k.
And, in fact,
here, there's a polynomial
version.
But, so, if you take two values
a and b, and you say,
well, max of ab is,
at most, a plus b.
And, on the other hand you say,
well, max of two to the a and
two to the b is,
at most, two to the a plus two
to the b.
Doesn't this feel better than
that?
Well, they are,
of course, the same.
But, if you look at a minus b,
as that grows,
this becomes a tighter bound
faster than this becomes a
tighter bound because here we're
looking at absolute difference
between a minus b.
So, that's why this is pretty
good and this is pretty bad.
We're still really bad if a and
b are almost the same.
But, we're trying to solve this
for all partitions into k minus
one and n minus k.
So, it's OK if we get a few of
the cases wrong in the middle
where it evenly partitions.
But, as soon as we get some
skew, this will be very close to
this, whereas this will be still
pretty far from this.
You have to get pretty close to
the edge before you're not
losing much here,
whereas pretty quickly you're
not losing much here.
That's the intuition.
Try it, and see what happens
with X_n, and it won't work.
See you Wednesday.