except for the ones at the
limit.
So, I get plus phi of L_0 minus
phi of L sub cardinality of S.
And now, this term is zero.
And this term is greater than
or equal to zero.
OK, so therefore this whole
thing is less than or equal to,
well, what's that?
That's just four times opt's
cost.
And so, we're four competitive.
OK, this is amazing,
I think.
It's not that hard,
OK, but it's quite amazing that
just by doing a simple
heuristic, you're nearly as good
as any omniscient algorithm
could possibly be.
OK, you're nearly as good.
And, in fact,
in practice,
this is a great heuristic.
So, if ever you have things
like a hash table that you're
actually seeing by chaining,
OK, often it's the case that if
when you access the elements,
you're just bringing them up to
the front of the list if it's an
unsorted list that you've put
them into, just bring them up to
the front.
You can easily save 30 to 40%
in run time for the accessing to
the hash table because you will
be much more likely to find the
elements inside.
Of course, it depends on the
distribution and so forth,
for empirical matters,
but the point is that you are
not going to be too far off from
the ordering that an optimal
algorithm would do,
optimal off-line algorithm:
I mean, amazing.
OK: optimal off-line.
Now, it turns out that in the
reading that we assigned,
so, we assigned you Sleator and
Tarjan's original paper.
In that reading,
they actually have a slightly
different model where they count
transposes that move in excess
to element x towards the front
of the list as free.
OK, so, and this basically
models, so here's the idea is if
I actually have a linked list,
and when I chase down,
once I find x,
I can actually move x up to the
front with just a constant
number of pointer operations to
splice it out and put it up to
the front.
I don't actually have to
transpose all way back down.
OK, so that's kind of the model
that they use,
which is a more realistic
model.
OK, I presented this argument
because it's a little bit
simpler.
OK, and the model is a little
bit simpler.
But in our model,
they have, when you access
something, you want to bring it
up to the front,
or anything that you happen to
go across during that time,
you could bring up to the front
essentially for free.
This model is the splicing in,
splicing x in and out of L in
constant time.
Then, MTF is,
it turns out,
too competitive.
It's within a factor of two of
optimal, OK, if you use that.
And that's actually a good
exercise to work through.
You could also go read about it
in the reading to understand
this better, to look to see
where you would use those
things.
You have to have another term
representing the number of,
quote, "free" transposes.
But it turns out that all the
math works out pretty much the
same.
OK, let's see,
another thing I promised you
is, what if, to look at the
case, what if they don't start
with the same lists?
OK, what if the two lists are
different when they start?
Then, the potential function at
the beginning might be as big as
what?
How big are the potential
function start out as if the
lists are different?
So, suppose we're starting out,
you have a list,
and opt says,
OK, I'm going to start out by
ordering my list according to
the sequence that I want to use,
OK, and MTF orders it according
to the sequence it must use.
What list is opt going to start
out with as an adversary?
Yeah, it's going to pick the
reverse of what ever MTF starts
out with, right,
because then,
if he picks the reverse,
what's the number of
inversions?
It's how many inversions in a
reverse ordered list?
Yeah, n choose two,
OK.
Is it n choose two,
or n minus one choose two?
n minus one choose two,
OK, inversions that you get
because it's basically a
triangular number when you add
them up.
But in any case,
it's order n^2,
worst case.
So, what does that do to our
analysis here?
It says that the cost of MTF of
S is going to be,
well, this is no longer zero.
This is now n^2.
OK, so we get that costs of MTF
of S is, at most,
four times opt's thing plus
order n^2, OK?
And, if we look at the
definition, did we erase it
already?
OK, this is still for
competitive, OK,
since n^2 is constant as the
size of S goes to infinity.
This is, once again,
sort of your notion of,
what does it mean to be a
constant?
OK, so as the size of the list
gets bigger, all we're doing is
accessing whatever that number,
n, is of elements.
That number doesn't grow with
the problem size,
OK, even if it starts out as
some variable number,
n.
OK, it doesn't grow with the
problem size.
We still end up being
competitive.
This is just the k that was in
that definition of
competitiveness.
OK, any questions?
Yeah?
Well, so you could change the
cost model a little bit.
Yeah.
And that's a good one to work
out.
But if you say the cost of
transposing, so,
the cost of transposing is
probably moving two pointers,
approximately.
No, one, three pointers.
So, suppose that the cost of,
wow, that's a good exercise,
OK?
Suppose the cost was three
times to do a transpose,
was three times the cost of
doing an access,
of following a pointer.
OK, how would that change the
number here?
OK, good exercise,
great exercise.
OK, hmm, good final question.
OK, yes, it will affect the
constant here just as when we do
the free transpose,
when we move things towards the
front, that we consider those as
free, OK.
Those operations end up
reducing the constant as well.
OK, but the point is that this
constant is independent of the
constant having to do with the
number of elements in the list.
So that's a different constant.
So, this is a constant.
OK, and so as with a lot of
these things,
there's two things.
One is, there's the theory.
So, theory here backs up
practice.
OK, those practitioners knew
what they were doing,
OK, without knowing what they
were doing.
OK, so that's really good.
OK, and we have a deeper
understanding that's led to,
as I say, many algorithms for
things like, the important ones
are like paging.
So, what's the comment page
replacement policy that people
study, people have at most
operating systems?
Who's done 6.033 or something?
Yeah, it's Least Recently Used,
LRU.
People have heard of that,
OK.
So, you can analyze LRU
competitive, and show that LRU
is actually competitive with
optimal page replacement under
certain assumptions.
OK, and there are also other
things.
Like, people do random
replacement algorithms,
and there are a whole bunch of
other kinds of things that can
be analyzed with the competitive
analysis framework.
OK, so it's very cool stuff.
And, we are going to see more
in recitation on Friday,
see a couple of other really
good problems that are maybe a
little bit easier than this one,
OK, definitely easier than this
one.
OK, they give you hopefully
some more intuition about
competitive analysis.
I also want to warn you about
next week's problem set.
So, next week's problem set has
a programming assignment on it.
OK, and the programming
assignment is mandatory,
meaning, well,
all the problem sets are
mandatory as you know,
but if you decide not to do a
problem there's a little bit of
a penalty and then the penalties
scale dramatically as you stop
doing problem sets.
But this one is
mandatory-mandatory.
OK, you don't pass the class.
You'll get an incomplete if you
do not do this programming
assignment.
Now, I know that some people
are less practiced with
programming.
And so, what I encourage you to
do over the weekend is spent a
few minutes and work on your
programming skills if you're not
up to snuff in programming.
It's not going to be a long
assignment, but if you don't
know how to read a file and
write out a file,
and be able to write a dozen
lines of code,
OK, if you are weak on that,
this weekend would be a good
idea to practice reading in a
text file.
It's going to be a text file.
Read it in a text file,
decent manipulations,
write out a text file,
OK?
So, I don't want people to get
caught with this being mandatory
and that not have time to finish
it because they are busy trying
to learn how to program in short
order.
I know some people take this
course without quite getting all
the programming prerequisites.
Here's where you need it.
Question?
No language limitations.
Pick your language.
The answer will be written in,
I think, Java,
and Eric has graciously
volunteered to use Python for
his solution to this problem.
We'll see whether he lives up
to that promise.
You did already?
OK, and George wrote the Java
solution.
And so, C is fine.
Matlab is fine.
OK, what else is fine?
Anything is fine.
Scheme is fine.
Scheme is great.
OK, so any such things will be
just fine.
So, we don't care what language
you program in,
but you will have to do
programming to solve this
problem.
OK, so thanks very much.
See you next week.