Good.
I haven't lost anyone.
And, indeed,
they're now in sorted order.
And you can start to see why
this is working.
When I have equal elements
here, I have already sorted the
suffix.
Let's write down a proof of
that.
What is nice about this
algorithm is we're not
partitioning into bins.
We always keep the huge batch
of elements in one big pile,
but we're just going through it
multiple times.
In general, we sort of need to
go through it multiple times.
Hopefully not too many times.
But let's first argue
correctness.
To analyze the running time is
a little bit tricky here because
it depends how you partition
into digits.
Correctness is easy.
We just induct on the digit
position that we're currently
sorting, so let's call that t.
And we can assume by induction
that it's sorted beyond digit t.
This is our induction
hypothesis.
We assume that we're sorted on
the low-order t - 1 digits.
And then the next thing we do
is sort on the t-th digit.
We just need to check that
things work.
And we restore the induction
hypothesis for t instead of t -
When we sort on the t-th digit
there are two cases.
If we look at any two elements,
we want to know whether they're
put in the right order.
If two elements are the same,
let's say they have the same
t-th digit --
This is the tricky case.
If they have the same t-th
digit then their order should
not be changed.
So, by stability,
we know that they remain in the
same order because stability is
supposed to preserve things that
have the same key that we're
sorting on.
And then, by the induction
hypothesis, we know that that
keeps them in sorted order
because induction hypothesis
says that they used to be
sorted.
Adding on this value in the
front that's the same in both
doesn't change anything so they
remain sorted.
And if they have differing t-th
digits --
-- then this sorting step will
put them in the right order.
Because that's what sorting
does.
This is the most significant
digit, so you've got to order
them by the t-th digit if they
differ.
The rest are irrelevant.
So, proof here of correctness
is very simple once you know the
algorithm.
Any questions before we go on?
Good.
We're going to use counting
sort.
We could use any sorting
algorithm we want for individual
digits, but the only algorithm
that we know that runs in less
than n lg n time is counting
sort.
So, we better use that one to
sort of bootstrap and get an
even faster and more general
algorithm.
I just erased the running time.
Counting sort runs in order k +
n time.
We need to remember that.
And the range of the numbers is
1 to k or 0 to k - 1.
When we sort by a particular
digit, we shouldn't use n lg n
algorithm because then this
thing will take n lg n for one
round and it's going to have
multiple rounds.
That's going to be worse than n
lg n.
We're going to use counting
sort for each round.
We use counting sort for each
digit.
And we know the running time of
counting sort here is order k +
n .
But I don't want to assume that
my integers are split into
digits for me.
That's sort of giving away too
much flexibility.
Because if I have some number
written in whatever form it is,
probably written in binary,
I can cluster together some of
those bits and call that a
digit.
Let's think of our numbers as
binary.
Suppose we have n integers.
And they're in some range.
And we want to know how big a
range they can be.
Let's say, a sort of practical
way of thinking,
you know, we're in a binary
world, each integer is b bits
long.
So, in other words,
the range is from 0 to 2b - 1.
I will assume that my numbers
are non-negative.
It doesn't make much difference
if they're negative,
too.
I want to know how big a b I
can handle, but I don't want to
split into bits as my digits
because then I would have b
digits and I would have to do b
rounds of this algorithm.
The number of rounds of this
algorithm is the number of
digits that I have.
And each one costs me,
let's hope, for linear time.
And, indeed,
if I use a single bit,
k = 2.
And so this is order n.
But then the running time would
be order n per round.
And there are b digits,
if I consider them to be bits,
order n times b time.
And even if b is something
small like log n,
if I have log n bits,
then these are numbers between
0 and n - 1.
I already know how to sort
numbers between 0 and n - 1 in
linear time.
Here I'm spending n lg n time,
so that's no good.
Instead, what we're going to do
is take a bunch of bits and call
that a digit,
the most bits we can handle
with counting sort.
The notation will be I split
each integer into b/r digits.
Each r bits long.
In other words,
I think of my number as being
in base 2^r.
And I happen to be writing it
down in binary,
but I cluster together r bits
and I get a bunch of digits in
base 2^r.
And then there are b/ r digits.
This b/r is the number of
rounds.
And this base --
This is the maximum value I
have in one of these digits.
It's between 0 and 2^r.
This is, in some sense,
k for a run of counting sort.
What is the running time?
Well, I have b/r rounds.
It's b/r times the running time
for a round.
Which I have n numbers and my
value of k is 2^r.
This is the running time of
counting sort,
n + k, this is the number of
rounds, so this is b/r (n+2^r).
And I am free to choose r
however I want.
What I would like to do is
minimize this run time over my
choices of r.
Any suggestions on how I might
find the minimum running time
over all choices of r?
Techniques, not necessarily
solutions.
We're not used to this because
it's asymptomatic,
but forget the big O here.
How do I minimize a function
with respect to one variable?
Take the derivative,
yeah.
I can take the derivative of
this function by r,
differentiate by r,
set the derivative equal to 0,
and that should be a critical
point in this function.
It turns out this function is
unimodal in r and you will find
the minimum.
We could do that.
I'm not going to do it because
it takes a little bit more work.
You should try it at home.
It will give you the exact
minimum, which is good if you
know what this constant is.
Differentiate with respect to r
and set to 0.
I am going to do it a little
bit more intuitively,
in other words less precisely,
but I will still get the right
answer.
And definitely I will get an
upper bound because I can choose
r to be whatever I want.
It turns out this will be the
right answer.
Let's just think about growth
in terms of r.
There are essentially two terms
here.
I have b/r(n) and I have
b/r(2^r).
Now, b/r(n) would like r to be
as big as possible.
The bigger r is the number of
rounds goes down.
This number in front of n,
this coefficient in front of n
goes down, so I would like r to
be big.
So, b/r(n) wants r big.
However, r cannot be too big.
This is saying I want digits
that have a lot of bits in them.
It cannot be too big because
there's 2^r term out here.
If this happens to be bigger
than n then this will dominate
in terms of growth of r.
This is going to be b times 2
to the r over r.
2 the r is much,
much bigger than r,
so it's going to grow much
faster is what I mean.
And so I really don't want r to
be too big for this other term.
So, that is b/4(2^r) wants r
small.
Provided that this term is
bigger or equal to this term
then I can set r pretty big for
that term.
What I want is the n to
dominate the 2^r.
Provided I have that then I can
set r as large as I want.
Let's say I want to choose r to
be maximum subject to this
condition that n is greater than
or equal to 2^r.
This is an upper bound to 2^r,
and upper bound on r.
In other words,
I want r = lg n.
This turns out to be the right
answer up to constant factors.
There we go.
And definitely choosing r to be
lg n will give me an upper bound
on the best running time I could
get because I can choose it to
be whatever I want.
If you differentiate you will
indeed get the same answer.
This was not quite a formal
argument but close,
because the big O is all about
what grows fastest.
If we plug in r = lg n we get
bn/lg n.
The n and the 2^r are equal,
that's a factor of 2,
2 times n, not a big deal.
It comes out into the O.
We have bn/lg n which is r.
We have to think about what
this means and translate it in
terms of range.
b was the number of bits in our
number, which corresponds to the
range of the number.
I've got 20 minutes under so
far in lecture so I can go 20
minutes over,
right?
No, I'm kidding.
Almost done.
Let's say that our numbers,
are integers are in the range,
we have 0 to 2^b,
I'm going to say that it's
range 0 to nd.
This should be a -1 here.
If I have numbers that are
between 0 and n^d - 1 where d is
a constant or d is some
parameter, so this is a
polynomial in n,
then you work out this running
time.
It is order dn.
This is the way to think about
it because now we can compare to
counting sort.
Counting sort could handle 0 up
to some constant times d in
linear time.
Now I can handle 0 up to n to
some constant power in linear
time.
This is if d = order 1 then we
get a linear time sorting
algorithm.
And that is cool as long as d
is at most lg n.
As long as your numbers are at
most n lg n then we have
something that beats our n lg n
sorting algorithms.
And this is pretty nice.
Whenever you know that your
numbers are order log end bits
long we are happy,
and you get some smooth
tradeoff there.
For example,
if we have our 32 bit numbers
and we split into let's say
eight bit chunks then we'll only
have to do four rounds each
linear time and we have just 256
working space.
We were doing four rounds for
32 bit numbers.
If you use n lg n algorithm,
you're going to be doing lg n
rounds through your numbers.
n is like 2000,
and that's at least 11 rounds
for example.
You would think this algorithm
is going to be much faster for
small numbers.
Unfortunately,
counting sort is not very good
on a cache.
In practice,
rating sort is not that fast an
algorithm unless your numbers
are really small.
Something like quicksort can do
better.
It's sort of shame,
but theoretically this is very
beautiful.
And there are contexts where
this is really the right way to
sort things.
I will mention finally that if
you have arbitrary integers that
are one word length long.
Here we're assuming that there
are b bits in a word and we have
some depends indirectly on b
here.
But, in general,
if you have a bunch of integers
and they're one word length
long, and you can manipulate a
word in constant time,
then the best algorithm we know
for sorting runs in n times
square root of lg lg n time
expected.
It is a randomized algorithm.
We're not going to cover that
algorithm in this class.
It's rather complicated.
I didn't even cover it in
Advanced Algorithms when I
taught it.
If you want something easier,
you can get n times square root
of lg lg n time worst-case.
And that paper is almost
readable.
I have taught that in Advanced
Algorithms.
If you're interested in this
kind of stuff,
take Advanced Algorithms next
fall.
It's one of the follow-ons to
this class.
These are much more complicated
algorithms, but it gives you
some sense.
You can even break out of the
dependence on b,
as long as you know that b is
at most a word.
And I will stop there unless
there are any questions.
Then see you Wednesday.