x starts out at the root.
And while it is not NIL,
and it's not NIL because it's
the root, what is this doing?
Somebody tell me what that code
does.
Well, what is this doing?
This is testing something
between i and int of x.
Int of x is the interval stored
at x.
What is this testing for?
I hope I got it right.
What is this testing for? Yeah?
Above or below?
I need just simple words.
Test for overlaps.
In particular test whether they
do or don't?
Do?
Don't?
If I get to this point,
what do I know about i and int
of x?
Don't overlap.
They don't overlap because the
high of one is smaller than the
low of the other.
The high of one is smaller than
the low of the other.
They don't overlap that way.
Could they overlap the other
way?
No because we're testing also
whether the low of the one is
bigger than the high of the
other.
They're saying it's either like
this or like this.
This is testing not overlap.
That makes it simpler.
When I'm searching for 14,
16, I check here.
And I say do they overlap?
And the answer is,
now we can understand it
without having to go through all
the arithmetic calculations,
no they don't overlap.
If they did overlap,
I found what I want.
And what's going to happen?
I am going to drop out of the
while loop and just return x,
because I will return something
that overlaps.
That is my goal.
Here it says they don't
overlap.
So then I say,
well, if left of x is not NIL,
in other words,
I've got a left child and low
of i is less than or equal to m
of left of x,
then we go left.
What happens in this case if
I'm searching for 14,
16?
Is the low of i less than or
equal to m of left of x?
Low of i is 14.
And I am searching.
And is it less than 18?
Yes.
Therefore, what do I do?
I go left and make x point to
this guy.
Now I check.
Does it overlap?
No.
I take a look at the left guy.
It is 8.
I compare 8 with 14,
right?
And is it lower?
No, so I go right.
And now I discover that I have
an overlap here and it overlaps.
It returns then the 15,
18 as an overlapping one.
If I were searching for 12,
I would go up to the top.
And I look, 12,
14, it doesn't overlap here.
I look at the 18 and it is
greater so I go left.
I then look here.
Does it overlap?
No.
So then what happens?
I look at the left.
It says I go right.
I look here.
Then I go and I look at the
left.
It says, no,
go right.
I go here, which is NIL,
and now it is NIL.
I return NIL.
And does 12,
14 overlap anything in the set?
No.
So, therefore,
it always works.
OK?
OK.
We're going to do correctness
in a minute, but let's just do
our analysis first so we don't
have to do it because the
correctness is going to be a
little bit tricky.
Time = O(lg n) because all I am
doing is going down the tree.
It takes time proportional to
the height of the tree.
That's pretty easy.
If I need to list all overlaps,
suppose I want to list all the
overlaps, how quickly can I do
that?
Can somebody suggest how I
could use this as a subroutine
to list all overlaps?
Suppose I have k overlaps,
k intervals that overlap my
query interval and I want to
find every single one of them,
how fast can I do that?
How do I do it?
If I search a second time,
I might get the same value.
Yeah, there you go.
Do what?
When you find it delete it.
Put it over to the side.
Find the next one,
delete it until there are none
left.
And then, if I don't want to
modify the data structure,
insert them all back in.
It costs me k lg n if they are
k overlaps.
That's actually called an
output sensitive algorithm.
Because the running time of it
depends upon how much it
outputs, so this is output
sensitive.
The best to date for this
problem, by the way,
of listing all is O(k+lg n)
with a different data structure.
And, actually,
that was open for a while as an
open problem.
OK. Correctness.
Why does this algorithm always
work correctly?
The key issue of the
correctness is that I am picking
one way to go,
left or right.
And that's great,
as long as it is in that
subtree.
But how do I know that when I
pick I decide I'm going to go
left that it might not be in the
right subtree and I went the
wrong way?
Or, if I went right,
that I accidentally left one
out on the left side?
We're always going just one
direction.
And that's sort of the
cleverness of the code.
The theorem is let's let L be
the set of intervals i prime in
the left of a node x.
And R be the set of i primes in
the right of x.
And now there are two parts I
am going to show.
If the search goes right then
the set of i prime in L,
such that i prime overlaps i is
the empty set.
That's the first thing I do.
If it goes right then there is
nothing in the left subtree that
overlaps.
It's always,
whenever the code goes right,
no problem, because there was
nothing in the left subtree to
be found.
Does everybody understand what
that says?
We are going to prove this,
but I want to make sure people
understand.
Because the second one is going
to be harder to understand so
you've got to make sure you
understand this one first.
Any questions about this?
OK.
If the search goes left --
-- then the set of i prime in L
such that i prime overlaps i
empty set implies that i prime
--
OK.
What is this saying?
If the search goes left,
if the left was empty,
in other words,
if you went left and you
discovered that there was
nothing in there to find,
no overlapping interval to find
then it is OK because it
wouldn't have helped me to go
right anyway because there is
nothing in the right to be
found.
So it is not guaranteeing that
there is nothing to be found in
the left, but if there happens
to be nothing to find in the
left it is OK because there was
nothing to be found in the right
either.
That is what the second one
says.
In either case,
you're OK to go the way.
So let's do this proof.
Does everybody understand what
the proof says?
Understanding the proof is
tricky.
It's logic.
Logic is tricky.
Suppose the search goes right.
We'll do the first one.
If left of x is NIL then we are
done since we proved what we
wanted to prove.
If we go right there are two
possibilities,
either we have left of x be NIL
or left of x is not NIL.
So if it is NIL we are OK
because we said if it goes right
I want to prove this,
that the things in the left
subtree that overlap is empty.
If there is nothing there,
there is clearly nothing there
that overlaps.
Otherwise, the low of i is
greater than m of the left of x.
If I look at x here,
either x was NIL in the while
statement here or this is true.
We just said it is not NIL so
let's take a look at,
excuse me.
I'm on the wrong line.
I am in this loop.
Left of x was not NIL and the
low of i was this.
Which way am I going here?
I am going right.
Therefore, this was not true.
So either left of x was not
NIL, which was the first one,
or low of i is greater than m
of left of x if I am going
right.
If I'm going right one of those
two had to be true.
The first one was easy.
Otherwise, we have this,
low of i is greater than m of
left of x.
Now this has got to be that
value.
m of left of x is the right
endpoint, is the high endpoint
of some interval in that
subtree.
This is equal to the high of j
for some j in L.
So m of left of x must be equal
to the high of some endpoint
because that's how we're picking
the m's.
For some j in the left subtree.
And no other interval in L has
a larger high endpoint --
-- than high of j.
If I draw a picture here,
I have over here i and this is
the low of i.
And I have j where we say its
high endpoint is less than the
low of i.
This is j, and I don't know how
far over it goes.
And this has high of j --
-- which is the highest one in
the left subtree.
There is nobody else who has
got a higher right endpoint.
There is nobody else in this
subtree who could possibly
overlap I, because all of them
end somewhere before this point.
This point is the highest one
in a subtree.
Therefore, i prime in L such
that i prime overlaps i is the
empty set.
And now the hard case.
Everybody stretch.
Hard case.
Does everybody follow this?
The point is that because this
is the highest guy everybody
else has to be left,
so if you didn't overlap the
highest guy you're not going to
overlap anybody.
Suppose the search goes left --
-- and that there is nothing to
overlap in the left subtree.
I went left here but I am not
going to find anything.
Now I want to prove that it
wouldn't have helped me to go
right.
That's essentially what the
theorem here says.
That if I assume this it
wouldn't have helped to go
right.
I want to show that there is
nothing in the right subtree.
So going left was OK because I
wasn't going to find anything
anyway.
Similarly, we go through a
similar analysis.
Low of i is less than or equal
to m of the left of x,
which once again is equal to
the high of j for some j in L.
We are just saying if I go left
these things must be true.
I went left.
Since j is in L it doesn't
overlap i, because the set of
things that overlap i in L is
empty set.
Since j doesn't overlap i that
implies that the high of i must
be less than the low of j.
Since j is in L and it doesn't
overlap i, what are the
possibilities?
We essentially have here,
if I draw a picture,
I have j and L and I have i
here.
The point is that it doesn't
overlap it, therefore,
it must be to the left because
its low endpoint is less than
this.
But it doesn't overlap it,
therefore its high endpoint
must be left of the low of this
one.
Now we will use the binary
search tree property.
That implies that for all i
prime in R, everything in the
right subtree,
we have a low of j is less than
or equal to low of i prime,
so we're sorted on the low
endpoints.
Everything in the right subtree
must have a low endpoint that
starts to the right of the low
endpoint of j because j in the
left subtree.
And everything in the whole
tree is sorted by low endpoints,
so anything in the right
subtree is going to start over
here.
Those are other things.
These are the i primes in R.
We don't know how many there
are, but they all start to the
right of this point.
So they cannot overlap i
either, therefore,
there is nothing.
All the i primes in R is also
nobody.
Just to go back again,
the basic idea is that since
this guy doesn't overlap the guy
who is in the left and everybody
to the right is going to be
further to the right,
if I go left and don't find
anything that's OK because I am
not going to find anything over
here anyway.
They are not going to overlap.
Data-structure augmentation,
great stuff.
It will give you a lot of rich,
rich data structures built on
any ones you know,
hash tables,
heaps, binary search trees and
so forth.