in.
OK, so you just scan down mod
m.
So, if you hit the bottom,
you go to the top.
OK, so the I'th one,
so that's fairly easy to do
because you don't have to
recomputed a full hash function
each time.
All you have to do is add one
each time you go because the
difference between this and the
previous one is just one.
OK, so you just go down.
Now, the problem with that is
that you get a phenomenon of
clustering.
If you get a few things in a
given area, then suddenly
everything, everybody has to
keep searching to the end of
those things.
OK, so that turns out not to be
one of the better schemes,
although it's not bad if you
just need to do something quick
and dirty.
So, it suffers from primary
clustering, where regions of the
hash table get very full.
And then, anything that hashes
into that region has to look
through all the stuff that's
there.
OK, so: long runs of filled
slots.
OK, there's also things like
quadratic clustering,
where you basically make this
be, instead of adding one each
time, you add i each time.
OK, but probably the most
effective popular scheme is
what's called double hashing.
And, you can do statistical
studies.
People have done statistical
studies to show that this is a
good scheme, OK,
where you let H of k,
i, let me do it below here
because I have for them.
So, H of k, i is equal to an
H_1 of k plus i times H_2 of k.
So, you have two hash functions
on m.
You have two hash functions,
H_1 of k and H_2 of k.
OK, so you compute the two hash
functions, and what you do is
you start by just using H_1 of k
for the zero probe,
because here,
i, then, will be zero.
OK.
Then, for the probe number one,
OK, you just add H_2 of k.
For probe number two,
you just add that hash function
amount again.
You just keep adding H_2 of k
for each successive probe you
make.
So, it's fairly easy;
you compute two hash functions
up front, OK,
or you can delay the second
one, in case.
But basically,
you compute two up front,
and then you just keep adding
the second one in.
You start at the location of
the first one,
and keep adding the second one,
mod m, to determine your probe
sequences.
So, this is an excellent
method.
OK, it does a fine job,
and you usually pick m to be a
power of two here,
OK, so that you're using,
usually people use this with
the multiplication method,
for example,
so that m is a power of two,
and H_2 of k you force to be
odd.
OK, so we don't use and even
value there, because otherwise
for any particular key,
you'd be skipping over.
Once again, you would have the
problem that everything could be
even, or everything could be odd
as you're going through.
But, if you make H_2 of k odd,
and m is a power of two,
you are guaranteed to hit every
slot.
OK, so let's analyze this
scheme.
This turns out to be a pretty
interesting scheme to analyze.
It's got some nice math in it.
So, once again,
in the worst case,
hashing is lousy.
So, we're going to analyze
average case.
OK, and for this,
we need a little bit stronger
assumption than for chaining.
And, we call it the assumption
of uniform hashing,
which says that each key is
equally likely,
OK, to have any one of the m
factorial permutations as its
probe sequence,
independent of other keys.
And, the theorem we're going to
prove is that the expected
number of probes is,
at most, one over one minus
alpha if alpha is less than one,
OK,
that is, if the number of keys
in the table is less than number
of slots.
OK, so we're going to show that
the number of probes is one over
one minus alpha.
So, alpha is the load factor,
and of course,
for open addressing,
we want the load factor to be
less than one because if we have
more keys than slots,
open addressing simply doesn't
work, OK, because you've got to
find a place for every key in
the table.
So, the proof,
we'll look at an unsuccessful
search, OK?
So, the first thing is that one
probe is always necessary.
OK, so if I have n over m,
sorry, if I have n items stored
in m slots, what's the
probability that when I do that
probe I get a collision with
something that's already in the
table?
What's the probability that I
get a collision?
Yeah?
Yeah, n over m,
right?
So, with probability,
n over m, we have a collision
because my table has got n
things in there.
I'm hashing,
at random, to one of them.
OK, so, what are the odds I hit
something, n over m?
And then, a second probe is
necessary.
OK, so then,
I do a second probe.
And, with what probability on
the second probe do I get a
collision?
So, we're going to make the
assumption of uniform hashing.
Each key is equally likely to
have any one of the m factorial
permutations as its probe
sequence.
So, what is the probability
that on the second probe,
OK, I get a collision?
Yeah?
If it's a permutation,
you're not, right?
Something like that.
What is it exactly?
So, that's the question.
OK, so you are not going to hit
the same slot because it's going
to be a permutation.
Yeah?
That's exactly right.
n minus one over m minus one
because I'm now,
I've essentially eliminated
that slot that I hit the first
time.
And so, I have,
now, and there was a key there.
So, now I'm essentially
looking, at random,
into the remaining n minus one
slots where there are
aggregately n minus one keys in
those slots.
OK, everybody got that?
OK, so with that probability,
I get a collision.
That means that I need a third
probe necessary,
OK?
And, we keep going on.
OK, so what is it going to be
the next time?
Yeah, it's going to be n minus
two over m minus two.
So, let's note,
OK, that n minus i over m minus
i is less than n over m,
which equals alpha,
OK?
So, n minus i over m minus i is
less than n over m.
And, the way you can sort of
reason that is that if n is less
than m, I'm subtracting a larger
fraction of n when I subtract i
than I am subtracting a fraction
of m.
OK, so therefore,
n minus i over m minus i is
going to be less than n over m.
OK, so, or you can do the
algebra.
I think it's always helpful
when you do algebra to sort of
think about it sort of
quantitatively as well,
you know, qualitatively what's
going on.
So, the expected number of
probes is, then,
going to be equal to,
it's going to be equal to
because we're going to need some
space, well, we have one which
is forced because we've got to
do one probe,
plus with probability n over m,
I have to do another probe plus
with probability of n over m
minus one I have to do another
probe up until I do one plus one
over m minus n.
OK, so each one is cascading
what's happened.
In the book,
there is a more rigorous proof
of this using indicator random
variables.
I'm going to give you the short
version.
OK, so basically,
this is my first probe.
With probability n over m,
I had to do a second one.
And, the result of that is that
with probability n minus one
over m minus one,
I have to do another.
And, with probability n over
two minus m over two,
I have to do another,
and so forth.
So, that's how many probes I'm
going to end up doing.
So, this is less than or equal
to one plus alpha.
There's one plus alpha times
one plus alpha times one plus
alpha, OK, just using the fact
that I had here.
OK, and that is less than or
equal to one plus I just
multiply through here.
Alpha plus alpha squared plus
alpha cubed plus k.
I can just take that out to
infinity.
It's going to bound this.
OK, does everybody see the math
there?
OK, and that is just the sum,
I, equals zero to infinity,
alpha to the I,
which is equal to one over one
minus alpha using your familiar
geometric series bound.
OK, and there's also,
in the textbook,
an analysis of the successful
search, which,
once again, is a little bit
more technical because you have
to worry about what the
distribution is that you happen
to have in the table when you
are searching for something
that's already in the table.
But, it turns out it's also
bounded by one over one minus
alpha.
So, let's just look to see what
that means.
So, if alpha is less than one
is a constant,
it implies that it takes order
one probes.
OK, so if alpha is a constant,
it takes order one probes.
OK, but it's helpful to
understand what's happening with
the constant.
So, for example,
if the table is 50% full,
so alpha is a half,
what's the expected number of
probes by this analysis?
Two, because one over one minus
a half is two.
If I let the table fill up to
90%, how many probes do I need
on average?
Ten.
So, you can see that as you
fill up the table,
the cost is going dramatically,
OK?
And so, typically,
you don't let the table get too
full.
OK, you don't want to be
pushing 99.9% utilization.
Oh, I got this great hash table
that's got full utilization.
It's like, yeah,
and it's slow.
It's really,
really slow,
OK, because as alpha approaches
one, the time is approaching and
essentially m,
or n.
Good.
So, next time,
we are going to address head-on
in what was one of the most,
I think, interesting ideas in
algorithms.
We are going to talk about how
you solve this problem that no
matter what hash function you
pick, there's a bad set of keys.
OK, so next time we're going to
show that there are ways of
confronting that problem,
very clever ways.
And we use a lot of math for it
so will be a really fun lecture.