OK.
One there, three,
three, four,
good, four.
OK, and our answer:
four.
So this is blindingly fast code
if you code this up,
OK, because it gets to use the
fact that modern machines in
particular do very well on
regular strides through memory.
So, if you're just plowing
through memory across like this,
OK, and your two-dimensional
array is stored in that order,
which it is,
otherwise you go this way,
stored in that order.
This can really fly in terms of
the speed of the calculation.
So, how much time did it take
us to do this?
Yeah, order MN,
theta MN.
Yeah?
We'll talk about space in just
a minute.
OK, so hold that question.
Good question,
good question,
already, wow,
good, OK, how do I now figure
out, remember,
we had the simplification.
We were going to just calculate
the length.
OK, it turns out I can now
figure out a particular sequence
that matches it.
And basically,
I do that.
I can reconstruct the longest
common subsequence by tracing
backwards.
So essentially I start here.
Here I have a choice because
this one was dependent on,
since it doesn't have a bar
here, it was dependent on one of
these two.
So, let me go this way.
OK, and now I have a diagonal
element here.
So what I'll do is simply mark
the character that appeared in
those positions as I go this
way.
I have three here.
And now, let me keep going,
three here, and now I have
another one.
So that means this character
gets selected.
And then I go up to here,
OK, and then up to here.
And now I go diagonally again,
which means that this character
is selected.
And I go to here,
and then I go here.
And then, I go up here and this
character is selected.
So here is my longest common
subsequence.
And this was just one path
back.
I could have gone a path like
this and gotten a different
longest common subsequence.
OK, so that simplification of
just saying, look,
let me just run backwards and
figure it out,
that's actually pretty good
because it means that by just
calculating the value,
then figuring out these back
pointers to let me reconstruct
it is a fairly simple process.
OK, if I had to think about
that to begin with,
it would have been a much
bigger mess.
OK, so the space,
I just mentioned,
was order MN because we still
need the table.
So, you can actually do the min
of m and n.
OK, to get to your question,
how do you do the min of m and
n?
Diagonal stripes won't give you
min of m and n.
That'll give you the sum of m
and n.
So, going in stripes,
maybe I'm not quite sure I know
what you mean.
So, you're saying,
so what's the order I would do
here?
So, I would start.
I would do this one first.
Then which one would I do?
This one and this one?
And then, this one,
this one, this one,
like this?
That's a perfectly good order.
OK, and so you're saying,
then, so I'm keeping the
diagonal there all the time.
So, you're saying the length of
the diagonal is the min of m and
n?
I think that's right.
OK, there is another way you
can do it that's a little bit
more straightforward,
which is you compare m to n.
Whichever is smaller,
well, first of all,
let's just do this existing
algorithm.
If I just simply did row by
row, I don't need more than a
previous row.
OK, I just need one row at a
time.
So, I can go ahead and compute
just one row because once I
computed the succeeding row,
the first row is unimportant.
And in fact,
I don't even need the whole
row.
All I need is just the current
row that I'm on,
plus one or two elements of the
previous row,
plus the end of the previous
row.
So, I use a prefix of this row,
and an extra two elements,
and the suffix of this row.
So, it's actually,
you can do it with one row,
plus order one element.
And then, I could do it either
running vertically or running
horizontally,
whichever one gives me the
smaller space.
OK, and it might be that your
diagonal trick would work there
too.
I'd have to think about that.
Yeah?
Ooh, that's a good question.
So, you can do the calculation
of the length,
and run row plus order one
elements.
OK, and our exercise,
and this is a hard exercise,
OK, so that a good one to do is
to do small space and allow you
to reconstruct the LCS because
the naïve way that we were just
doing it, it's not clear how you
would go backwards from that
because you've lost the
information.
OK, so this is actually a very
interesting and tricky problem.
And, it turns out it succumbs
of all things to divide and
conquer, OK, rather than some
more straightforward tabular
thing.
OK: so very good practice,
for example,
for the upcoming take home
quiz, OK, which is all design
and cleverness type quiz.
OK, so this is a good one for
people to take on.
So, this is basically the
tabular method that's called
dynamic programming.
OK, memo-ization is not dynamic
programming, even though it's
related.
It's memo-ization.
And, we're going to see a whole
bunch of other problems that
succumb to dynamic programming
approaches.
It's a very cool method,
and on the homework,
so let me just mention the
homework again.
On the homework,
we're going to look at a
problem called the edit distance
problem.
Edit distance is you are given
two strings.
And you can imagine that you're
typing in a keyboard with one of
the strings there.
And what you have to do is by
doing inserts,
and deletes,
and replaces,
and moving the cursor around,
you've got to transform one
string to the next.
And, each of those operations
has a cost.
And your job is to minimize the
cost of transforming the one
string into the other.
This actually turns out also to
be useful for computational
biology applications.
And, in fact,
there have been editors,
screen editors,
text editors,
that implement algorithms of
this nature in order to minimize
the number of characters that
have to be sent as IO in and out
of the system.
So, the warning is,
you better get going on your
programming on problem one on
the homework today if at all
possible because whenever I
assign programming,
since we don't do that as sort
of a routine thing,
I'm just concerned for some
people that there will not be
able to get things like the
input and output to work,
and so forth.
We have example problems,
and such, on the website.
And we also have,
you can write it in any
language you want,
including Matlab,
Python, whatever your favorite,
the solutions will be written
in Java and Python.
OK, so the fastest solutions
are likely to be written in c.
OK, you can also do it in
assembly language if you care
to.
You laugh.
I used to be in assembly
language programmer back in the
days of yore.
OK, so I do encourage people to
get started on this because let
me mention, the other thing is
that this particular problem on
this problem set is an
absolutely mandatory problem.
OK, all the problems are
mandatory, but as you know you
can skip them and it doesn't
hurt you too much if you only
skip one or two.
This one, you skip,
hurts big time:
one letter grade.
It must be done.