I know this is pretty boring.
At this point we are just
applying this stupid theorem.
How about n^2/lg n?
What is the answer?
Good.
In this case no one should
answer.
It is a big tricky.
I forget exactly the answer.
I think it is like n^2 log log
n over log n,
no?
Oh, no.
n^2 log log n,
that's right.
Yeah.
But you shouldn't know that,
and this doesn't follow from
the master method.
This is something you would
have to solve,
probably with the
recursion-tree would be a good
way to do this one,
and you need to know some
properties of logs to know how
that goes.
But here the master method does
not apply.
And so you have to use a
different method.
OK.
The last thing I want to do is
tell you why the master method
is true, and that makes it much
more intuitive,
especially using
recursion-trees,
why everything works.
This is a sketch of a proof,
not the full thing.
You should read the proof in
the textbook.
It is not that much harder than
what I will show,
but it is good for you to know
the formal details.
I don't have time here to do
all of the details.
I will just tell you the
salient parts.
This is the proof sketch or the
intuition behind the master
method.
What we are going to do is just
take the recursion-tree for this
recurrence and add up each level
and then add up all the levels
and see what we get.
We start with f(n) at the top
after we have expanded one
level.
Then we get a different
problems, each of n/b.
And after we expand them it
will f(n/b) for each one.
They are all the same size.
Then we expand all of those and
so on, and we get another a
subproblems from there.
We are going to get like
f((n/b)^2).
That is sort of decreasing
geometrically the size,
and so on and so on and so on,
until at the bottom we get
constant size problems.
This is a bit special because
this is the base case,
but we have some other constant
at the bottom.
We would like to know how many
leaves there are,
but that is a little bit tricky
at the moment.
Let's first compute the height
of this tree.
Let me draw it over here.
What is the height of this
tree?
I start with a problem of size
n.
I want to get down to a problem
of size 1.
How long does that take?
How many levels?
This is probably too easy for
some and not at your fingertips
for others.
Log base b of n,
good.
The height of this tree is
n^(log_b(a)),
because it is just how many
times I divide by b until I get
down to 1.
That is great.
Now I should be able to compute
the number of leaves because I
have branching factor a,
I have height h.
The number of leaves is a^h,
a^log_b(n).
Let me expand that a little
bit.
a^log_b(n), properties of logs,
we can take the n downstairs
and put the a upstairs,
and we get n^(log_b(a)).
Our good friend n^(log_b(a)).
So, that is why Our good friend
n^(log_b(a)) is so important in
the master method.
What we are doing is comparing
f, which is the top level,
to n^(log_b(a)),
which up to theta is the bottom
level.
Now the leaves are all at the
same level because we are
decreasing at the same rate in
every branch.
If I add up the cost at the
bottom level,
it is Theta(n^(log_b(a))).
I add up the things at the top
level it is f(n),
not terribly exciting.
But the next level,
this is a little bit more
interesting, is af(n/b),
which should look familiar if
you had the master method
already memorized,
it is that.
So, we know that af(n/b) has
decreased by some constant
factor, 1-epsilon prime.
We have gone down.
This is a constant factor
smaller than this.
And then you sum up the next
level.
It is going to be like
a^2f(n/b^2).
I see that I actually wrote
this wrong, the parentheses.
Sorry about that.
It is not (n/b)^2.
It is (n/b^2).
So, this sequence,
in Case 3 at least,
is decreasing geometrically.
If it is decreasing
geometrically up to constant
factors, it is dominated by the
biggest term,
which is f(n).
Therefore, in Case 3,
we get Theta[f(n)].
Let's look at the other cases,
and let me adapt those cases to
how much time we have left.
Wow, lot's of time.
Five minutes.
Tons of time.
What to do?
Let me write that down.
Case 3, the costs decrease.
Now, this is a place I would
argue where the dot,
dot, dot is pretty obvious.
Here, this is damn simple,
it is a^kf(n/b^k).
And, in Case 3,
we assume that the costs
decrease geometrically as we go
down the tree.
That was sort of backwards to
start with Case 3.
Let's do Case 1,
which is sort of the other
intuitively easy case.
In Case 1, we know that f(n) is
polynomially smaller than this
thing.
And we are sort of changing by
this very simple procedure in
the middle.
I am going to wave my hands if
this is where you need a more
formal argument.
I claim that this will increase
geometrically.
It has to increase
geometrically because this f(n)
is polynomially smaller than
this one, you are going to get
various polynomials in the
middle which interpret
geometrically from the small one
to the big one.
Therefore, the big one
dominates because it is,
again, geometric series.
As I said, this is intuition,
not a formal argument.
This one was pretty formal
because we assumed it,
but here you need a bit more
argument.
They may not increase
geometrically but they could
increase faster,
and that is also fine.
So, in Case 3,
you are dominated,
I mean you are always dominated
by the biggest term in a
geometric series.
Here it happens to be f(n) and
here you are dominated by
n^(log_b(a)) with a bottom term,
oh, Theta.
Case 2, here it is pretty easy
but you need to know some
properties of logs.
In Case 2, we assume that all
of these are basically the same.
I mean, we assume that the top
is equal to the bottom.
And this is changing in this
very procedural way.
Therefore, all of the ones in
the middle have to be pretty
much the same.
Not quite because here we don't
have the log factor.
Here we have a log to the k.
We have n^(log_b(a)) times log
to the kn.
Here we don't have the log to
the k.
So, the logs do disappear here.
It turns out the way they
disappear is pretty slowly.
If you look at the top half of
these terms, they will all have
log to the k.
The bottom half they will start
to disappear.
I am giving you some oracle
information.
If you take logs and you don't
change the argument by too much,
the logs remain.
Maybe halfway is too far.
The claim is that each level is
roughly the same,
especially the upper most
levels are all asymptotically
equal.
Roughly the same.
And, therefore,
the cost is one level,
here like f(n) times the number
of levels, h.
And h is log base b of n.
B is a constant so we don't
care.
This is Theta(lg n).
And, therefore,
we get T(n) = (n^(log_b(a))
lg^(k+1)(n)) times another log
n.
So, we get [f(n)lg n].
That is the very quick sketch.
Sorry, I am being pretty fuzzy
on Cases 1 and 2.
Read the proof because you will
have to, at some point,
manipulate logs in that way.
And that is all.
Any questions?
Or, you are all eager to go.
OK.
Thanks.
See you Wednesday.