these would be zeros,
and these would be twos,
right, for the accounting
method if we do the same thing,
because this is halfway
through, right,
all zeros, and that we add two
for each one that we're going
in.
So, I function is,
in fact, telling me what the
actual cost is.
OK, everybody with me?
OK, so that's what we mean by
this particular potential
function.
OK, so now let's add up the
amortized cost of the i'th
insert.
OK, so that's the amortized
cost of the i'th insert,
just by definition.
OK, and now that's equal to,
well, what is c_i?
Do we still have that written
down somewhere,
or have we erased that at this
point?
I think we erased it.
Well, we can write it down
again.
It is i if i minus one is an
exact power of two.
And, it's one otherwise.
That's c_i.
That's this term,
plus, and now phi of D_i:
so, what is that?
phi of D_i is this business,
2i minus two ceiling of log i
minus 2i minus one minus two
ceiling of log of I minus one.
OK, so that's the amortized
cost.
That's a nice,
pretty formula,
right?
OK, let's hope it simplifies a
little.
OK, so that's equal to,
well, we have the i and the one
here, if, etc.,
that business,
plus, OK, well,
we have some things we can
cancel here, right?
So here, we have 2i minus 2i.
That cancels.
And then we have what's left
over here is a minus two.
So, that's a plus two.
And now, I have minus this term
plus this term.
That's a lot prettier.
OK, it's still a mess.
We've got to case analysis.
Why is it suggestive of a case
analysis?
We have a case.
OK, so let's do a case
analysis.
OK, so case one,
I minus one is an exact power
of two.
So then, c_i hat is equal to,
well, c_i is now just i.
That's that case.
And then we have the rest
there, plus two,
minus two, ceiling of log i
minus two ceiling of log of i
minus one.
OK, and that's equal to i plus
two.
Well, let's see.
If I minus one is an exact
power of two,
what is this term?
i minus one is an exact power
of two.
Plus, thank you,
sorry about that.
It's good to have students,
let me say, because,
boy, my math is so bad.
This is actually why I end up
being a pretty good theoretician
is because I don't ever trust
what I've written down.
And so, I write it down in a
way that I can verify it because
otherwise I just am not smart
enough to carry through five
equations in a row and expect
that everyone is going to be
transformed appropriately.
OK, so you write it down.
So I always write it down so I
can verify it.
And that fortunately has the
side benefit that other people
can understand what I've done as
well.
OK, so what is this one?
This is two to the log of i
minus one because the ceiling,
if this is an exact power of
two, right, then ceiling of log
of i minus one is just log of i
minus one.
So, this is two to the log of i
minus one, which is i minus one,
right?
Yeah?
OK.
OK, if it's an exact power of
two, then the log is an integer,
right?
So, taking the ceiling,
it doesn't matter,
get rid of the ceiling.
OK, this one,
however, is not an exact power
of two.
But what is it?
It's just one more than this
guy.
We know that i minus one is not
an exact power of two,
so it's going to be the next
bigger one.
OK, so that means this is what?
So, it's going to be,
how do these two compare?
How much bigger is this one
than this one?
It's twice the size.
We know what this one is.
OK, or it can reason it from
first principles.
This is going to be the log of
i minus one plus one.
OK, and so then you can reduce
it to this.
So, you've got to think about
those floors and ceilings,
right?
It's like, what's happening in
the round off there?
OK, so now we can simplify
this.
OK, so what do we have here?
We have, OK,
so if I multiply this through,
I have an i plus two minus 2i
plus two plus i minus one.
I know a lot of you,
probably 90% of you will do
this step.
You will go directly from this
step to the last step.
And that's where 30% of you,
or some number,
will get it wrong.
OK, so let me encourage you to
do that step.
OK, it's easier to find your
bugs if you take it slow.
Actually, taking it slow is
faster in the long run.
It's hard to teach young
stallions, or phillies,
or whatever,
OK?
Just take it easy.
Just patience,
just do it slow,
get it right.
It's actually faster.
OK, everybody knows the
tortoise and hare story.
Yeah, yeah, yeah,
OK, but nobody believes it.
OK, so now here we have 2i
here, an i here,
and an i here.
And then, that leaves us with
two plus two minus one,
equals three.
Awesome, awesome.
OK, amortized cost is three
when i minus one is an exact
power of two.
OK, case two.
OK, i minus one is not an exact
power of two.
So then we have c_i hat is
equal to, now instead of i it's
one plus, and then the two minus
two to the ceiling of log i plus
two to the ceiling of log of i
minus one.
OK, now what can somebody tell
me about these two terms in the
case where i minus one is not an
exact power of two?
What are they?
Equal.
Why is that?
Yeah, the ceiling is going to
do the same thing to both,
going to take it up to the same
integer.
So these two things are equal,
which means this is equal to
three.
OK, so therefore,
n inserts, OK,
so now I say,
oh, the amortized cost is three
for every operation for every
insert.
So therefore,
n inserts costs,
well, the amortized cost of
each is three.
So n of them,
the amortized cost is 3n.
That's an upper bound on the
worst-case true costs.
So, n inserts costs order n in
the worst case.
OK, there is a bug in this
analysis.
It's a minor bug.
It's the one I pointed out
before the first insert has
amortized cost of two,
and not three.
I didn't actually deal with
that one carefully enough.
OK, so that's an exercise to
just go and look to see where it
is that that happens and how you
show that, in fact,
the amortized cost of the first
one is two, OK,
where that shows up.
OK, so to summarize,
actually let me summarize over
here, conclusions about
amortized analysis.
So amortized costs provide a
clean abstraction for data
structure performance.
So, what I can tell somebody,
so suppose I built a dynamic
table, for example,
OK.
It's easier to say,
in terms of your own
performance modeling,
it costs a constant amount of
time for each insert.
As long as you don't care about
real-time behavior,
but only the aggregate
behavior, that's a great
abstraction for the performance
Rather than saying it's got
that complicated thing which
sometimes cost you a lot,
how do they reason about that?
But you could say every
operation costs me order one,
that's really simple.
But they have to understand,
it's order one in an amortized
sense, OK.
So, if they do have a real-time
constraint to make,
amortized doesn't cut it.
OK, but for many problems,
it's perfectly good.
It lets me explain it rather
simply.
OK, we will see some other data
structures that have amortized
costs where different operations
have different amortized costs.
And the nice thing about that
is I just add up,
what's the cost of all my
different operations,
OK, where there is a different
cost for each operation?
Some will be log n.
Some will be order one,
or whatever.
Add them up:
that's an upper bound on the
true costs.
OK: tremendous simplification
in abstracting and reasoning
about those complicated data
structures.
OK, now, so this is probably,
this is huge.
OK, abstraction,
you know, computer science,
what teach you through four
years of undergraduate,
and another year if you go on
to M.Eng., and then if you get a
Ph.D., it's another 15 years or
whatever it takes to get a Ph.D.
OK, all you teach about is
abstraction: abstraction,
abstraction,
abstraction.
So, this is a powerful
abstraction: quite good.
Now, we learned three methods.
In general, any method can be
used.
You can convert one to the
other.
But each has situations where
it is arguably simplest or most
precise.
So, any of the methods can be
used.
However, you must learn all of
them, OK, because there are
going to be some situations
where you need one,
where it's better to do one,
better to do another.
If you're reading in the
literature, you want to know
these different ways of doing
it.
And that means that even though
you may get really comfortable
with accounting,
OK, in an exam,
or whatever,
I may say solve this with a
potential function argument.
So, you want to be comfortable
with all the methods,
OK.
Last point is that,
in fact, different potential
functions or accounting costs
may yield different bounds.
OK, so when you do an amortized
analysis, there's nothing to say
that one set of costs is better
than another.
So, just as an example,
OK, in any data structure
generally that supports delete,
I can amortize all the deletes
against the inserts.
So, in general,
what I could do is say deletes
are free, OK,
and charge twice as much for
each insert.
OK, charging enough when I do
the insert to amortize it
against the delete.
That you could do with an
accounting method.
You can also do it with a
potential method,
the potential,
then, being the number of items
that I actually have in my data
structure times the cost of the
delete for each of those items.
OK, so the point is that I can
allocate costs in different
ways.
Or I could have amortized costs
which are equal to the true
costs.
So, there are different ways
that I could assign amortized
costs.
There is no one way,
OK, and choosing different ones
may yield different bounds.
It may not, but it may yield
different bounds.
OK, generally it does yield
different ones.
OK, next time:
an amazing use of potential
functions.
OK, the stuff is cool,
but let me tell you,
Wednesday's lecture:
amazing.
Amazing the type of analysis we
are going to be able to do.