order of log n time.
Now, this constant will depend
on alpha.
So, you know,
you want error probability one
over n^100 is probably going to
be, like, 100 log n.
It's still log n.
OK, this is a very strong claim
about the tale of the
distribution of the running time
of search, very strong.
Let me give you an idea of how
strong it is.
How many people know what
Boole's inequality is?
How many people know what the
union bound is in probability?
You should.
It's in appendix c.
Maybe you'll know it by the
theorem.
It's good to know it by name.
It's sort of like linearity of
expectations.
It's a lot easier to
communicate to someone.
Linearity of expectations:
instead of saying,
you know that thing where you
sum up all the expectations of
things, and that's the
expectation of the sum?
It's a lot easier to say
linearity of expectation.
So, let me quiz you in a
different way.
So, if I take a bunch of
events, and I take their union,
either this happens or this
happens, or so on.
So, this is the inclusive OR of
k events.
And, instead,
I look at the sum of the
probabilities of those events.
OK, easy question:
are these equal?
No, unless they are
independent.
But can I say anything about
them, any relation?
Smaller, yeah.
This is less than or equal to
that.
OK, this should be intuitive to
you from a probability point of
view.
Look at the textbook.
OK: very basic result,
trivial result almost.
What does this tell us?
Well, suppose that E_i is some
kind of error event.
We don't want it to happen.
OK, and suppose,
mix some letters here.
Suppose I have a bunch of
events which occur with high
probability.
OK, call those E_i complement.
So, suppose,
so this is the end of that
statement, E_i complement occurs
with high probability.
OK, so then the probability of
E_i is very small,
polynomially small.
One over n to the alpha for any
alpha I want.
Now, suppose I take a whole
bunch of these events,
and let's say that k is
polynomial in n.
So, I take a bunch of events,
which I'd like to happen.
They all occur with high
probability.
There is only polynomially many
of them.
So let's say,
let me give this constant a
name.
Let's call it c.
Let's say I take n to the c
such events.
Well, what's the probability
that all those events occur
together?
Because they should rest of the
time occurred together because
each one occurs most of the
time, occurs with high
probability.
So, I want to look at E_1 bar
intersect, E_2 bar,
and so on.
So, each of these occurs as
high probability.
What's the chance that they all
occur?
It's also with high
probability.
I'm changing the alpha.
So, the union bound tells me
the probability of any one of
these failing,
the probability of this
failing, or this failing,
or this failing,
which is this thing,
is, at most,
the sum of the probabilities of
each failure.
These are the error
probabilities.
I know that each of them is,
at most, one over n to the
alpha, with a constant in front.
If I add them all up,
there's only n to the c of
them.
So, I take this error
probability, and I multiply by n
to the c.
So, I get like n to the c over
n to the alpha,
which is one over n to the
alpha minus c.
I can set alpha as big as I
want.
So, I said it much,
much bigger than c,
and this event occurs with high
probability.
I sort of made a mess here,
but this event occurs with high
probability because of this.
Whatever the constant is here,
however many events I'm taking,
I just set alpha to be bigger
than that.
And, this event will occur with
high probability,
too.
So, when I say here that every
search of cost order log n with
high probability,
not only do I mean that if you
look at one search,
it costs order log n with high
probability.
You look at another search,
and it costs log n with high
probability.
I mean, if you take every
search, all of them take order
log n time with high
probability.
So, this event that every
single search you do takes order
log n, is true with high
probability estimate the number
of searches you are doing is
polynomial in n.
So, I'm assuming that I'm not
using this data structure
forever, just for a polynomial
amount of time.
But, who's got more than a
polynomial amount of time
anyway?
This is MIT.
So, hopefully that's clear.
We'll see it a few more times.
Yeah?
The algorithm doesn't depend on
Alpha.
The question is how do you
choose alpha in the algorithm.
So, we don't need to.
This is just sort of for an
analysis tool.
This is saying that the farther
out you get, so you say,
well, what's the probability
that more than ten log n.
Well, it's like one over n^10.
Let's say it's linear.
Well, what's the chance that
you're more than 20 log n?
Well that's one over n^20.
So, the point is the tail of
this distribution is getting a
really small,
really fast.
And, such using alpha is more
like sort of for your own
feeling good.
OK, you can set it to 100,
and then n is at least two.
So, that's like one over 2^100
chance that you fail.
That's damn small.
If you've got a real random
number generator,
the chance that you're going to
hit one over 2^200 is pretty
tiny, right?
So, let's say you set alpha to
256, which is always a good
number.
2^256 is much bigger than the
number of particles in the known
universe, so,
the light matter.
So, actually I think this even
accounts for some notion of dark
matter.
So, this is really,
really, really big.
So, the chance that you pick a
random particle in the universe
that happens to be your favorite
particle, this one right here,
that's over one over 2^256,
or even smaller.
So, set alpha to 256,
the chance to your algorithm
takes more than order log n time
is a lot smaller than the chance
that a meteor strikes your
computer at the same time that
it has a flooding point error,
at the same time that the earth
explodes because they're putting
a transport through this part of
the solar system at the same
time, I mean,
I could go on,
right?
It's really,
really unlikely that you are
more than log n.
And how unlikely:
you get to choose.
But it's just in the analysis
the algorithm doesn't depend on
it.
It's the same algorithm,
very cool.
Sometimes, with high
probability, bounds depends on
alpha.
I mean, the algorithm depends
on alpha.
But here, it will not.
OK, away we go.
So now you all understand the
claim.
So let's do a warm up.
We will also need this fact.
But it's pretty easy.
The lemma is that with high
probability, the number of
levels in the skip list is order
log n.
I think it's order log n,
certainly.
So, how do we prove that
something happens with high
probably?
Compute the probability that it
happened; show that it's high.
Even if you don't know what
high probability means,
in fact, I used to ask that
earlier on.
So, let's compute the chance
that it doesn't happen,
the error probability,
because that's just a one minus
the cleaner.
So, I'd like to say,
let's say, that it's,
at most, c log n levels.
So, what's the error
probability for that event?
This is sort of an event.
I'll put it in squiggles just
for, all set.
This is the probability that
they are strictly greater than c
log n levels.
So, I want to say that that
probability is particularly
small, polynomially small.
Well, how do I make levels?
When I insert an element,
the probability half,
it goes up.
And, the number of levels in
the skip list is the max over
all the elements of how high it
goes up.
But, max, oh,
that's a mess.
All right, you can compute the
expectation of the max if you
have a bunch of unknown
variables; there is expectation
there is a constant,
and you take the max.
It's like log in and
expectation, but we want a much
stronger statement.
And, we have this Boole's
inequality that says I have a
bunch of things,
polynomially many things.
Let's say we have n items.
Each one independently,
I don't even care if it's a
dependent.
If it goes up more than c log
n, yeah, the number of levels is
more than c log n.
So, this is,
at most, and then I want to
know, do any of those events
happen for any of the n
elements?
So, I just multiplied by n.
It's certainly,
at most, n times the
probability that x gets
promoted, this much here,
greater than or equal to log n
times.
OK, if I pick,
for any element,
x, because it's the same for
each element.
They are done independently.
So, I'm just summing over x
here, and that's just a factor
of n.
Clear?
This is Boole's inequality.
Now, what's the probability
that x gets promoted c log n
times?
We did this before for log n.
It was one over n.
For c log n,
it's one over n to the c.
OK, this is n times two.
Let's be nicer:
one half to the power of c log
n.
One half to the power of c log
n is one over two to the c log
n.
The log n comes out here,
becomes an n.
We get n to the c.
So, this is n divided by n to
the c, which is n to the c minus
one.
And, I get to choose c to be
whatever I want.
So, I choose c minus one to be
alpha.
I think exactly that.
Oh, sorry, one over n to the c
minus one.
Thank you.
It better be small.
This is an upper bound.
So, probability is polynomially
small.
I get to choose,
and this is a bit of the trik.
I'm choosing this constant to
be large, large enough for
alpha.
The point is,
as c grows, alpha grows.
Therefore, I can set alpha to
be whatever I want,
set c accordingly.
So, there's a little bit more
words that have to go here.
But, they're in the notes.
I can set alpha to be as large
as I want.
So, I can make this probability
as small as I want in the
polynomial sets.
So, that's it.
Number of levels,
order log n:
wasn't that easy?
Rules and equality,
the point is that when you're
dealing with high probability,
use Boole's inequality.
And, anything that's true for
one element is true for all of
them, just like that.
Just lose a factor of n,
but that's just one in the
alpha, and alpha is big:
big constant,
but it's big.
OK, so let's prove the theorem.
High probability searches cost
order log n.
We now know the height is order
log n, but it depends how
balanced this thing is.
It depends how long the chains
are to really know that a search
costs log n.
Just knowing a bound on the
height is not enough,
unlike a binary tree.
So, we have one cool idea for
this analysis.
And it's called backwards
analysis.
So, normally you think of a
search as starting in the top
left corner going left and down
until you get to the item that
you're looking for.
I'm going to look at the
reverse process.
You start at the item you're
looking for, and you go left and
up until you get to the top left
corner.
The number of steps in those
two walks is the same.
And, I'm not implementing an
algorithm here,
I'm just doing analysis.
So, those are the same
processes, just in reverse.
So, here's what it looks like.
You have a search,
and it starts,
which really means that it ends
at a node in the bottom list.
Then, each time you visit a
node in this search,
you either go left or up.
And, when do you go left or up?
Well, it depends with the coin
flip was.
So, if the node wasn't promoted
at this level.
So, if it wasn't promoted
higher, and that happened
exactly when we got a tails.
Then, we go left,
which really means we came from
the left.
Or, if we got a heads,
so if this node was promoted to
the next level,
which happened whenever we got
a heads at that particular
moment.
This is in the past some time
when we did the insertion.
Then we go, or came from,
up.
And, we stop at the root.
This is really where we start;
same thing.
So, either at the root or I'm
also going to think of this as
stopping at minus infinity.
OK, that was a bit messy,
but let me review.
So, normally we start up here.
Well, just looking at
everything backwards,
and in brackets is what's
really happening.
So, this search ends at the
node you were looking for.
It's always in the bottom list.
Then it says,
well, was this node promoted
higher?
If it was, I came from above.
If not, I came to the left.
It must have been in the bottom
chain somewhere.
OK, and that's true at every
node you visit.
It depends whether that quite
slipped heads or tails at the
time that you inserted that node
into that level.
But, these are just a bunch of
events.
I'm just going to check,
what is the probability that
its heads, and what is the
probability that a tails?
It's always a half.
Every time I look at a coin
flip, when it was flipped,
there was a probability of half
going out of their way.
That's the magic.
And, I'm not using that these
events are independent anyway.
For every element that I search
for, for every value,
x, that's another search.
Those events may not be
independent.
I can still use Boole's
inequality and conclude that all
of them are order log n with
high probability.
As long as I can prove that any
one event happens with high
probability.
So, I don't need independence
between, I knew that these coin
flips in a single search are
independent, but everything
else, for different searches I
don't care.
So, how long can this process
go on?
We want to know how many times
can I make this walk?
Well, when I hit the root node,
I'm done.
Well, how quickly would I hit
the root node?
Well, with probability,
a half, I go up each step.
The number of times I go up is,
at most, the number of levels
minus one.
And that's order log n with
high probability.
So, this is the only other
idea.
So, we are now improving this
theorem.
So, the number of up moves in a
search, which are really down
moves, but same thing,
is less than the number of
levels.
Certainly, you can't go up more
than there are levels in the
search.
And in insert,
you can go arbitrarily high.
But a search:
as high as you can go.
And this is,
at most, c log n with high
probability.
This is what we proved in the
lemma.
So, we have a bound on the
number of up moves.
Half of the moves,
roughly, are going to be up
moves.
So, this pretty much down to
the number of moves.
Not quite.
So, what this means is that
with high probability,
so this is the same
probability, but I could choose
that as high as I want by
setting c large enough.
The number of moves,
in other words,
the cost of the search is at
most the number of coin flips
until we get c long n heads,
right, because in every step of
the search, I make a move,
and then I flip another coin,
conceptually.
There is another independent
coin lying there.
And it's either heads or tails.
Each of those is independent.
So, how many independent coin
flips does it take until I get c
log n heads?
The claim is that that's order
log n with high probability.
But we need to prove that.
So, this is a claim.
So, if you just sit there with
a coin, and you want to know how
many times does it take until I
get c log n heads,
the claim is that that number
is order log n with high
probability.
As long as I prove that,
I know that the total number of
steps I make,
which is the number of heads
and tails is order log n because
I definitely know the number of
heads is, at most,
c log n.
The claim is that the number of
tails can't be too much bigger.
Notice, I can't just say c
here.
OK, it's really important that
I have log n.
Why?
Because with high probability,
it depends on n.
This notion depends on n.
Log n: it's true.
Anything bigger that log n:
it's true, like n.
If I put n here,
this is also true.
But, if I put a constant or a
log log n, this is not true.
It's really important that I
have log n here because my
notion of high probability
depends on what's written here.
OK, it's clear so far.
We're almost done,
which is good because I just
ran out of time.
Sorry, we're going to go a
couple minutes over.
So, I want to compute the error
probability here.
So, I want to compute the
probability that there is less
than c log n heads.
Let me skip this step.
So, I will be approximate and
say, what's the probability that
there is, at most,
c log n heads?
So, I need to say how many
coins we are flipping here for
what this event is.
So, I need to specify this
constant.
Let's say we flip ten c log n
coins.
Now I want to look at the error
probability under that event.
The probability that there is
at most c log n heads among
those ten c log n flips.
So, the claim is this should be
pretty small.
It's going to depend on ten.
Then I'll choose ten to be
arbitrarily large,
and I'll be done,
OK, make my life a little bit
easier.
Well, I would ask you normally,
but this is 6.042 material.
So, what's the probability that
we have, at most,
this many heads?
Well, that means that nine c
log n of the coins,
because there are ten c log n
flips, c log n heads at most,
nine c log n at least better be
tails.
So this is the probability that
all those other guys become
tails, which is already pretty
small.
And then, there is this
permutation thing.
So, if I had exactly c log n
heads, this would be the number
of ways to rearrange c log n
heads among ten c log n coin
flips.
OK, that's just the number of
permutations.
So, this is a bit big,
which is kind of annoying.
This is really,
really small.
The claim is this is much
smaller than that is big.
So, this is just some math.
I'm going to whiz through it.
So, you don't have to stay too
long.
But you should go over it.
You should know that y choose x
is, at most, ey over x to the x,
good fact.
Therefore, this is,
at most, ten c log n over c log
n, also known as ten.
These cancel.
There's an e out here.
And then I raise that to the c
log n power.
OK, then I divide by two to the
power, nine c log n.
OK, so what's this?
This is e times ten to the c
log n divided by two to the nine
c log n.
OK, claim this is very big.
This is not so big,
because I have a nine here.
So, let's work it out.
This e times ten,
that's a good number,
we can put upstairs.
So, we get log of e times ten,
ten times, e,
and then c log n.
And then, we have over two to
the nine c log n.
So, we have this two to the c
log n in both cases.
So, this is two to the log,
ten e minus nine,
c, log n: some basic algebra.
So, I'm going to set,
not quite.
This is one over two to the
nine minus log:
so, just inverting everything
here, negating the sign in here.
And, this is my alpha because
the rest is n.
So, this is one over n to the
alpha when alpha is this
particular value:
nine minus log of ten times e
times c.
It's a bit of a strange thing.
But, the point is,
as ten goes to infinity,
nine here is the number one
smaller than ten,
right?
We subtracted one somewhere
along the way.
So, as ten goes to infinity,
this is basically,
this is ten minus one.
This is log of ten times e.
e doesn't really matter.
The point is,
this is logarithmic in ten.
This is linear in ten.
The thing that's linear in ten
is much bigger than the thing
that's logarithmic in ten.
This is called abusive
notation.
OK, as ten goes to infinity,
this goes to infinity,
gets bigger.
And, there is a c out here.
But, for any value of c that
you want, whatever value of c
you wanted in that claim,
I can make alpha arbitrarily
large by changing the constant
in the big O,
which here was ten.
OK, so that claim is true with
high probability.
Whatever probability you want,
which tells you alpha,
you set a constant effort of
the log N to be this number,
which grows,
and you're done.
You get the claim that is order
log N heads, order log N flips
with the high probability,
therefore.
[None of the steps?] in the
search is order log N with high
probability.
Really cool stuff;
read the notes.
Sorry I went so fast at the
end.