so this is going to be K,
I believe, for each of these.
This is square root of K
squared is the cost of these
levels.
And, you keep going.
I don't particularly care what
the bottom looks like because at
the top we have K^2.
That we have K times root K
plus one cost at the next level.
This is K to the three halves
plus K.
OK, so we go from K^2 to K to
the three halves plus K.
This is a super-geometric.
It's like an exponential
geometric decrease.
This is decreasing really fast.
So, it's order K^2.
That's my hand-waving argument.
OK, so the cost is basically
the size of the buffers at the
top level, the total space.
We're going to need this.
It's actually theta K^2 because
I have a theta K^2 here.
We are going to be this in
order to analyze the time.
That's why it mentioned it.
It's not just a good feeling
that the space is not too big.
In fact, the funnel is a lot
smaller than a total input size.
The input size is K^3.
But that's not so crucial.
What's crucial is that it's
K^2, and we'll use that in the
analysis.
OK, naturally,
this thing is laid out
recursively.
You recursively store the
funnel, top funnel.
Then, for example,
you write out each buffer as a
consecutive array,
in this case.
There's no recursion there.
So just write them all out one
by one.
Don't interleave them or
anything.
Store them in order.
And that, you write out
recursively these funnels,
the bottom funnels.
OK, any way you do it
recursively, as long as each
funnel remains a consecutive
chunk of memory,
each buffer remains a
consecutive chuck of memory,
the time analysis that we are
about to do will work.
OK, let me actually give you
the algorithm that we're
analyzing.
In order to make the funnel go,
what we do is say,
initially, all the buffers are
empty.
Everything is at the bottom.
And what we are going to do is,
say, fill the root buffer.
Fill this one.
And, that's a recursive
algorithm, which I'll define in
a second, how to fill a buffer.
Once it's filled,
that means everything has been
pulled up, and then it's merged.
OK, so that's how we get
started.
So, merge means to merge
algorithm is fill the topmost
buffer, the topmost output
buffer.
OK, and now,
here's how you fill a buffer.
So, in general,
if you expand out this
recursion all the way,
in the base case,
I didn't mention you sort of
get a little node there.
So, if you look at an arbitrary
buffer in this picture that you
want to fill,
so this one's empty and you
want to fill it,
then immediately below it will
be a vertex who has two
children, two other buffers.
OK, maybe they look like this.
You have no idea how big they
are, except they are the same
size.
It could be a lot smaller than
this one, a lot bigger,
we don't know.
But in the end,
you do get a binary structure
out of this just like we did
with the binary search tree at
the beginning.
So, how do we fill this buffer?
Well, we just merge these two
child buffers as long as we can.
So, we merge the two children
buffers as long as they are both
non-empty.
So, in general,
the invariant will be that this
buffer, let me write down a
sentence.
As long as a buffer is
non-empty, or whatever is in
that buffer, and hasn't been
used already,
it's a prefix of the merged
output of the entire subtree
beneath it.
OK, so this is a partially
merged subsequence of everything
down here.
This is a partially merged
subsequence of everything down
here.
I can just merge element by
element off the top,
and that will give me outputs
to put there until one of them
gets emptied.
And, we have no idea which one
will empty first just because it
depends on the order.
OK, whenever one of them
empties, we recursively fill it,
and that's it.
That's the algorithm.
Whenever one empties --
-- we recursively fill it.
And at the base case at the
leaves, there's sort of nothing
to do.
I believe you just sort of
directly read from an input
list.
So, at the very bottom,
if you have some note here
that's trying to merge between
these two, that's just a
straightforward merge between
two lists.
We know how to do that with two
parallel scans.
So, in fact,
we can merge the entire thing
here and just spit it out to the
buffer.
Well, it depends how big the
buffer is.
We can only merge it until the
buffer fills.
Whenever a buffer is full,
we stop and we pop up the
recursive layers.
OK, so we keep doing this merge
until the buffer we are trying
to fill fills,
and that we stop,
pop up.
OK, that's the algorithm for
merging.
Now, we just have to analyze
the algorithm.
It's actually not too hard,
but it's a pretty clever
analysis.
And, to top it off,
it's an amortization,
your favorite.
OK, so we get one last practice
at amortized analysis in the
context of cache oblivious
algorithms.
So, this is going to be a bit
sophisticated.
We are going to combine all the
ideas we've seen.
The main analysis idea we've
seen is that we are doing this
recursion in the construction,
and if we imagine,
we take our K funnel,
we split it in the middle
level, make a whole bunch of
square root of K funnels,
and so on, and then we cut
those in the middle level,
get fourth root of K funnels,
and so on, and so on,
at some point the funnel we
look at fits in cache.
OK, before we said if it's in a
block.
Now, we're going to say that at
some point, one of these funnels
will fit in cache.
Each of the funnels at that
recursive level of detail will
fit in cache.
We are going to analyze that
level.
We'll call that level J.
So, consider the first
recursive level of detail,
and I'll call it J,
at which every J funnel we have
fits, let's say,
not only does it fit in cache,
but four of them fit in cache.
It fits in one quarter of the
cache.
OK, but we need to leave some
cache extra for doing other
things.
But I want to make sure that
the J funnel fits.
OK, now what does that mean?
Well, we've analyzed space.
We know that the space of a J
funnel is about J^2,
some constant times J^2.
We'll call it C times J^2.
OK, so this is saying that C
times J^2 is at most,
M over 4, one quarter of the
cache.
OK, that means a J funnel that
happens at the size sits in the
quarter of the cache.
OK, at some point in the
recursion, we'll have this big
tree of J funnels,
with all sorts of buffers in
between them,
and each of the J funnels will
fit.
So, let's think about one of
those J funnels.
Suppose J is like the square
root of K.
So, this is the picture because
otherwise I have to draw a
bigger one.
So, suppose this is a J funnel.
It has a bunch of input
buffers, has one output buffer.
So, we just want to think about
how the J funnel executes.
And, for a long time,
as long as these buffers are
all full, this is just a merger.
It's doing something
recursively, but we don't really
care.
As soon as this whole thing
swaps in, and actually,
I should be drawing this,
as soon as the funnel,
the output buffer,
and the input buffer swap in,
in other words,
you bring all those blocks in,
you can just merge,
and you can go on your merry
way merging until something
empties or you fill the output.
So, let's analyze that.
Suppose everything is in
memory, because we know it fits.
OK, well I have to be a little
bit careful.
The input buffers are actually
pretty big in total size because
the total size is K to the three
halves here versus K to the one
half.
Actually, this is of size K.
Let me draw a general picture.
We have a J funnel,
because otherwise the
arithmetic is going to get
messy.
We have a J funnel.
Its size is C times J^2,
we're supposing.
The number of inputs is J,
and the size of them is pretty
big.
Where did we define that?
We have a K funnel.
The total input size is K^3.
So, the total input size here
would be J^3.
We can't afford to put all that
in cache.
That's an extra factor of J.
But, we can afford to one block
per input.
And for merging,
that's all we need.
I claim that I can fit the
first block of each of these
input arrays in cash at the same
time along with the J funnel.
And so, for that duration,
as long as all of that is in
cache, this thing can merge at
full speed just like we were
doing parallel scans.
You use up all the blocks down
here, and one of them empties.
You go to the next block in the
input buffer and so on,
just like the normal merge
analysis of parallel arrays,
at this point we assume that
everything here is fitting in
cache.
So, it's just like before.
Of course, in fact,
it's recursive but we are
analyzing it at this level.
OK, I need to prove that you
can fit one block per input.
It's not hard.
It's just computation.
And, it's basically the way
that these funnels were designed
was so that you could fit one
block per input buffer.
And, here's the argument.
So, the claim is you can also
fit one memory block in the
cache per input buffer.
So, this is in addition to one
J funnel.
You could also fit one block
for each of its input buffers.
OK, this is of the J funnel.
It's not any funnel because
bigger funnels are way too big.
OK, so here's how we prove
that.
J^2 is at most a quarter M.
That's what we assumed here,
actually CJ2.
I'm not going to bother with
the C because that's going to
make my life even harder.
OK, I think this is even a
weaker constraint.
So, the size of our funnel
proves about J^2.
That's at most a quarter of the
cache.
That implies that J,
if we take square roots of both
sides, is at most a half square
root of M.
OK, also, we know that B is at
most square root of M because M
is at least B squared.
So, we put these together,
and we get J times B is at most
a half M.
OK, now I claim that what we
are asking for here is J times B
because in a J funnel,
there are J input arrays.
And so, if you want one block
each, that costs a space of B
each.
So, for each input buffer we
have one block of size B,
and the claim is that that
whole thing fits in half the
cache.
And, we've only used a quarter
of the cache.
So in total,
we use three quarters of the
cache and that's all we'll use.
OK, so that's good news.
We can also fit one more block
to the output.
Not too big a deal.
So now, as long as this J
funnel is running,
if it's all in cache,
all is well.
What does that mean?
Let me first analyze how long
it takes for us to swap in this
funnel.
OK, so how long does it take
for us to read all the stuff in
a J funnel and one block per
input buffer?
That's what it would take to
get started.
So, this is swapping in a J
funnel, which means reading the
J funnel in its entirety,
and reading one block per input
buffer.
OK, the cost of the swap in is
pretty natural.
The size of the buffer divided
by B, because that's just sort
of a linear scan to read it in,
and we need to read one block
per buffer.
These buffers could be all over
the place because they're pretty
big.
So, let's say we pay one memory
transfer for each input buffer
just to get started to read the
first block.
OK, the claim is,
and here we need to do some
more arithmetic.
This is, at most,
J^3 over B.
OK, why is it,
at most, J^3 over B?
Well, this was the first level
at which things fit in cache.
That means the next level
bigger, which is J^2,
which has size J^4,
should be bigger than cache.
Otherwise we would have stopped
then.
OK, so this is just more
arithmetic.
You can either believe me or
follow the arithmetic.
We know that J^4 is at least M.
So, this means that,
and we know that M is at least
B^2.
Therefore, J^2,
instead of J^4,
we take the square root of both
sides, J^2 is at least B.
OK, so certainly J^2 over B is
at most J^3 over B.
But also J is at most J^3 over
B because J^2 is at least B.
Hopefully that should be clear.
That's just algebra.
OK, so we're not going to use
this bound because that's kind
of complicated.
We're just going to say,
well, it causes J^3 over B to
get swapped in.
Now, why is J^3 over B a good
thing?
Because we know the total size
of inputs to the J funnel is
J^3.
So, to read all of the inputs
to the J funnel takes J^3 over
B.
So, this is really just a
linear extra cost to get the
whole thing swapped in.
It sounds good.
To do the merging would also
cost J^3 over B.
So, the swap-in causes J^3 over
B to merge all these J^3
elements.
If they were all there in the
inputs, it would take J^3 over B
because once everything is
there, you're merging at full
speed, one per B items per
memory transfer on average.
OK, the problem is you're going
to swap out, which you may have
imagined.
As soon as one of your input
buffers empties,
let's say this one's almost
gone, as soon as it empties,
you're going to totally
obliterate that funnel and swap
in this one in order to merge
all the stuff there,
and fill this buffer back up.
This is where the amortization
comes in.
And this is where the log
factor comes in because so far
it we've basically paid a linear
cost.
We are almost done.
So, we charge,
sorry, I'm jumping ahead of
myself.
So, when an input buffer
empties, we swap out.
And we recursively fill that
buffer.
OK, I'm going to assume that
there is absolutely no reuse,
that is recursive filling
completely swapped everything
out and I have to start from
scratch for this funnel.
So, when that happens,
I feel this buffer,
and then I come back and I say,
well, I go swap it back in.
So when the recursive call
finishes, I swap back in.
OK, so I recursively fill,
and then I swap back in.
And, at the swapping back in
costs J^3 over B.
I'm going to charge that cost
to the elements that just got
filled.
So this is an amortized
charging argument.
How many are there?
It's the only question.
It turns out,
things are really good,
like here, for the square root
of K funnel, we have each buffer
has size K to the three halves.
OK, so this is a bit
complicated.
But I claim that the number of
elements here that fill the
buffer is J^3.
So, if you have a J funnel,
each of the input buffers has
size J^3.
It should be correct if you
work it out.
So, we're charging this J^3
over B cost to J^3 elements,
which sounds like you're
charging, essentially,
one over B to each element.
Sounds great.
That means that,
so you're thinking overall,
I mean, there are N elements,
and to each one you charge a
one over B cost.
That sounds like the total
running time is N over B.
It's a bit too fast for
sorting.
We lost the log factor.
So, what's going on is that
we're actually charging to one
element more than once.
And, this is something that we
don't normally do,
never done it in this class,
but you can do it as long as
you bound that the number of
times you charge.
OK, and wherever you do a
charging argument,
you say, well,
this doesn't happen too many
times because whenever this
happens, this happens.
You should say,
you should prove that the thing
that you're charging to,
Ito charged to that think very
many times.
So here, I have a quantifiable
thing that I'm charging to:
elements.
So, I'm saying that for each
element that happened to come
into this buffer,
I'm going to charge it a one
over B cost.
How many times does one element
get charged?
Well, each time it gets charged
to, it's moved into a new
buffer.
How many buffers could it move
through?
Well, it's just going up all
the time.
Merging always goes up.
So, we start here and you go to
the next buffer,
and you go to the next buffer.
The number of buffers you visit
is the right log,
it turns out.
I don't know which log that is.
So, the number of charges of a
one over B cost to each element
is the number of buffers it
visits, and that's a log factor.
That's where we get an extra
log factor on the running time.
It is, this is the number of
levels of J funnels that you can
visit.
So, it's log K divided by log
J, if I got it right.
OK, and we're almost done.
Let's wrap up a bit.
Just a little bit more
arithmetic, unfortunately.
So, log K over log J.
Now, J^2 is like M,
roughly.
It might be square root of M.
But, log J is basically log M.
There's some constants there.
So, the number of charges here
is theta, log K over log M.
So, now this is a bit,
we haven't seen this in
amortization necessarily,
but we just need to count up
total amount of charging.
All work gets charged to
somebody, except we didn't
charge the very initial swapping
in to everybody.
But, every time we do some
swapping in, we charge it to
someone.
So, how many times does
everything it charged?
Well, there are N elements.
Each gets charged to a one over
B cost, and the number of times
it gets charged is its log K
over log M.
So therefore,
the total cost is number of
elements times a one over B
times this log thing.
OK, it's actually plus K.
We forgot about a plus K,
but that's just to get started
in the very beginning,
and start on all of the input
lists.
OK, this is an amortization
analysis to prove this bound.
Sorry, what was N here?
I assumed that I started out
with K cubed elements at the
bottom.
The total number of elements in
the bottom was K^3 theta.
OK, so I should have written
K^3 not M.
This should be almost the same
as this, OK, but not quite.
This is log based M of K,
and if you do a little bit of
arithmetic, this should be K^3
over B times log base M over B
of K over B plus K.
That's what I want to prove.
Actually there's a K^3 here
instead of a K,
but that's just a factor of
three.
And this follows because we
assume we are not in the base
case.
So, K is at least M,
which is at least B^2,
and therefore K over B is omega
square root of K.
OK, so K over B is basically
the same as K when you put it in
a log.
So here we have log base M.
I turned it into log base M
over B.
That's even worse.
It doesn't matter.
And, I have log of K.
I replaced it with K over B,
but K over B is basically
square root of K.
So in a log,
that's just a factor of a half.
So that concludes the analysis
of the funnel.
We get this crazy running time,
which is basically sorting
bound plus a little bit.
We plug that into our funnel
sort, and we get,
magically, optimal cache
oblivious sorting just in time.
Tuesday is the final.
The final is more in the style
of quiz one, so not too much
creativity, mostly mastery of
material.
It covers everything.
You don't have to worry about
the details of funnel sort,
but everything else.
So it's like quiz one but for
the entire class.
It's three hours long,
and good luck.
It's been a pleasure having
you, all the students.
I'm sure Charles agrees,
so thanks everyone.
It was a lot of fun.