analysis.
But the key thing here is that
what we are going to do the
recursion, we're going to have
at least n over 4 elements in
whatever the smaller thing is.
OK, but let's start.
It turns out the work is the
hard part of this.
Let's start with critical path
length.
OK, look at that,
critical path length.
OK, so parallel merge,
so infinity of n is going to
be, at most, so if the smaller
piece has at least a quarter,
what's the larger piece going
to be of these two things here?
So, we have two problems
responding off.
Now, we really have to do max
because they're not symmetric.
Which one's going to be worse?
One could have,
at most, three quarters,
OK, of n.
Woops, 3n, of 3n over 4 plus,
OK, so the worst of those two
is going to be three quarters of
the elements plus,
what?
Plus log n.
What's the log n?
The binary search.
OK, and that gives me a
solution of, this ends up being
n to the, what?
n to the zero,
right.
OK, it's n to the log base four
thirds of one.
OK, it was the log of anything
of one is zero.
So, it's n to the zero.
So that's just one compared
with log n, tack on this log
squared n.
So, we have a critical path of
log squared n.
That's good news.
Now, let's hope that we didn't
blow up the work by a
substantial amount.
OK, so the work is PM_1 of n is
equal to, OK,
so we don't know what the split
is.
So let's call it alpha.
OK, so alpha n in one side,
and then the work on the other
side will be PM of one of one
minus alpha n plus,
and then still order of log n
to the binary search where,
as we've said,
alpha is going to fall between
one quarter and three quarters.
OK, how do we solve a
recurrence like this?
What's the technical name for
this kind of recurrence?
Hairy.
It's a hairy recurrence.
How do we solve hairy
recurrences?
Substitution.
OK, good.
OK, so we're going to say PM
one of k is less than or equal
to, OK, I want to make a good
guess here, OK,
because I've fooled around with
it.
I want it to be linear,
so it's going to have a linear
term, a times k minus,
and then I'm going to do b log
k.
So, this is this trick of
subtracting a low order term.
Remember that in substitution
in order to make it stronger?
If I just did ak it's not going
to work because here I would get
n, and then when I did this
substitution I'm going to get a
alpha n, and then a one minus
alpha n, and those two together
are already going to add up to
everything here.
So, there's no way I'm going to
get it down when I add this term
in.
So, I need to subtract
something from both of these so
as to absorb this term,
OK?
So, I'm skipping over those
steps, OK, because we did those
steps in lecture two or
something.
OK, so that's the thing I'm
going to guess where a and b are
greater than zero.
OK, so let's do the
substitution.
OK, so we have PM one of n is
less than or equal to,
OK, we substitute this
inductive hypothesis in for
these two guys.
So, we get a alpha n minus b
log of alpha n plus a of one
minus alpha n minus b log of one
minus alpha, maybe another
parentheses there,
one minus alpha n,
and even leave myself enough
space here plus a of one minus
alpha n minus b log of one minus
alpha, maybe another parenthesis
there, one minus alpha n.
I didn't even leave myself
enough space here.
Plus, let me just move this
over so I don't end up using too
much space.
So, b log of one minus alpha n
plus theta of log n.
How's that?
Are we OK on that?
OK, so that's just
substitution.
Let's do a little algebra.
That's equal to a of times
alpha na times one minus alpha
n.
That's just an,
OK, minus, well,
the b isn't quite so simple.
OK, so I have a b term.
Now I've got a whole bunch of
stuff there.
I've got log of alpha n.
I have, then,
this log of one minus alpha n,
OK, I'll start with the n,
and then plus theta log n.
Did I do that right?
Does that look OK?
OK, so look at that.
OK, so now let's just multiply
some of this stuff out.
So, I have an minus b times,
well, log of alpha n is just
log alpha plus log n.
And then I have plus log of one
minus alpha plus log n,
OK, plus theta log n.
That's just more algebra,
OK, using our rules for logs.
Now let me express this as my
solution minus my desired
solution minus a residual,
an minus b log n,
OK, minus, OK,
and so that was one of these b
log n's, right,
is here.
And the other one's going to
end up in here.
I have B times log n plus log
of alpha times one minus alpha
minus, oops, I've got too many.
Do I have the right number of
closes.
Close that, close that,
that's good,
minus theta log n.
Two there.
Boy, my writing is degrading.
OK, did I do that right?
Do I have the parentheses
right?
That matches,
that matches,
good.
And then B goes to that,
OK, good.
OK, and I claim that is less
than or equal to AN minus B log
n if we choose B large enough.
OK, this mess dominates this
because this is basically a log
n here, and this is essentially
a constant.
OK, so if I increase B,
OK, times log n,
I can overcome that log n,
whatever the constant is,
hidden by the asymptotic
notation, OK,
such that B times log n plus
log of alpha times one minus
alpha dominates the theta log n.
OK, and I can also choose my
base condition to be big enough
to handle the initial
conditions, whatever they might
be.
OK, so we'll choose A big
enough --
-- to satisfy the base of the
induction.
OK, so thus PM_1 of n is equal
to theta n, OK?
So I actually showed O,
and it turns out,
the lower bound that it is
omega n is more straightforward
because the recurrence is easier
because I can do the same
substitution.
I just don't have to subtract
off low order terms.
OK, so it's actually theta,
not just O.
OK, so that gives us a log,
what did we say the critical
path was?
The critical path is log
squared n for the parallel
merge.
So, let's do the analysis of
merge sort using this.
So, the work is,
as we know already,
T_1 of n is theta of n log n
because our work that we just
analyzed was order n,
same as for the serial
algorithm, OK?
The critical path length,
now, is T infinity of n is
equal to, OK,
so in normal merge sort,
we have a problem of half the
size, T of n over 2 plus,
now, my critical path for
merging is not order n as it was
before.
Instead, it's just over there.
Log squared n,
there we go.
OK, and so that gives us theta
of log cubed n.
So, our parallelism is then
theta of n over log cubed n.
And, in fact,
the best that's been done is,
sorry, log squared n,
you're right.
Log squared n because it's n
log n over log cubed n.
It's n over log squared n,
OK?
And the best,
so now I wonder if I have a
typo here.
I have that the best is,
p bar is theta of n over log n.
Is that right?
I think so.
Yeah, that's the best to date.
That's the best to date.
By Occoli, I believe,
is who did this.
OK, so you can actually get a
fairly good, but it turns out
sorting is a really tough
problem to parallelize to get
really good constants where you
want to make it so it's running
exactly the same.
Matrix multiplication,
you can make it run in parallel
and get straight,
hard rail, linear speed up with
a number of processors.
There is plenty of parallelism,
and running on more processors,
every processor carries a full
weight.
With sorting,
typically you lose,
I don't know,
20% in my experience,
OK, in terms of other stuff
going on because you have to
work really hard to get the
constants of this merge
algorithm down to the constants
of that normal merge,
right?
I mean that's a pretty good
algorithm, right,
the one that just goes,
BUZZING SOUND,
and just takes two lists and
merges them like that.
So, it's an interesting issue.
And a lot of people work very
hard on sorting,
because it's a hugely important
problem, and how it is that you
can actually get the constants
down while still guaranteeing
that it will scale up with a
number of processors.
OK, that's our little sojourn
into parallel land,
and next week we're going to
talk about caching,
which is another very important
area of algorithms,
and of programming in general.