that this other thing was a
minimum spanning tree.
OK: so, a lower weight spanning
tree than T results,
and that's a contradiction --
-- than T results.
And that's a contradiction,
OK?
How are we doing?
Everybody with me?
OK, now we get to do some
algorithms.
Yea!
So, we are going to do an
algorithm called Prim's
algorithm.
Prim eventually became a very
high-up at AT&T because he
invented this algorithm for
minimum spanning trees,
and it was used in all of the
billing code for AT&T for many
years.
He was very high up at Bell
Labs back in the heyday of Bell
Laboratories.
OK, so it just shows,
all you have to do is invent an
algorithm.
You too can be a president of a
corporate monopoly.
Of course, the government can
do things to monopolies,
but anyway, if that's your
mission in life,
invent an algorithm.
OK, so here's the idea.
What we're going to do is we're
going to maintain V minus A as a
priority queue.
We'll call it Q.
And each vertex,
we're going to key each vertex
in Q with the weight of the
least weight edge,
connecting it to a vertex in A.
So here's the code.
So, we're going to start out
with Q being all vertices.
So, we start out with A being,
if you will,
the empty set.
OK, and what we're going to do
it is the least weight edge,
therefore, for everything in
the priority queue is basically
going to be infinity because
none of them have any edges.
The least weight edge to the
empty set is going to be empty.
And then, we're going to start
out with one guy.
We'll call him S,
which will set to zero for some
arbitrary S in V.
And then, the main part of the
algorithm kicks in.
So that's our initialization.
OK, when we do the analysis,
I'm going to write some stuff
on the left hand side of the
board.
So if you're taking notes,
you may want to also leave a
little bit of space on the left
hand side of your notes.
So, while Q is not empty,
we get the smallest element out
of it.
And then we do some stuff.
That's it.
And the only thing I should
mention here is,
OK, so let's just see what's
going on here.
And then we'll run it on the
example.
OK, so what we do is we take
out the smallest element out of
the queue at each step.
And then for each step in the
adjacency list,
in other words,
everything for which I have an
edge going from v to u,
we take a look,
and if v is still in our set V
minus A, so things we'(V,E)
taken out are going to be part
of A.
OK, every time we take
something out,
that's going to be a new A that
we construct.
At every step,
we want to find,
what's the cheapest edge
connecting that A to everything
else?
We basically are going to take
whatever that cheapest thing is,
OK, add that edge in,
and now bring that into A and
find the next cheapest one.
And we just keep repeating the
process.
OK, we'll do it on the example.
And what we do,
is every time we bring it in,
I keep track of,
what was the vertex responsible
for bringing me in.
And what I claim is that at the
end, if I look at the set of
these pairs that I'(V,E) made
here, V and pi of V,
that forms the minimum spanning
tree.
So let's just do this.
And, what's that?
We're all set up.
So let's get rid of these guys
here because we are going to
recompute them from scratch.
OK, so you may want to copy the
graph over again in your notes.
I was going to do it,
but it turned out,
this is exactly the board is
going to erase this.
OK, well let me just modify it.
OK, so we start out.
We make everything be infinity.
OK, so that's where I'm going
to keep the key value.
OK, and then what I'm going to
do is find one vertex.
And I'm going to call him S.
And I'm going to do this vertex
here.
We'll call that S.
So basically,
I now make him be zero.
And now, what I do,
is I execute extract min.
So basically,
what I'll do is I'll just shade
him like this,
indicating that he has now
joined the set A.
So, this is going to be A.
And this is element of V minus
A.
OK, so then what we do is we
take a look.
We extract him,
and then for each edge in the
adjacency list,
OK, so for each vertex in the
adjacency lists,
that these guys here,
OK, we're going to look to see
if it's still in Q,
that is, in V minus A.
And if so, and its key value is
less than what the value is at
the edge, there,
we're going to replace it by
the edge value.
So, in this case,
we're going to replace this by
seven.
We're going to replace this by
15, and we're going to replace
this by ten, OK,
because what we're interested
in is, what is the cheapest?
Now, notice that everything in
V minus A, that is,
what's in the priority queue,
everything in there,
OK, now has its cheapest way of
connecting it to the things that
I'(V,E) already removed,
the things that are in A.
OK, and so now I just,
OK, when I actually do that
update, there's actually
something implicit going on in
this priority queue.
And that is that I have to do a
decreased key.
So, there's an implicit
decrease of the key.
So, decreased key is a priority
queue operation that lowers the
value of the key in the priority
queue.
And so, that's implicitly going
on when I look at what data
structure I'm going to use to
implement that priority queue.
OK, so common data structures
for implementing a priority
queue are a min heap.
OK, so I have to make sure that
I'm actually doing this
operation.
I can't just change it and not
affect my heap.
So, there is an implicit
operation going on there.
OK, now I repeat.
I find the cheapest thing,
oh, and I also have to set,
now, a pointer from each of
these guys back to u.
So here, this guy sets a
pointer going this way.
This guy sets a pointer going
this way, and this guy sets a
pointer going this way.
That's my pi thing that's going
to keep track of who caused me
to set my value to what it is.
So now, we go in and we find
the cheapest thing,
again.
And we're going to do it fast,
too.
OK, this is a fast algorithm.
OK, so now we're going to go do
this again.
So now, what's the cheapest
thing to extract?
This guy here,
right?
So, we'll take him out,
OK, and now we update all of
his neighbors.
So this guy gets five.
This guy gets 12.
This guy gets nine.
This guy we don't update.
We don't update him because
he's no longer in the priority
queue.
And all of these guys now,
we make point to where they're
supposed to point to.
And, we're done with that step.
Now we find the cheapest one.
What's the cheapest one now?
The five over here.
Good.
So, we take him out.
OK, we update the neighbors.
Here, yep, that goes to six
now.
And, we have that pointer.
And, this guy we don't do,
because he's not in there.
This guy becomes 14,
and this guy here becomes
eight.
So, we update that guy,
make him be eight.
Did I do this the right way?
Yeah, because pi is a function
of this guy.
So basically,
this thing, then,
disappears.
Yeah, did I have another one
that I missed?
12, yes, good,
it's removed,
OK, because pi is just a
function.
And now I'm OK.
OK, so now what do I do?
OK, so now my set,
A, consists of these three
things, and now I want the
cheapest edge.
I know it's in the minimum
spanning tree.
So let me just greedily pick
it.
OK, so what's the cheapest
thing now?
This guy appear?
Yeah, six.
So we take it.
We go to update these things,
and nothing matters here.
OK, nothing changes because
these guys are already in A.
OK, so now the cheapest one is
eight here.
Good.
So, we take eight out.
OK, we update this.
Nothing to be done.
This: nothing to be done.
This: oh, no,
this one, instead of 14 we can
make this be three.
So, we get rid of that pointer
and make it point that way.
Now three is the cheapest
thing.
So, we take it out,
and of course there's nothing
to be done over there.
And now, last,
I take nine.
And it's done.
And 15: it's done.
And the algorithm terminates.
OK, and as I look at,
now, all the edges that I
picked, those are exactly all
the edges that we had at the
beginning.
OK, let's do an analysis here.
OK, so let's see,
this part here costs me order
V, right?
OK, and this part,
let's see what we are doing
here.
Well, we're going to go through
this loop how many times?
V times.
It's V elements we put into the
queue.
We are not inserting anything.
We're just taking them out.
This goes V times,
OK, and we do a certain number
of extract Mins.
So, we're going to do order V
extract Mins.
And then we go to the adjacency
list, and we have some constant
things.
But we have these implicit
decreased keys for this stuff
here.
That's this thing here.
OK, and so how many implicit
decreased keys do we have?
That's going to be the
expensive thing.
OK, we have,
in this case,
the degree of u of those.
OK, so overall,
how many implicit decreased
keys do we have?
Well, we have V times through.
How big could the degree of u
be?
OK, it could be as big as V,
order V.
So, that's V^2 decreased use.
But we can do a better bound
than that.
How many do we really have?
Yeah, at most order E,
OK, because what am I doing?
I'm summing up the degrees of
all the vertices.
That's how many times I
actually execute that.
So, I have order E,
implicit decreased keys.
So the time overall is order V
times time for whatever the
extract Min is plus E times the
time for decreased key.
So now, let's look at data
structures, and we can evaluate
for different data structures
what this formula gives us.
So, we have different ways of
implementing a data structure.
We have the cost of extract
Min, and of decreased key,
and total.
So, the simplest way of
implementing a data structure is
an unsorted array.
If I have an unsorted array,
how much time does it take me
to extract the minimum element?
If I have an unsorted array?
Right, order V in this case
because it's an array of size V.
And, to do a decreased key,
OK, I can do it in order one.
So, the total is V^2,
good, order V^2 algorithm.
Or, as people suggested,
how about a binary heap?
OK, to do an extract Min in a
binary heap will cost me what?
O of log V.
Decreased key will cost me,
yeah, it turns out you can do
that in order log V because
basically you just have to
shuffle the value,
actually shuffle it up towards
the root, OK?
Or at log V.
And, the total cost therefore
is?
E log V, good.
Which of these is better?
It depends, good.
When is one better,
and when is the other better?
Yeah, if it's a dense graph,
E is close to V^2,
the array is better.
But if it's a sparse graph,
and E is much smaller than V^2,
then the binary heap is better.
So that motivated the invention
of a data structure,
OK, called a Fibonacci Heap.
So, Fibonacci Heap is covered
in Chapter 20 of CLRS.
We're not going to hold you
responsible for the content,
but it's an interesting data
structure because it's an
amortized data structure.
And it turns out that it is
data structure,
you can do extract Min in order
log V amortized time.
And remarkably,
you can do decreased key in
order one amortized.
So, when I plug those in,
what do I get over here?
What's that going to be?
Plug that it here.
It's going to be V times log V
plus E: E plus V log V.
These are amortized,
so what's this?
Trick question.
It's worst-case.
It's not amortized over here.
These are amortized,
but that's the beauty of
amortization.
I can say it's going to be
worst case: E plus V log V over
here, because when I add up the
amortized cost of my operations,
it's an upper bound on the true
costs.
OK, so that's why I say,
one of the beauties of this
amortized analysis,
and in particular,
being able to assign different
costs to different operations is
I can just add them up and I get
my worst-case costs.
So this is already V log V.
There are a couple other
algorithms just before I let you
go.
Kruskal's Algorithm in the book
uses another amortized data
structure called a disjoint set
data structure,
which also runs in E log V,
that is, this time:
runs in this time,
the same as using a binary
heap.
So, I'll refer you to the book.
The best algorithm to date with
this problem is done by our own
David Karger on the faculty here
with one of our former
graduates, Phil Kline,
who is now a professor at
Brown, and Robert Tarjan,
who is sort of like the master
of all data structures who was a
professor at Princeton in 1993.
OK, it's a randomized
algorithm, and it gives you
order V plus E expected time.
OK, so that's the best to date.
It's still open as to whether
there is a deterministic,
there is worst-case bound,
whether there is a worst-case
bound that is linear time.
OK, but there is a randomized
to linear time,
and otherwise,
this is essentially the best
bound without additional
assumptions.
OK, very cool stuff.
Next, we're going to see a lot
of these ideas of greedy and
dynamic programming in practice.