technique that is very useful
when thinking about shortest
paths.
And, it's a bit hard to guess,
especially if you haven't seen
it before.
This is useful in problem sets,
and in quizzes,
and finals, and everything.
So, keep this in mind.
I mean, I'm using it to prove
this rather simple theorem,
but the idea of changing the
graph, so I'm going to call this
constraint graph G.
Changing the graph is a very
powerful idea.
So, we're going to add a new
vertex, s, or source,
use the source,
Luke, and we're going to add a
bunch of edges from s because
being a source,
it better be connected to some
things.
So, we are going to add a zero
weight edge, or weight zero edge
from s to everywhere,
so, to every other vertex in
the constraint graph.
Those vertices are called v_i,
v_1 up to v_n.
So, I have my constraint graph.
But I'll copy this one so I can
change it.
It's always good to backup your
work before you make changes,
right?
So now, I want to add a new
vertex, s, over here,
my new source.
I just take my constraint
graph, whatever it looks like,
add in weight zero edges to all
the other vertices.
Simple enough.
Now, what did I do?
What did you do?
Well, I have a candidate source
now which can reach all the
vertices.
So, shortest path from s,
hopefully, well,
paths from s exist.
I can get from s to everywhere
in weight at most zero.
OK, maybe less.
Could it be less?
Well, you know,
like v_2, I can get to it by
zero minus two.
So, that's less than zero.
So I've got to be a little
careful.
What if there's a negative
weight cycle?
Oh no?
Then there wouldn't be any
shortest paths.
Fortunately,
we assume that there's no
negative weight cycle in the
original graph.
And if you think about it,
if there's no negative weight
cycle in the original graph,
we add an edge from s to
everywhere else.
We're not making any new
negative weight cycles because
you can start at s and go
somewhere at a cost of zero,
which doesn't affect any
weights.
And then, you are forced to
stay in the old graph.
So, there can't be any new
negative weight cycles.
So, the modified graph has no
That's good because it also has
paths from s,
and therefore it also has
shortest paths from s.
The modified graph has no
negative weight because it
didn't before.
And, it has paths from s.
There's a path from s to every
vertex.
There may not have been before.
Before, I couldn't get from v_2
to v_3, for example.
Well, that's still true.
But from s I can get to
everywhere.
So, that means that this graph,
this modified graph,
has shortest paths.
Shortest paths exist from s.
In other words,
if I took all the shortest path
weights, like I ran Bellman-Ford
from s, then,
I would get a bunch of finite
numbers, d of v,
for every value,
for every vertex.
That seems like a good idea.
Let's do it.
So, shortest paths exist.
Let's just assign x_i to be the
shortest path weight from s to
v_i.
Why not?
That's a good choice for a
number, the shortest path weight
from s to v_i.
This is finite because it's
less than infinity,
and it's greater than minus
infinity, so,
some finite number.
That's what we need to do in
order to satisfy these
constraints.
The claim is that this is a
satisfying assignment.
Why?
Triangle inequality.
Somewhere here we wrote
triangle inequality.
This looks a lot like the
In fact, I think that's the end
of the proof.
Let's see here.
What we want to be true with
this assignment is that x_j
minus x_i is less than or equal
to w_ij whenever ij is an edge.
Or, let's say v_i,
v_j, for every such constraint,
so, for v_i,
v_j in the edge set.
OK, so what is this true?
Well, let's just expand it out.
So, x_i is this delta,
and x_j is some other delta.
So, we have delta of s,
vj minus delta of s_vi.
And, on the right-hand side,
well, w_ij, that was the weight
of the edge from I to J.
So, this is the weight of v_i
to v_j.
OK, I will rewrite this
slightly.
Delta s, vj is less than or
equal to delta s,
vi plus w of v_i,
v_j.
And that's the triangle
inequality more or less.
The shortest path from s to v_j
is, at most, shortest path from
s to v_i plus a particular path
from v_i to v_j,
namely the single edge v_i to
v_j.
This could only be longer than
the shortest path.
And so, that makes the
right-hand side bigger,
which makes this inequality
more true, meaning it was true
before.
And now it's still true.
And, that proves it.
This is true.
And, these were all equivalent
statements.
This we know to be true by
triangle inequality.
Therefore, these constraints
are all satisfied.
Magic.
I'm so excited here.
So, we've proved that having a
negative weight cycle is exactly
when these system of difference
constraints are unsatisfiable.
So, if we want to satisfy them,
if we want to find the right
answer to x, we run
Bellman-Ford.
Either it says,
oh, no negative weight cycle.
Then you are hosed.
Then, there is no solution.
But that's the best you could
hope to know.
Otherwise, it says,
oh, there was no negative
weight cycle,
and here are your shortest path
weights.
You just plug them in,
and bam, you have your x_i's
that satisfy the constraints.
Awesome.
Now, it wasn't just any graph.
I mean, we started with
constraints, algebra,
we converted it into a graph by
this transform.
Then we added a source vertex,
s.
So, I mean, we had to build a
graph to solve our problem,
very powerful idea.
Cool.
This is the idea of reduction.
You can reduce the problem you
want to solve into some problem
you know how to solve.
You know how to solve shortest
paths when there are no negative
weight cycles,
or find out that there is a
negative weight cycle by
Bellman-Ford.
So, now we know how to solve
difference constraints.
It turns out you can do even
more.
Bellman-Ford does a little bit
more than just solve these
constraints.
But first let me write down
what I've been jumping up and
down about.
The corollary is you can use
Bellman-Ford.
I mean, you make this graph.
Then you apply Bellman-Ford,
and it will solve your system
of difference constraints.
So, let me put in some numbers
here.
You have m difference
constraints.
And, you have n variables.
And, it will solve them in
order m times n time.
Actually, these numbers go up
slightly because we are adding n
edges, and we're adding one
vertex, but assuming all of
these numbers are nontrivial,
m is at least n.
It's order MN time.
OK, trying to avoid cases where
some of them are close to zero.
Good.
So, some other facts,
that's what I just said.
And we'll leave these as
exercises because they're not
too essential.
The main thing we need is this.
But, some other cool facts is
that Bellman-Ford actually
optimizes some objective
functions.
So, we are saying it's just a
feasibility problem.
We just want to know whether
these constraints are
satisfiable.
In fact, you can add a
particular objective function.
So, you can't give it an
arbitrary objective function,
but here's one of interest.
x_1 plus x_2 plus x_n,
OK, but not just that.
We have some constraints.
OK, this is a linear program.
I want to maximize the sum of
the x_i's subject to all the
x_i's being nonpositive and the
difference constraints.
So, this we had before.
This is fine.
We noticed at some point you
could get from s to everywhere
with cost, at most,
zero.
So, we know that in this
assignment all of the x_i's are
negative.
That's not necessary,
but it's true when you run
Bellman-Ford.
So if you solve your system
using Bellman-Ford,
which is no less general than
anything else,
you happen to get nonpositive
x_i's.
And so, subject to that
constraint, it actually makes
them is close to zero as
possible in the L1 norm.
In the sum of these values,
it tries to make the sum as
close to zero,
it tries to make the values as
small as possible in absolute
value in this sense.
OK, it does more than that.
It cooks, it cleans,
it finds shortest paths.
It also minimizes the spread,
the maximum over all i of x_i
minus the minimum over all i of
x_i.
So, I mean, if you have your
real line, and here are the
x_i's wherever they are.
It minimizes this distance.
And zero is somewhere over
here.
So, it tries to make the x_i's
as compact as possible.
This is actually the L infinity
norm, if you know stuff about
norms from your linear algebra
class.
OK, this is the L1 norm.
I think it minimizes every LP
norm.
Good, so let's use this for
something.
Yeah, let's solve a real
problem, and then we'll be done
for today.
Next class we'll see the really
cool stuff, the really cool
application of all of this.
For now, and we'll see a cool
but relatively simple
application, which is VLSI
layout.
We talked a little bit about
VLSI way back and divide and
conquer.
You have a bunch of chips,
or you want to arrange them,
and minimize some objectives.
So, here's a particular,
tons of problems that come out
of VLSI layout.
Here's one of them.
You have a bunch of features of
an integrated circuit.
You want to somehow arrange
them on your circuit without
putting any two of them too
close to each other.
You have some minimum
separation like at least they
should not get top of each
other.
Probably, you also need some
separation to put wires in
between, and so on,
so, without putting any two
features too close together.
OK, so just to give you an
idea, so I have some objects and
I'm going to be a little bit
vague about how this works.
You have some features.
This is stuff,
some chips, whatever.
We don't really care what their
shapes look like.
I just want to be able to move
them around so that the gap at
any point, so let me just think
about this gap.
This gap should be at least
some delta.
Or, I don't want to use delta.
Let's say epsilon,
good, small number.
So, I just need some separation
between all of my parts.
And for this problem,
I'm going to be pretty simple,
just say that the parts are
only allowed to slide
horizontally.
So, it's a one-dimensional
problem.
These objects are in 2-d,
or whatever,
but I can only slide them an x
coordinate.
So, to model that,
I'm going to look at the left
edge of every part and say,
well, these two left edges
should be at least some
separation.
So, I think of it as whatever
the distance is plus some
epsilon.
But, you know,
if you have some funky 2-d
shapes you have to compute,
well, this is a little bit too
close because these come into
alignment.
But, there's some constraint,
well, for any two pieces,
I could figure out how close
they can get.
They should get no closer.
So, I'm going to call this x_1.
I'll call this x_2.
So, we have some constraint
like x_2 minus x_1 is at least d
plus epsilon,
or whatever you compute that
weight to be.
OK, so for every pair of
pieces, I can do this,
compute some constraint on how
far apart they have to be.
And, now I'd like to assign
these x coordinates.
Right now, I'm assuming they're
just variables.
I want to slide these pieces
around horizontally in order to
compactify them as much as
possible so they fit in the
smallest chip that I can make
because it costs money,
and time, and everything,
and power, everything.
You always want your chip
small.
So, Bellman-Ford does that.
All right, so Bellman-Ford
solves these constraints because
it's just a bunch of difference
constraints.
And we know that they are
solvable because you could
spread all the pieces out
arbitrarily far.
And, it minimizes the spread,
minimizes the size of the chip
I need, a max of x_i minus the
min of x_i.
So, this is it maximizes
compactness, or minimizes size
of the chip.
OK, this is a one-dimensional
problem, so it may seem a little
artificial, but the two
dimensional problem is really
hard to solve.
And this is,
in fact, the best you can do
with a nice polynomial time
algorithm.
There are other applications if
you're scheduling events in,
like, a multimedia environment,
and you want to guarantee that
this audio plays at least two
seconds after this video,
but then there are things that
are playing at the same time,
and they have to be within some
gap of each other,
so, lots of papers about using
Bellman-Ford,
solve difference constraints to
enable multimedia environments.
OK, so there you go.
And next class we'll see more
applications of Bellman-Ford to
all pairs shortest paths.
Questions?
Great.