can evaluate.
What is the evaluation?
If I want to simplify this
formula, what is that equal to?
Sorry. In the back there.
Yeah. OK.
That's just Theta(n^2),
good.
Because when you're saying is
the sum of consecutive numbers,
you mean what?
What's the mathematic term we
have for that so we can
communicate?
You've got to know these things
so you can communicate.
It's called what type of
sequence?
It's actually a series,
but that's OK.
What type of series is this
called?
Arithmetic series,
good.
Wow, we've got some sharp
people who can communicate.
This is an arithmetic series.
You're basically summing 1 + 2
+ 3 + 4, some constants in
there, but basically it's 1 + 2
+ 3 + 4 + 5 + 6 up to n.
That's Theta(n^2).
If you don't know this math,
there is a chapter in the book,
or you could have taken the
prerequisite.
Erythematic series.
People have this vague
recollection.
Oh, yeah.
Good.
Now, you have to learn these
manipulations.
We will talk about a bit next
time, but you have to learn your
theta manipulations for what
works with theta.
And you have to be very careful
because theta is a weak
notation.
A strong notation is something
like Leibniz notation from
calculus where the chain rule is
just canceling two things.
It's just fabulous that you can
cancel in the chain rule.
And Leibniz notation just
expresses that so directly you
can manipulate.
Theta notation is not like
that.
If you think it is like that
you are in trouble.
You really have to think of
what is going on under the theta
notation.
And it is more of a descriptive
notation than it is a
manipulative notation.
There are manipulations you can
do with it, but unless you
understand what is really going
on under the theta notation you
will find yourself in trouble.
And next time we will talk a
little bit more about theta
notation.
Is insertion sort fast?
Well, it turns out for small n
it is moderately fast.
But it is not at all for large
n.
So, I am going to give you an
algorithm that is faster.
It's called merge sort.
I wonder if I should leave
insertion sort up.
Why not.
I am going to write on this
later, so if you are taking
notes, leave some space on the
left.
Here is merge sort of an array
A from 1 up to n.
And it is basically three
steps.
If n equals 1 we are done.
Sorting one element,
it is already sorted.
All right.
Recursive algorithm.
Otherwise, what we do is we
recursively sort A from 1 up to
the ceiling of n over 2.
And the array A of the ceiling
of n over 2 plus one up to n.
So, we sort two halves of the
input.
And then, three,
we take those two lists that we
have done and we merge them.
And, to do that,
we use a merge subroutine which
I will show you.
The key subroutine here is
merge, and it works like this.
I have two lists.
Let's say one of them is 20.
I am doing this in reverse
order.
I have sorted this like this.
And then I sort another one.
I don't know why I do it this
order, but anyway.
Here is my other list.
I have my two lists that I have
sorted.
So, this is A[1] to A[|n/2|]
and A[|n/2|+1] to A[n] for the
way it will be called in this
program.
And now to merge these two,
what I want to do is produce a
sorted list out of both of them.
What I do is first observe
where is the smallest element of
any two lists that are already
sorted?
It's in one of two places,
the head of the first list or
the head of the second list.
I look at those two elements
and say which one is smaller?
This one is smaller.
Then what I do is output into
my output array the smaller of
the two.
And I cross it off.
And now where is the next
smallest element?
And the answer is it's going to
be the head of one of these two
lists.
Then I cross out this guy and
put him here and circle this
one.
Now I look at these two guys.
This one is smaller so I output
that and circle that one.
Now I look at these two guys,
output 9.
So, every step here is some
fixed number of operations that
is independent of the size of
the arrays at each step.
Each individual step is just me
looking at two elements and
picking out the smallest and
advancing some pointers into the
array so that I know where the
current head of that list is.
And so, therefore,
the time is order n on n total
elements.
The time to actually go through
this and merge two lists is
order n.
We sometimes call this linear
time because it's not quadratic
or whatever.
It is proportional to n,
proportional to the input size.
It's linear time.
I go through and just do this
simple operation,
just working up these lists,
and in the end I have done
essentially n operations,
order n operations each of
which cost constant time.
That's a total of order n time.
Everybody with me?
OK.
So, this is a recursive
program.
We can actually now write what
is called a recurrence for this
program.
The way we do that is say let's
let the time to sort n elements
to be T(n).
Then how long does it take to
do step one?
That's just constant time.
We just check to see if n is 1,
and if it is we return.
That's independent of the size
of anything that we are doing.
It just takes a certain number
of machine instructions on
whatever machine and we say it
is constant time.
We call that theta one.
This is actually a little bit
of an abuse if you get into it.
And the reason is because
typically in order to say it you
need to say what it is growing
with.
Nevertheless,
we use this as an abuse of the
notation just to mean it is a
constant.
So, that's an abuse just so
people know.
But it simplifies things if I
can just write theta one.
And it basically means the same
thing.
Now we recursively sort these
two things.
How can I describe that?
The time to do this,
I can describe recursively as T
of ceiling of n over 2 plus T of
n minus ceiling of n over 2.
That is actually kind of messy,
so what we will do is just be
sloppy and write 2T(n/2).
So, this is just us being
sloppy.
And we will see on Friday in
recitation that it is OK to be
sloppy.
That's the great thing about
algorithms.
As long as you are rigorous and
precise, you can be as sloppy as
you want.
[LAUGHTER] This is sloppy
because I didn't worry about
what was going on,
because it turns out it doesn't
make any difference.
And we are going to actually
see that that is the case.
And, finally,
I have to merge the two sorted
lists which have a total of n
elements.
And we just analyze that using
the merge subroutine.
And that takes us to theta n
time.
That allows us now to write a
recurrence for the performance
of merge sort.
Which is to say that T of n is
equal to theta 1 if n equals 1
and 2T of n over 2 plus theta of
n if n is bigger than 1.
Because either I am doing step
one or I am doing all steps one,
two and three.
Here I am doing step one and I
return and I am done.
Or else I am doing step one,
I don't return,
and then I also do steps two
and three.
So, I add those together.
I could say theta n plus theta
1, but theta n plus theta 1 is
just theta n because theta 1 is
a lower order term than theta n
and I can throw it away.
It is either theta 1 or it is
2T of n over 2 plus theta n.
Now, typically we won't be
writing this.
Usually we omit this.
If it makes no difference to
the solution of the recurrence,
we will usually omit constant
base cases.
In algorithms,
it's not true generally in
mathematics, but in algorithms
if you are running something on
a constant size input it takes
constant time always.
So, we don't worry about what
this value is.
And it turns out it has no real
impact on the asymptotic
solution of the recurrence.
How do we solve a recurrence
like this?
I now have T of n expressed in
terms of T of n over 2.
That's in the book and it is
also in Lecture 2.
We are going to do Lecture 2 to
solve that, but in the meantime
what I am going to do is give
you a visual way of
understanding what this costs,
which is one of the techniques
we will elaborate on next time.
It is called a recursion tree
technique.
And I will use it for the
actual recurrence that is almost
the same 2T(n/2),
but I am going to actually
explicitly, because I want you
to see where it occurs,
plus some constant times n
where c is a constant greater
than zero.
So, we are going to look at
this recurrence with a base case
of order one.
I am just making the constant
in here, the upper bound on the
constant be explicit rather than
implicit.
And the way you do a recursion
tree is the following.
You start out by writing down
the left-hand side of the
recurrence.
And then what you do is you say
well, that is equal to,
and now let's write it as a
tree.
I do c of n work plus now I am
going to have to do work on each
of my two children.
T of n over 2 and T of n over
If I sum up what is in here,
I get this because that is what
the recurrence says,
T(n)=2T(n/2)+cn.
I have 2T(n/2)+cn.
Then I do it again.
I have cn here.
I now have here cn/2.
And here is cn/2.
And each of these now has a
T(n/4).
And these each have a T(n/4).
And this has a T(n/4).
And I keep doing that,
the dangerous dot,
dot, dots.
And, if I keep doing that,
I end up with it looking like
this.
And I keep going down until I
get to a leaf.
And a leaf, I have essentially
a T(1).
That is T(1).
And so the first question I ask
here is, what is the height of
this tree?
Yeah.
It's log n.
It's actually very close to
exactly log n because I am
starting out at the top with n
and then I go to n/2 and n/4 and
all the way down until I get to
The number of halvings of n
until I get to 1 is log n so the
height here is log n.
It's OK if it is constant times
log n.
It doesn't matter.
How many leaves are in this
tree, by the way?
How many leaves does this tree
have?
Yeah.
The number of leaves,
once again, is actually pretty
close.
It's actually n.
If you took it all the way
down.
Let's make some simplifying
assumption.
n is a perfect power of 2,
so it is an integer power of 2.
Then this is exactly log n to
get down to T(1).
And then there are exactly n
leaves, because the number of
leaves here, the number of nodes
at this level is 1,
2, 4, 8.
And if I go down height h,
I have 2 to the h leaves,
2 to the log n,
that is just n.
We are doing math here,
right?
Now let's figure out how much
work, if I look at adding up
everything in this tree I am
going to get T(n),
so let's add that up.
Well, let's add it up level by
level.
How much do we have in the
first level?
Just cn.
If I add up the second level,
how much do I have?
cn.
How about if I add up the third
level?
cn.
How about if I add up all the
leaves?
Theta n.
It is not necessarily cn
because the boundary case may
have a different constant.
It is actually theta n,
but cn all the way here.
If I add up the total amount,
that is equal to cn times log
n, because that's the height,
that is how many cn's I have
here, plus theta n.
And this is a higher order term
than this, so this goes away,
get rid of the constants,
that is equal to theta(n lg n).
And theta(n lg n) is
asymptotically faster than
theta(n^2).
So, merge sort,
on a large enough input size,
is going to beat insertion
sort.
Merge sort is going to be a
faster algorithm.
Sorry, you guys,
I didn't realize you couldn't
see over there.
You should speak up if you
cannot see.
So, this is a faster algorithm
because theta(n lg n) grows more
slowly than theta(n^2).
And merge sort asymptotically
beats insertion sort.
Even if you ran insertion sort
on a supercomputer,
somebody running on a PC with
merge sort for sufficient large
input will clobber them because
actually n^2 is way bigger than
n log n once you get the n's to
be large.
And, in practice,
merge sort tends to win here
for n bigger than,
say, 30 or so.
If you have a very small input
like 30 elements,
insertion sort is a perfectly
decent sort to use.
But merge sort is going to be a
lot faster even for something
that is only a few dozen
elements.
It is going to actually be a
faster algorithm.
That's sort of the lessons,
OK?
Remember that to get your
recitation assignments and
attend recitation on Friday.
Because we are going to be
going through a bunch of the
things that I have left on the
table here.
And see you next Monday.