with that, then,
then we are either in case two
or three.
So, here's the dichotomy.
It turns out we've actually
seen all of the cases,
maybe not A versus B,
but we've seen the case of the
very beginning where we just
recolor.
That's case one.
The next thing we saw is,
well, it's kind of annoying
that the grandparent and ten,
so seven and ten were not
straight.
They were zigzagged.
So, case two is when they are
zigzagged.
It turns out if x is the right
child of its parent,
and the parent is the left
child of the grandparent,
that's a we've assumed so far,
that is case two.
OK, the other case is that x is
the left child of its parent.
So, then we have a left chain,
x, parent of x,
grandparent of x.
That is case three.
OK, I did not write else here
because what case two does is it
reduces to case three.
So, in case two,
we are going to do the stuff
that's here.
And then, we're going to do the
stuff here.
For case three,
we just do the stuff here.
Or in case one,
And then, that finishes the
three cases on the A side,
then back to this if.
We say else,
this is case B,
which is the same as A,
but reversing the notions of
left and right,
OK, in the natural way.
Every time we write left of
something, we instead write
right of something,
and vice versa.
So, this is really just
flipping everything over.
We'll just focus on category A.
And, let's see what we do in
each of the three cases.
We've seen it in an example.
But let's do it generically.
Let's do it here.
Sorry, there's one more line to
the algorithm,
I should say.
It's not aligned with here.
We color the root.
There's a chance when you do
all of this that the root
becomes red.
We always want the root to be
black.
If it's red,
we set it to black at the very
end of the algorithm.
This does not change the black
height property.
Everything will still be fine
because every path either goes
to the root or it doesn't,
every x to leaf path.
So, changing the root from red
to black is no problem.
It will increase the black
heights of everyone,
but all the paths will still
have the same value.
It will be one larger.
So, let's look at the three
cases.
And, I'm going to use some
notation.
Remember, we had triangles in
order to denote arbitrary
subtrees when we define a
rotation.
I'm going to use triangle with
a dot on top to say that this
subtree has a black root.
So, when I fill something
white, it means black because
I'm on a black board.
Sorry.
OK, and I also have the
property that each of these
triangles have the same black
height.
So, this will let me make sure
that the black height property,
property four,
is being observed.
So, let me just show you case
one.
We always want to make sure
property four is preserved
because it's really hard to get
that back.
It's essentially the balance of
the tree.
So, let's suppose we have some
node, C, left child,
A, right child,
B, and some subtrees hanging
off of those guys.
And, all of those subtrees have
the same black height.
So, in other words,
these things are all at the
same level.
OK, this is not quite what I
wanted, sorry.
So, I'm considering,
this is node x.
x is red, and its parent is
red.
Therefore, we need to fix
something.
We look at the node,
y, which is over here.
And, I'll call it,
the key is D.
The node is called y.
OK, it has subtrees hanging off
as well, all with the same black
height.
So, that will be true.
If all of these nodes are red,
then all of these nodes have
the same black height.
And therefore,
all of the child subtrees,
which have black roots,
all had to have the same black
height as well.
OK, so we're looking at a big
chunk of red children subtree of
a black node,
looking at all the stuff that
happens to be red.
In case one,
why is red so it participates?
So, a way to think of this as
if we converted into the
two-three-four-tree,
or tried to,
we would merge all of this
stuff into one node.
That's essentially what we're
doing here.
This is not a two-three-four
tree, though.
We now have five children,
which is bad.
This is why we want to fix it.
So, we're going to recolor in
case one.
And, we're going to take C.
Instead of making C black,
and A and D red,
we are going to make A and D
black, and C red.
So, C is red.
A is black.
D is black.
And, the subtrees are the same.
B is the same.
It's still red.
OK, now we need to check that
we preserve property four,
that all of the paths have the
same number of black nodes.
That follows because we know we
didn't touch these subtrees.
They all have the same black
height.
And, if you look at any path,
like, all the paths from A are
going to have that black height.
All the paths from C are going
to have that black height plus
one because there's a black node
in all the left paths,
and there is a black node in
all the right paths.
So, all the black links are the
same.
So, this preserves property
four.
And, it fixes property three
locally because B used to
violate A.
Now B does not violate
anything.
C, now, might be violated.
So, what we're going to do is
set x, our new value of x,
will be C.
So, it used to be B.
We move it up a couple levels.
Or, in the original tree,
yeah, we also move it up a
couple levels.
So, we're making progress up
the tree.
And then we continue this loop.
That's case one:
recolor, go up.
C may violate its parent in
which case we have to recurse.
So, we are recursing,
in some sense,
or continuing on C.
So now, let's look at case two.
So, I'm still,
in some sense,
defining this algorithm by
picture.
This is some nice,
graphical, programming
language.
So, let's draw case two.
Yeah, I forgot to mention
something about case one.
So, I drew some things here.
What do I actually know is
true?
So, let's look at the algorithm
in which I've now reversed.
But, we are assuming that we
are in category A.
In other words,
the parent is the left child of
the grandparent.
So, A is the left child of C.
That much I knew.
Therefore, y is the right
child.
D is the right child of C.
I didn't actually know whether
B was the right child or the
left child.
It didn't matter.
In case one,
it doesn't matter.
OK, so I should've said,
the children of A may be
reversed.
But it just said the same
picture.
OK, I thought of this because
in case two, we care.
So, case one:
we didn't really care.
In case two,
we say, well,
case two is up there,
is x the right child of the
parent, or the left child?
If it's the right child,
we are in case two.
So now, I can really know that
x here, which is B,
is the right child of A.
Before, I didn't know and I
didn't care.
Now, I'm assuming that it's
this way.
OK, y is still over here.
And now, now we know that y is
black.
So, y over here is a black
node.
So now, if I did the
contraction trick,
all of these nodes,
A, B, and C,
would conglomerate into one.
I only have four children.
That actually looks pretty
good.
y would not be involved because
it's black.
So, in this case,
we are going to do a left
rotation on A.
So, we take the edge,
we turn at 90°.
What we get is A on the left,
B on the right still.
It should preserve the in order
traversal, C up top still.
We have the y subtree hanging
off, as before.
We have one of the other three
subtrees hanging off B,
and the other two now hang off
A.
So, this is just a generic
rotation picture applied to this
edge.
OK, what that does,
is before we had a zigzag
between x and its grandparent.
Now, we have a zigzig.
We have a straight path between
x.
So, x is still down here.
I'm not changing x in this case
because after I do case two,
I immediately do case three.
So, this is what case three
will look like.
And now, I continue on to case
three.
So, finally,
here's case three.
And, this will finally complete
the insertion algorithm.
We have a black node,
C.
We have a red left child from
We have a red,
left, grandchild which is x.
And then, we have these black
subtrees all of the same black
height hanging off,
OK, which is exactly what we
had at the end of case two.
So, that definitely connects
over.
And remember,
this is the only case left in
category A.
Category A, we assumed that B
was the parent of x,
was the left child of the
grandparent, B or C.
So, we know that.
We already did the case one,
y over here as red.
That was case one.
So, we are assuming y is black.
Now, we look at whether x was
the left child or the right
child.
If it was the right child,
we made it into the left child.
x actually did change here.
Before, x was B.
Now, x is A.
OK, and then case three,
finally, is when x is the left
child of the parent who is the
left child of the grandparent.
This is the last case we have
to worry about.
And, what we do is another
rotation just like the last
rotation we did in the example.
That was case three.
So, we're going to do a right
rotate in this case of C.
And, we are going to recolor.
OK, so, what do we get?
Well, B now becomes the root.
And, I'm going to make it
black.
OK, remember,
this is the root of the
subtree.
There is other stuff hanging
off here.
I really should have drawn
extra parents in all of these
pictures.
There was somewhere in the
middle of the tree.
I don't know where.
It could be a rightward branch;
it could be a leftward branch.
We don't know.
C becomes the child of B,
and I'm going to make it a red
child.
A becomes a child of B,
as it was before,
keep it red.
And, everything else just hangs
off.
So, there were four subtrees
all at the same black height.
And, in particular,
this last one had y,
but we don't particularly care
about y anymore.
Now, we are in really good
shape because we should have no
more violations.
Before, we had a violation
between x and its parent,
A and B.
Well, A and B still have a
parent child relation.
But B is now black.
And, B is black,
so we don't care what its
parent looks like.
It could be red or black.
Both are fine.
We are no longer violating
property three.
We should be done in this case.
Property three is now true.
If you want,
you can say,
well, x becomes this node.
And then, the loop says,
oh, x is no longer red.
Therefore, I'm done.
We also need to check that
property four is preserved
during this process.
Again, it's not hard because of
the two-three-four tree
transformation.
If I contract all the red
things into their parents,
everything else has a constant,
I mean, every path in that tree
has the same length because they
have the same black length.
And over here,
that will still be true.
It's a little bit trickier
here, because we are recoloring
at the same time.
But, if you look at a path that
comes through this tree,
it used to go through a black
node, C, and then maybe some red
stuff; I don't care.
And then, it went through these
trees, which all have the same
black height.
So they were all the same.
Now, you comment,
and you go through a black node
called B.
And then, you go through some
red nodes.
It doesn't really matter.
But all the trees that you go
through down here have the same
black height.
So, every path through this
tree will have the same black
length, OK, if it starts from
the same node.
So, we preserve property four.
We fix property three.
That is the insertion
algorithm.
It's pretty long.
This is something you'll
probably just have to memorize.
If you try a few examples,
it's not so hard.
We can see that all the things
we did in this example were the
three cases.
The first step,
which unfortunately I had to
erase for space,
all we did was recolor.
We recolored ten,
and eight, and 11.
That was a case one.
Ten was the grandparent of 15.
Then, we looked at ten.
Ten was the violator.
It was a zigzag case relative
to its grandparent.
So, we did a right rotation to
fix that, took this edge,
and turned it so that ten
became next to seven.
That's the picture on the top.
Then, 18, which is the new
violator, with its grandparent,
is a zigzig.
They are both going in the same
direction.
And, now, we do one more
rotation to fix that.
That's really the only thing
you have to remember.
Recolor your grandparent if you
can.
Otherwise, make it zigzig.
And then, do one last rotation.
And recolor.
And that will work.
I mean, if you remember that,
you will figure out the rest on
any particular example.
We rotate ten over.
That better be black,
because in this case it's
becoming the root.
But, we will make it black no
matter what happens because
there has to be one black node
there.
If we didn't recolor at the
same time, we would violate
property four.
Why don't I draw that just for,
OK, because I have a couple
minutes.
So, if we just did the rotation
here, so let's say,
not the following,
we take B.
B is red.
This will give some intuition
as to why the algorithm is this
way, and not some other way.
And, C is black.
That's what we would have
gotten if we just rotated this
tree, rotated B,
or rotated C to the right.
So, these subtrees hang off in
the same way.
Subtrees look great because
they all have the same black
height.
But, you see,
there's a problem.
If we look at all the paths
starting from B and going down
to a leaf, on the left,
the number of black nodes is
whatever the black height is
over here.
Label that: black height,
whereas all the paths on the
right will be that black height
plus one because C is black.
So now, we've violated property
four.
So, we don't do this in case
three.
After we do the rotation,
we also do a recoloring.
So, we get this.
In other words,
we are putting the black node
at the top because then every
path has to go through that
node, whereas over here,
some of the nodes went through
the C.
Some of them went through A.
So, this is bad.
Also, we would have violated
property three.
But, the really bad thing is
that we are violating property
four over here.
OK, let me sum up a little bit.
So, we've seen,
if we insert into a red black
tree, we can keep it a red black
tree.
So, RB insert adds x to the set
to the dynamic set that we are
trying to maintain,
and preserves red blackness.
So, it keeps the tree a red
black tree, which is good
because we know then it keeps
logarithmic height.
Therefore, all queries in red
black trees will keep taking
logarithmic time.
How long does red black insert
take?
We know we are aiming for log n
time preparation.
We are not going to prove that
formally, but it should be
pretty intuitive.
So, cases two and three,
sorry, pointing at the wrong
place, cases two and three are
terminal.
When we do case three,
we are done.
When we do case two,
we are about to do case three,
and then we are done.
OK, so the only thing we really
have to count is case one
because each of these
operations, they are recoloring,
rotation, they all take
constant time.
So, it's a matter of,
how many are there?
Case one does some recoloring,
doesn't change the tree at all,
and moves x up by two levels.
We know that the height of the
tree is, at most,
two log n plus one.
So, the number of case ones is,
at most, log n plus one.
OK, so the number of case ones
is, at most, log n.
So, those take log n time.
And then, the number of case
twos and threes is,
at most, one for one of these
columns.
Well, together,
twos and threes is,
at most, two.
OK, so, log n time,
cool.
The other thing that is
interesting about red black
insertion is that it only makes
order one rotations.
So, most of the changes are
recolorings.
Case one just does recoloring,
no rotations.
Case two maybe does one
rotation.
Case three does one rotation if
you happen to be in those cases.
So, the number of rotations is,
at most, two.
It's either one or two in an
insertion.
It's kind of nice because
rotating a tree is a bit more
annoying than recoloring a tree.
Why?
Because if you had,
say, a data structure,
you have a search tree,
presumably, people are using
the search tree for something.
They are, like,
making queries.
For example,
the search tree represents all
the documents matching the word
computer in Google.
You've got the Google T-shirt
on here, so let's use a Google
reference.
You have the search tree.
It stores all the things
containing the word Google.
You'd like to search may be for
the ones that were modified
after a certain date,
or whatever it is you want to
do.
So, you're doing some queries
on this tree.
And, people are pummeling
Google like crazy with queries.
They get a zillion a second.
Don't quote me on that.
The number may not be accurate.
It's a zillion.
But, people are making searches
all the time.
If you recolor the tree,
people can still make searches.
It's just a little bit you are
flipping.
I don't care in a search
whether a node is red or black
because I know it will have
logarithmic height.
So, you can come along and make
your occasional updates as your
crawler surfs the Web and finds
changes.
And, recoloring is great.
Rotation is a bit expensive
because you have to lock those
nodes, make sure no one touches
them for the duration that you
rotate them, and then unlock
them.
So, it's nice that the number
of rotations is small,
really small,
just two, whereas the time has
to be log n because we are
inserting into a sorted list
essentially.
So, there is an n log n lower
bound if we do n insertions.
OK, deletion and I'm not going
to cover here.
You should read it in the book.
It's a little bit more
complicated, but the same ideas.
It gets the same bounds:
log n time order one rotations.
So, check it out.
That's red black trees.
Now, you can maintain data in
log n time preparation:
cool.
We'll now see three ways to do
it.