And so what I'm going to show
is that under those
circumstances,
it's easy for me to find hash
functions such that there are n
collisions.
That's the name of the game.
Figure out how can I make these
hash functions so that there are
no collisions.
So that's why I draw this with
so few elements here.
So here for example,
I have two elements and I have
a hash table size four here.
I have three elements.
I need a hash table size nine.
OK, if there are a hundred
elements, I need a hash table
size 10,000.
I'm not going to pick something
so there's likely that there's
anything of that size.
And then the fact that this
actually works and gives us all
the properties that we want,
that's part of the analysis.
So does everybody see that this
takes Order one worst case time
and what the basic structure of
it is?
These things,
by the way, are not in this
case prime.
I could always pick primes that
were close to this.
I didn't do that in this case.
Or I could use a universal hash
function that in fact would work
for things other than primes.
But I didn't do that for this
example.
We all ready for analysis?
OK, let's do some analysis
then.
And this is really pretty
analysis.
Partly as you'll see because
we've already done some of this
analysis.
So the trick is analyzing level
two.
That's the main thing that I
want to analyze,
to show that I can find hash
functions here that are going
to, when I map them into,
very sparsely,
into these arrays here,
that in fact,
such hash functions exist and I
can compute them in advance.
So that I have a good way of
storing those.
So here's the theorem we're
going to use.
My hash and keys into m equals
n squared slots using a random
hash function in a universal set
H.
Then the expected number of
collisions is less than one
half.
OK.
The expected number of
collisions I don't expect there
to be even one collision.
I expect there to be less than
half a collision on average.
And so, let's prove this,
so that the probability that
two given keys collide under h
is what?
What's the probability that two
given keys collide under h when
h is chosen randomly from the
universal set?
One over m.
Right?
That's the definition,
right, of, which is in this
case equal to one over n
squared.
So now how many keys,
how many pairs of keys do I
have in this table?
How many keys could possibly
collide with each other?
OK.
So that's basically just
looking at how many different
pairs of keys do I have to
evaluate this for.
So that's n choose two pairs of
keys.
n choose two pairs of keys.
So therefore,
the expected number of
collisions is while for each of
these n, not n over two.
n choose two pairs of keys.
The probability that it
collides is one in n squared.
So that's equal to n times n
minus one over two,
if you remember your formula,
times one in n squared.
And that's less than a half.
So for every pair of keys,
so those of you who remember
from 6.042 the birthday paradox,
this is related to the birthday
paradox a little bit.
But here I basically have a
large set, and I'm looking at
all pairs, but my set is
sufficiently big that the odds
that I get a collision is
relatively small.
If I start increasing it beyond
the square root of m,
OK, the number of elements,
it starts getting bigger in the
square root of m then the odds
of a collision go up
dramatically as you know from
the birthday paradox.
But if I'm less than,
if I'm really sparse in there,
I don't get collisions.
Or at least I get a relatively
small number expected.
Now I want to remind you of
something which actually in the
past I have just assumed,
but I want to actually go
through it briefly.
It's Markov's inequality.
So who remembers Markov's
inequality?
Don't everybody raise their
hand at once.
So Markov's inequality says the
following.
This is one of these great
probability facts.
For random variable x which is
bounded below by 0,
says the probability that x is
bigger than, greater than or
equal to any given value T is
less than or equal to the
expectation of x divided by T.
It's a great fact.
Doesn't happen if x isn't bound
below by 0.
But it's a great fact.
It allows me to relate the
probability of an event to its
expectation.
And the idea is in general that
if the expectation is going to
be small, then I can't have a
high probability that the value
of the random variable is large.
It doesn't make sense.
How could you have a high
probability that it's a million
when my expectation is one or in
this case we're going to apply
it when the expectation is a
half?
Couldn't happen.
And the proof follows just
directly on the definition of
expectation, and so I'mdoing
this for a discrete random
variable.
So the expectation by
definition is just the sum from
little x goes to 0 to infinity
of x times the probability that
my random variable takes on the
value x.
That's the definition.
And now it's just a question of
doing like the coarsest
approximation you can imagine.
First of all,
let me just simply throw away
all small terms that can be
greater to or equal to x equals
T to infinity of x times the
probability that x is equal to
little x.
So just throw away all the low
order terms.
Now what I'm going to do is
replace every one of these terms
is lower bounded by the value x
equals T.
So that's just the summation of
x equals T to infinity of T
times the probability that x
equals x.
OK.
Over x going from T larger.
Because these are only bigger
values.
And that's just equal then to
T, because I can pull that out,
and the summation of x equals T
to infinity of the probability
that x equals x is just the
probability that x is greater
than or equal to T.
And that's done because I just
divide by T.
So that's Markov's inequality.
Really dumb.
Really simple.
There are much stronger things
like Chebyshev bounds and
Chernoff bounds and things of
that nature.
But Markov's is like
unbelievably simple and useful.
So we're going to just apply
that as a corollary.
So the probability now of no
collisions, when I hash n keys
into n squared slots using a
universal hash function,
I claim is the probability of
no collisions is greater than or
equal to a half.
So I pick a hash function at
random.
What are the odds that I got no
collisions when I hashed those n
keys into n squared slots?
Answer.
Probability is I have no
collisions is at least a half.
Half the time I'm guaranteed
that there won't be a collision.
And the proof,
pretty simple.
The probability of no
collisions is the same as the
probability as,
sorry, is one minus the
probability that I have at most
one collision.
So the odds that I have at
least one collision,
the odds that I have at least
one collision,
probability greater than or
equal to one collision is less
than or equal to,
now I just apply Markov's
inequality with this.
So it's just the expected
number of collisions --
-- divided by one.
And that is by Markov's
inequality less than,
by definition,
excuse me, of expected number
of collisions,
which we've already shown,
is less than a half.
So the probability of at least
one collision is less than a
half.
The probability of 0 collisions
is at least a half.
So we're done here.
So to find a good level to hash
function is easy.
I just test a few at random.
Most of them out there,
OK, half of them,
at least half of them are going
to work.
So this is in some sense,
if you think about it,
a randomized construction,
because I can't tell you which
one it's going to be.
It's non-constructive in that
sense, but it's a randomized
construction.
But they have to exist because
most of them out there have this
good property.
So I'mgoing to be able to find
for each one of these,
I just test a few at random,
and I find one.
Test a few at random,
find one, etc.
Fill in my table there.
Because all that is
pre-computation.
And I'mgoing to find them
because the odds are good that
one exists.
So --
-- we just test a few at random.
And we'll find one quickly --
-- since at least half will
work.
I just want to show that there
exists good ones.
All I have to prove is that at
least one works for each of
these cases.
In fact, I've shown that
there's a huge number that will
work.
Half of them will work.
But to show it exists,
I would just have to show that
the probability was greater than
So to finish up,
we need to still analyze the
storage because I promised in my
theorem that the table would be
of size order n.
And yet now I've said there's
all of these quadratic-sized
slots here.
So I'mgoing to show that that's
order n.
So for level one,
that's easy.
We'll just choose the number of
slots to be equal to the number
of keys.
And that way the storage at
level one is just order n.
And now let's let n sub i be
the random variable for the
number of keys --
-- that hash to slot i in T.
OK, so n sub i is just what
we've called it.
Number of elements that slot
there.
And we're going to use m sub i
equals n sub i squared slots in
each level two table S sub i.
So the expected total storage --
-- is just n for level one,
order n if you want,
but basically n slots for level
one plus the expected value,
whatever I expect the sum of i
equals 0 to m minus one of theta
of n sub i squared to be.
Because I basically have to add
up the square for every element
that applies here,
the square of what's in there.
Who recognizes this summation?
Where have we seen that before?
Who attends recitation?
Where have we seen this before?
What's the --
We're summing the expected
value of a bunch of --
Yeah, what was that algorithm?
We did the sorting algorithm,
right?
What was the sorting algorithm
for which this was an important
thing to evaluate?
Don't everybody shout it out at
once.
What was that sorting algorithm
called?
Bucket sort.
Good.
Yeah.
We showed that the sum of the
squares of random variables when
they're falling randomly into n
bins is order n.
Right?
And you can also out of this
get a, as we did before,
get a probability bound.
What's the probability that
it's more than a certain amount
times n using Markov's
inequality.
But this is the key thing is
we've seen this analysis.
OK, we used it there in time,
so there's a little bit,
but that's one of the reasons
we study sorting at the
beginning of the term is because
the techniques of sorting,
they just propagate into all
these other areas of analysis.
You see a lot of the same kinds
of things.
And so now that you know bucket
sort clearly so well,
now you know that this without
having to do any extra work.
So you might want to go back
and review your bucket sort
analysis, because it's applied
now.
Same analysis.
Two places.
OK.
Good recitation this Friday,
which will be a quiz review and
we have a quiz next,
there's no class on Monday,
but we have a quiz on next
Wednesday.
OK, so good luck everybody on
the quiz.
Make sure you get plenty of
sleep.